Uhtred: I am uhtred, son of uhtred.
Sigefrid and Erik's army raided our camp
and kidnapped the lady aethelflaed.
You took my daughter into battle.
Uhtred: To learn her fate,
isent my loyal men, rypere and sihtric,
to beamfleot as spies.
I swear that this prize
will not be sold cheaply.
Wessex shall pay its share of silver
and if necessary its share of blood.
I will do what needs to be done.
What's your opinion
on paying a ransom for aethelflaed?
Not one I am prepared to say aloud.
I may need you.
Uhtred: Alfred sent us
to negotiate the ransom,
but secretly aethelflaed and Erik
had fallen in love.
Your husband's a fortunate man.
He is not the man
I would choose to be with.
I cannot let her go.
I will leave this place with Erik
or I will not leave at all.
Will you help me, please?
Uhtred: Destiny is all.
Pyrlig: What binds a man to a land?
You have a poor wretch,
toiling in the fields.
Burning in summer, shivering in winter.
He works all day every day
for nothing more than a loaf of bread
and a pot to piss in.
His children die of disease,
his wife dies giving him children.
Yet when that land is threatened,
something stirs. Why?
It is the land that feeds him.
More than that.
That the trees off the land
are used for shelter, fire.
More than that.
Is it love, father?
Oh, for the lord's sake,
can you not remain quiet?
But, yes, the bastard has it.
It can only be love.
It is a powerful thing.
Would you not agree, lord uhtred?
From wretch to warrior,
love gives a man strength,
often at the cost of his mind.
How much?
It's not a small amount, lord.
Three thousand pounds' weight of silver
and 500 pounds' weight of gold.
The first of the metal is to be
delivered by the next full moon,
the remaining amount one month later.
- That is an impossible amount.
- An absurd amount.
- That is the best price?
- It is, lord.
It is less than half
their first demand, lord.
What it is
is the entire wealth of wessex.
What it would buy is an army
to ensure the end of wessex and mercia.
Without the money...
What will happen to my daughter?
She's too valuable to simply kill, lord.
It would be humiliation.
She will be taken
to every town where Danes rule.
She will be paraded
before mocking crowds.
And men would pay to take their turn.
It is not just the life and reputation
of my daughter at stake here.
It is the dignity of wessex.
So many thousands of men must die, lord,
for the dignity of wessex?
Yes, odda.
A country is its history,
the sum of all its stories.
We are what our fathers made us.
Would you have me leave my descendants
the shameful tale
of how a Princess of wessex
was whored to the highest bidder?
Aelswith: That is a tale
that would overshadow all others.
The battle of ethandun
would become insignificant.
But, lord, if we pay this ransom,
I do not see how there will be a wessex.
The tale they tell will be of the king
who paid for the very army
that destroyed him.
- God would not allow that to happen.
- It's not god we are dealing with.
It is the northmen, the Danes!
Non-believers,
over whom we will triumph.
Should a great battle come of this,
we shall have men enough to face them.
I expect the fyrd of mercia
to be at our side.
Shall be there, lord.
The metal will be paid in full.
My daughter will be spared
and wessex shall avoid indignity.
But not the slaughter.
Odda, I hear your doubts
and I ask you to renew your faith.
Yes, lord.
Aethelred, you will join father beocca
and I before returning to mercia.
We must decide how best
to gather the ransom.
Yes, lord.
This cannot be how it ends.
Lord, you have said all you can say.
And bravely.
There's nothing more for you to do,
so I beg you... do nothing.
Lord.
Dagfinn, you can go.
- All of you.
- Yes, lord.
Do you have it?
- Is that enough?
- Yes.
Uhtred can read?
All of my father's ealdormen
can read and write.
Although the letters uhtred has written
you could count with one finger.
I will teach you.
What is to prevent him
from doing nothing?
We are asking him to risk everything
for no reward. Why should he come?
It is uhtred.
He will come. I swear.
He is with her? Again?
- He is.
- He cannot keep away from her.
Let us hope he does not take her
for his wife.
Or else our fortune is lost.
Guard: Is this true, huh?
Sigefrid!
Which woman is mine?
The ugly one.
We walked them for miles.
See they are fed and watered,
horses and slaves.
Erik: You are called sihtric?
Yes, lord. Good evening to you, lord.
Uhtred says you can be trusted.
So you will take him this letter.
This is a great responsibility.
Gisela: They will have no peace.
None.
I have told them the same.
But you will still help them?
I must. I have no choice.
If they escape,
then there will be no ransom paid.
No great army.
The men of wessex are saved, yes.
But what becomes of you? Of us?
Alfred will see it as a betrayal.
You will have broken your oath.
We leave.
Tomorrow I will make a sacrifice,
to keep you safe.
All of us.
Beocca: You give your name
to the scribe.
The sum of your contribution
will be written beside your name.
We're helping to free
the lady aethelflaed.
Man: We've got nothing to give!
Any man or woman found to be
hiding the value of their wealth
shall be punished!
All must pay their share.
You have the gratitude
of the king, of god.
Lord.
News, lord.
Speak.
Say to the king
exactly what you said to me. Exactly.
Lord, this man is from canterbury.
The northmen at beamfleot
are now crossing the river
and raiding directly into wessex.
They have taken my wife and daughters,
lord, the youngest just eight years.
While we do nothing, lord,
but gather halfpennies from the poor.
Father, you will take this man away.
Feed him and give him rest at an inn.
Odda, what is it you want?
Lord, he is just one man,
but he has lost two brothers
at ethandun,
two daughters and a wife
to the northmen,
and yet guards will knock at his door
and demand one third
of the little he has,
all to help preserve
the dignity of wessex.
This insolence is too much.
Then in six months' time
we shall ask for his life.
What I want, lord,
is for good sense to prevail.
By good sense I presume you mean
the death or humiliation of my daughter
and of the reputation of wessex.
Or we march, lord, and we fight.
If we march, they will kill her.
And she will be considered a martyr,
for wessex, lord, her dignity preserved!
And you would still have
the prince Edward. Your line is intact.
Odda, what has saved you
from outright banishment
is that you chose your king
over your own son.
- Lord, I chose wessex over my son.
- A traitor!
You should at least consider
doing the same.
What am I to do with you?
Your injury and your appetite for wine
have robbed us both of your worth.
You no longer serve a purpose.
Then with your permission, lord,
I shall return to my estate
and my wife at Devonshire,
whilst it is still a Saxon estate.
That would be for the best.
Should you be needed
you will be sent for.
http://hiqve.com/
They buy the very swords
that will slay them.
Lord, good evening.
I am a moth to the flame.
Yes, it is becoming
a significant amount.
Significant is the word, lord,
in its size and its effect.
- Your father...
- The king?
He would have done the same.
Pay such a ransom
for his offspring, lord? I doubt it.
I was a great disappointment to him...
Which I regret.
But if you were not a disappointment,
aethelwold, I may have had you killed.
For the good of wessex.
Never doubt it.
Every decision I make is for my country.
Yes, lord.
I understand completely.
Lord odda.
You will set tongues wagging,
drinking with the peasants.
Let them wag if it please them.
You asked me some days ago if I agree
with the payment of a ransom.
I do not.
If I had an army to call upon,
a fyrd to raise,
I would prove it.
But I have not.
I appear to have joined you, lord.
He's been there for part of the day
and all of the night.
He's a good man and I worry
that it will damage his reputation.
If he can stand
it can only enhance his reputation.
Uhtred: Lord.
May we join you?
Is he here still or has he already left?
Aethelwold.
Um... no, he is long gone, lord.
- Perhaps you have drunk enough, lord.
- It is entirely possible.
Though the ale they brew here is weak,
upon the orders of Alfred.
You're joking, lord.
- What, that's true?
- It is, yes.
It is so a man can work the next day
and swords remain in scabbards.
But they must not.
Somebody needs a bed.
- You will stay with him.
- And do what?
If he needs to piss or spew,
you'll fetch him a bucket.
I have a plan,
though it is likely I will die.
What is this plan, lord? Tell me.
I will raise the Devonshire fyrd.
Against the king's wishes, lord?
That is not something he would forgive.
Lord!
Uhtred: He will go nowhere.
And you will go nowhere and you will say
nothing about what you've just heard.
- Yes, lord.
- You mean, "no, lord."
- I'll...
- Do as I say.
So... what does it say?
Erik has enough oath-men to crew a ship.
Three nights before the first
of the metal is to be delivered,
we make our way downriver to beamfleot.
We kill the men
who stand guard over the ships.
Erik and aethelflaed sail away.
And wessex is saved.
- How many guards?
- Eight or ten, on the shore.
- That is all?
- Yes.
- It's as simple as that?
- Erik is in command.
His men guard aethelflaed,
his ship is ready and waiting.
It begins as simple.
What happens is fate.
Why go by river and not horseback?
If we go with the tides it'll be faster,
and to escape we row across river.
They will follow you.
They will follow aethelflaed.
She's the silver.
Father pyrlig.
Lord, you came from nowhere,
like the devil himself.
You are leaving us?
I am. I've invited myself to Devonshire
with the lord odda.
I'm looking fowvard to cooling my feet
in the blue waters of the sea.
You're spying for Alfred.
Of course I'm spying for Alfred.
I despise the sea.
Should odda decide to do anything rash,
you will tell him to hold fast?
And why should he listen to me?
Do you have a reason
you would like to share?
And he's behind you.
Lord.
Did you sleep well?
Uhtred. I did, soundly.
Though I'm not sure how I found my bed.
You were a little worse for ale, lord,
but no bother.
I'm glad to hear it.
You spoke of a plan.
- I did?
- Mm-hm.
Am ito be reminded?
The men of Devonshire.
They should remain in the fields.
I must have been very drunk.
- It can be the only explanation, lord.
- Yes.
You swear?
On my life.
I have no memory of it whatsoever.
Lord odda, I say this to you
as your friend.
Do nothing.
If I do not see you again,
uhtred of bebbanburg,
I wish you good luck.
Wherever fate may take you.
Thank you, lord.
Should we pray, lord? Together?
Am I being selfish
in wanting to spare aethelflaed?
Lord, you were a father
before you were a king.
But your reasons stand.
She is wessex.
She is the blood, the heart
and the spirit of wessex.
She cannot be humiliated.
Dagfinn!
Dagfinn. Where is she?
Lord?
Where is she?
Sigefrid: Now it is clear.
Each man has a right to see her.
And every man will guard her
with his life!
She is our wealth.
She belongs to us all!
Dear god! Who might they be?
They are the Devonshire fyrd,
father pyrlig.
You are here as Alfred's spy
and will go no further.
You will get down from your horse and
walk back to Winchester with your news.
What news is that, lord?
What do you mean?
You will tell the king that odda is
marching against the enemies of wessex.
He can either march to halt me or march
to join me. It does not matter which.
Once the northmen at beamfleot
see an army, a battle will follow.
Please, lord. Think what you are doing.
You are making traitors of your men.
The men you see
are here to die for their king,
not betray him.
They know nothing of Alfred's weakness.
But, uhtred, lord...
Did he not ask you to do nothing?
You will get down from your horse
and you will return to Winchester.
And if I refuse?
Now, father pyrlig.
Lord, I beg you...
Think again!
Thank you.
What's your name?
I asked for ten, dagfinn.
How are we supposed to scrub down a ship
with three men?
The men refuse to leave the hall, lord.
Refuse?
They say they are protecting their
wealth, under the orders of sigefrid.
Who said this? Name them.
Your brother has called for more guards,
lord, until the metal comes.
Erik.
You have been sleeping at the river.
Why?
You have made a fool of me.
You have humped her enough.
You have fed and washed her enough.
Do not allow the men to see
what I know for certain.
You have grown too fond of her.
It is not her arse you want.
It is herself. It will pass.
You have shamed me.
What I have done... is protect you.
Erik, my brother, what is happening
around us is your plan.
And it is a fine plan, to give up
lundene and take the Princess,
to ransom her for ships
full of gold and silver,
on which we will build an army
that no man will want to face
and every man will want to join.
This... will be our land.
All of it.
I will not allow us to fail.
Sigefrid: Haesten!
A guard every ten paces.
Yes, lord.
Forgive me, lord.
It's not that the men
do not want to serve you.
It's that they do not know
where your loyalties lie.
Oh, sweet Jesus, I cannot run.
Please let them be Saxon.
Father pyrlig!
Lord! Thank the heavens!
A friendly face.
Are you lost, father?
Not lost, but abandoned, lord.
I'm returning to Winchester
with an important message for Alfred.
We're going to see Alfred.
Climb onto the cart.
You can help guard mercia's ransom.
God bless you, lord,
saviour of my blistered feet.
Lord?
Osferth?
Can I say to you that I'm afraid?
I wear a sword
but barely know how to use it.
I pray that when battle comes...
I will not fail you.
Osferth, at times we're all afraid.
Courage is finding the will
to overcome your fear. Nothing more.
Perhaps we'll find you an axe.
It requires less skill than a sword.
But you must find the courage.
Yes, lord.
Thank you, lord.
- Lord.
- Lord king.
Father pyrlig.
Aethelred and aldhelm I was expecting.
It is odda, lord.
Prior to leaving Winchester,
he sent a man, some man,
with word to raise
the fighting men of Devonshire.
He has now met them on the road, lord.
- With the intention of doing what?
- He is marching against beamfleot.
Yes, lord. He is.
Damn him.
Isay damn him.
Lord, are we to stop him?
We have no choice but to stop him.
We must stop him.
Lord, may I ask, where is uhtred?
He was not beside odda,
if that is your meaning
and it cannot have been uhtred
who carried the message to Devonshire.
Aethelred, you have how many men?
Over 50, lord, household guard.
I can send for many more.
You will do that.
Rest your men and horses,
but you will join me and my own guard
before first light.
If we are to halt odda,
we must march day and night
and we must pray.
Aethelflaed: Dear lord god in heaven.
Grant me the strength
to survive this ordeal.
Give me the courage
to overcome these hardships.
And instil within me...
Faith.
Faith in those I love...
For they will not abandon me.
Lord, I beg of you.
- Amen.
You! With me!
Finan: Twenty guards.
Sihtric, you said there'd be
no more than eight or ten.
He cannot count.
No, lord. It has never been
more than ten men.
Rypere's group will strike
first from the water.
They look to the river and then...
We kill them.
But, lord, we are just 11.
Rypere.
- Two each.
- We attack as soon as it's dark.
Brother.
May I speak?
I've something to say!
I've something to say to each of you.
You will be disappointed to know
that this woman here is now mine!
No man is to touch her.
Not with his hands
and most certainly not with his cock!
She belongs to me!
You weakened me, brother.
It should have been me who took
the Princess and put her in the cage.
Yes. You are right.
I... did not think.
You never think.
Because I have you to think for me.
It is three nights before
the first of the silver will arrive.
We must be ready.
Tomorrow there will be no more ale,
no more games,
no more fighting over women!
But that is tomorrow.
Tonight... we drink
as if there were no tomorrow!
Woman: Lady.
Have faith.
It is tonight.
Soldier: What's happening?
Get the shields!
Watch your backs!
Rypere!
Finan!
You! That's enough!
He's not your kill!
That is not how you wet your sword!
Find your courage!
Or find your cross and go back
to the monastery as Alfred would wish.
We shall rest, for a short time only.
Take rest! Stay alert!
I want watchmen front and rear.
Feed the horses and yourselves.
Odda is out there. He is near.
As is aethelflaed, lord.
We are here for odda.
Erik should have been here
by now.
Something's wrong. Why increase
the number of guards? For what reason?
- Do we care?
- They are dead.
We go to the fortress.
- We do?
- We came to free aethelflaed.
- We came to kill the guards.
- Bastard, you will say nothing.
The guards will soon
be discovered missing.
And when they are, it's over.
We cannot wait.
But, lord, we have lost half our men.
And there are hundreds of them,
both inside and outside the fortress.
And a few more men will not be noticed.
We go to the fortress.
Uhtred. She said that you would come.
I dared not believe her,
but you are here.
Tell me what has changed.
In truth?
It is hopeless.
I have no crew for my ship.
But the first task is not
how we escape beamfleot,
it is how we free aethelflaed.
She hangs where every man can see her.
Lord, I enjoy a fight as much as
the next idiot, but this is beyond us.
She's inside the hall?
Inside the hall, inside a cage,
surrounded by men.
Warriors.
We must first get rid of the men.
We do it now.
Fire. Fire! Fire!
Outside, now! Quickly!
Put the fire out!
Find something to carry water!
Six men stay with the Princess!
Lock the doors!
Aethelflaed: Uhtred!
Clapa, sihtric, the cage.
Come on!
Sihtric: This is
one bastard lock to break!
Get it done before we burn!
So we've cleared the hall of men, lord.
Now how do we clear the yard?
They will follow the silver.
Haesten: Up to the ramparts!
Go! Move!
Where did this begin?
Lady, quickly. Run for the rear gate.
Do not stop!
Princess! Stop her!
After her!
Sigefrid: Stop her! After her!
Where is he?
- Erik! Where is he?
- Lord, I do not know.
I have not seen him outside of the hall!
Erik!
Erik. Do not do this.
Do not dare to do this!
Brother, please let me have
this one chance.
I cannot let her go.
She is our fortune!
She is our reputation!
If it's reputation you want,
you can begin with killing me.
Uhtred, no!
If you want your fortune,
you must kill me.
Clapa, the cage!
Uhtred! Get her out of here!
Aethelflaed: Erik, no!
We need to go.
Aethelflaed!
You...
You did this.
You have killed us both.
Uhtred: With me!
Clapa! With us!
Clapa!
We go!
She's escaping with uhtred!
I want them dead!
Everyone after them!
Odda: Lord, I'm grateful to see you,
as are my men.
I've told each one of them
we are here on the orders of Alfred.
Lord, as you appear to have
marched an army to their door,
I doubt the northmen will believe
you are not here to fight.
Why, odda?
Why?
For wessex, lord.
Only for wessex.
Lord, the sky!
It must be beamfleot.
It is an army, lord!
It's odda. It's odda's army!
- Steapa: Stand ready!
- Aldhelm: Stand ready!
Good god. I think it is uhtred.
Alfred: It is her.
It is aethelflaed. They have her.
Lord!
We are being pursued by sigefrid.
The Danes are low in number
and disorganized.
My advice is that we kill them all.
Steapa, put a guard around my daughter.
- Father, I want to fight them!
- You will do as I say!
Erik is dead, lord. Sigefrid will have
no mind to negotiate nor wait.
He wants Saxon blood. We have to fight.
Shield wall, lord.
Only you can give the order.
Lord, we only have a fraction
of their number.
We cannot win.
I am ready.
Lord?
To die.
It will be today.
Who is with me?
Who is ready for glory?
Or Valhalla!
- Shield wall!
Shield wall!
Faster! Move!
Uhtred: Faster!
Shield! Shield!
Fill the breach!
Close the wall!
Sigefrid: Princess!
I see you, Princess!
And I will kill you!
I will have your head and your tits!
Sigefrid!
Princess!
Sigefrid: Princess!
Uhtred: Sigefrid!
I'm here!
Face me!
Aethelflaed: Leave us.
Uhtred, there are no words.
Then say nothing.
You answered my call
at the risk of everything.
I only wish he did survive, lady.
Erik is still with me.
And perhaps within me.
And if, over the coming months,
my husband should think
what you are thinking,
it would be a great comfort, uhtred,
to know that I could
call upon you again,
should I ever need to.
Of course.
Do you swear?
You are the man I trust most,
uhtred of bebbanburg.
I swear.
I swear, lady.
Then I shall dare to kiss you.
It seems you have made a habit
of rescuing wessex.
Odda claims that you believed
you were acting upon my orders, uhtred.
What will happen to him?
There will be a trial.
And then you will kill him.
Treachery cannot be ignored.
He's a good man.
He is my friend...
And a traitor.
May I go, lord?
You are free to go.
As my oath-man.
I would have liked to have seen
my land of Devonshire once more.
How did it look?
Devonshire was beautiful, lord.
God be with you.
Uhtred: What binds a man to his land?
What power within
allows him to give his life
to preserve his land and the lives
of the families who work it?
It can only be love.
It will not be written
that the lord odda saved wessex,
but that is the story I will tell.
That he gave his life
to save the lives of many
and ensured king Alfred of wessex
became more powerful than ever.
Sigefrid had been defeated.
But Alfred knew as well as I
that the Danes were sure to return.
Shackled by oaths
to both wessex and mercia,
it seems fate has made my sword Saxon,
even though in my heart I remain a Dane.
I, uhtred, son of uhtred,
shall be the warrior
to bind kingdom to kingdom.
Honour-bound to forge
Alfred's dream of an england.
But one day my sword
will belong to bebbanburg.
Destiny is all.
http://hiqve.com/