Uhtred: I am uhtred, son of uhtred.
When I was a child my sister thyra
was attacked by sven
and he looked at her nakedness.
Our father exacted his revenge.
Then I shall only take his one eye.
Ragnar senior:
Kjartan, you are banished.
Uhtred: So years later, kjartan burned
down our home and killed our parents.
I thought thyra dead.
I will not stand by and have
everything that's mine taken from me.
But she lives,
held in chains
just as I was held in chains.
She will not die a slave.
She will not share halig's fate.
Under orders of king Alfred,
my brother ragnar found and freed me.
Seeking revenge for my friend,
for my own captivity,
and gisela being taken from me,
I killed the Abbot eadred,
a man of god.
My price was to renew my oath
of allegiance to Alfred of wessex.
Destiny is all.
- Gisela: Uhtred?
- Uhtred: Mmm?
When you go to eofenlvic,
will you kill my brother?
Are you asking if I will,
or are you telling me to do it?
The first one.
I have sworn to Alfred
that guthred will not be harmed.
I want to go with you.
You might return to find me
claimed by another, like vacant land.
Gisela, no.
Alfred could marry me off
to some ealdorman
and you won't be here to stop it.
What is funny?
It would not be the first time
a king has tried.
You're not coming with me,
- it would be too dangerous for you.
- It is for you too.
I could not...
I could not bear it,
to have you taken from me again.
What's this? You are leaving without me?
Brida has gone already.
She is gathering my men.
Whatever is left of them.
- You will meet them where?
- Loidis.
I'd ask you to come with me, but I hear
you have been making more of your oaths.
I will be with you.
- Our plan doesn't change.
- You belong to Alfred.
Our plan doesn't change.
Alfred sends me to kill Erik
and sigefrid.
If I succeed,
then guthred will be in my debt.
And I will demand the use of his men.
I have men.
Ragnar: And we have our own war,
we do not need guthred's.
How many men?
- Enough to take dunholm?
- Guthred made you a slave.
And by swearing to Alfred,
you remain a slave.
Why?
I have my reasons.
I would like to hear those reasons.
I did not forget what guthred did to me.
But if it means we have
a greater chance of killing kjartan,
if it means we find our sister,
then I will do what Alfred asks.
Kjartan falls, by my sword.
He will, brother. He will.
Aethelwold: Lord?
You asked for me.
Alfred: I did.
The king should be at the centre.
Alfred: Surrounded by his enemies.
Alfred: I am sending uhtred to eofenlvic,
to aid guthred against the brothers
who would take the city for themselves.
I want you to go with him.
Steapa shall accompany you.
Remain at his side.
Lord, forgive me, but I do not see
what need uhtred would have of me.
It is not uhtred's need
that concerns me. It is mine.
Guthred's misjudgments
have divided northumbria.
I sent uhtred to re-assert guthred's
authority, I am sending you to remind
"king" guthred of his debt
and obligations to wessex.
Surely a letter would suit the purpose?
A letter is constant,
whereas I shall merely come and go.
Think of this as reward, aethelwold.
You have proven yourself
both in battle and within my witan.
You have also sought
greater responsibilities.
In wessex, yes, responsibilities in
mercia, perhaps, but northumbria?!
Lord, they are almost Scots.
Should I turn my hair red?
You will remind uhtred of his oaths,
but above all, you will reassure
our northern king
that in spite of what has passed,
my commitment to his prosperity
has not waned.
Eoferwic must remain Christian.
You do me a great honor.
You shall be my eyes, ears and voice,
aethelwold.
Hmm, a bold response.
Yes, father, I thought so.
Take this.
It is the symbol of my kingship.
Alfred: Bear it with authority.
Make yourself ready.
Consider how you spend this time.
Tomorrow, you're my errands man.
- Father beocca?
- Uhtred.
Thank you.
- Come to make your peace with god?
- Come to find you.
You weren't in your room.
Nor the brothel.
Well, I have been very busy.
These are for guthred?
Yes.
The fortunes of kings.
Their failures are rewarded with gifts.
Father.
- Is something wrong?
- I need you to marry me, to gisela.
What?
Uhtred: I want us to make our pledges
before I ride for eofenlvic.
Mildrith has joined the order,
I am free to marry.
Do you have Alfred's blessing?
It is not Alfred I wish to marry!
Beocca, this cannot wait.
- You love her?
- I do.
I feel you are too fond of love.
Nevertheless, bring her here.
But quietly.
We need to be quick and discreet.
Quick and discreet...
We are off to the great north,
you and I.
I am to be Alfred's errand boy.
He wants me away from Winchester...
- Aethelwold, I am not listening...
- He wants me dead even.
That is the plan, I know it!
Beocca: "One may be overpowered,
two can defend themselves.
A cord of three
is not so quickly broken."
Now that you are bound together,
uhtred and gisela,
I can declare you man and wife.
Now I will never be
taken from you.
Ragnar rides with them, lord?
Odda: A Dane?
You have doubts, odda?
Alfred: Then we shall air them.
Lord. Should he survive,
I fear uhtred will not return.
You believe he will break his oath?
No, I believe bebbanburg will have
a greater pull than wessex.
Should he rid northumbria of these
northmen he will look towards kjartan,
- his blood feud.
- Yes, but that is no bad thing.
Lord, should he defeat kjartan,
then who holds the power in northumbria?
Uhtred and ragnar? Pagans.
There is that risk, but firstly,
uhtred is a warrior, a viking even,
- he will forever be restless.
- Perhaps.
And secondly, should he turn
his attention to bebbanburg
and indeed to northumbria as a whole,
then steapa is under instruction
to kill him.
When will we have sight of eofenlvic?
I have never ridden for so long
nor so far.
Have you a sore arse, lord?
I have a sore everything.
I need a woman to rub and bathe me.
We will be stopping soon enough.
At eoferwic?
We ride first for loidis.
What awaits us at loidis?
We shall see.
Need I remind you
that first and foremost
our purpose here is the king's business.
Nothing has changed
but our path, beocca.
We shall see.
Brida.
You brought friends?
Brida: They serve Alfred.
Do we have men?
Some.
This way.
Well, that was a warm greeting.
Uhtred.
Uhtred, you were sent north to aid
guthred, not to go chasing revenge.
Perhaps I plan to do both, father.
I think I know what you plan. Uhtred,
revenge will not bring you peace.
Only death.
Father beocca, you will have me kill for
Alfred but not for myself, why is that?
And what business does Alfred have
with northumbria?
God's business.
Ragnar: I didn't think
so many would come.
Ragnar!
Rollo.
What makes you think we're here for you?
Brida: Guthred is seen as weak
and friendless.
These men won't fight their brothers
for a turd.
We need the turd's army
to take dunholm.
So why not kill the northmen,
then kill the turd, take eofenlvic
and its army for yourself?
- The woman's got a point.
- No, she does not have a point.
Those are the words of a traitor.
I don't want eoferwic.
All I want is kjartan's heart on the end
of my sword and to see my sister.
We will need guthred's army.
Brida: I promised these men silver
and the glory of avenging your father.
Don't dishonor them by getting them
killed for guthred, the turd.
0h, ragnar, your woman's got
the balls of a bear. I like her.
- She's right.
- Beocca: What do you mean she's right?
Beocca, she's right.
These men are here for ragnar.
We can't ask them to die
for the like of guthred.
Isn't it what Danes do, fight?
- We cannot face the brothers alone.
- Why not?
Finan, there is bravery
and then there is stupidity.
The northmen have a camp, do they not?
Not a fortress but an open camp.
If it is sigefrid and Erik we must kill,
then let us do just that.
We kill them while they're sleeping.
Shadow-walkers.
Rider: Open the gates!
They are here. In northumbria.
Uhtred and ragnar.
How many men?
They had barely 50 at loidis.
They will find others.
They will go to their poxy king guthred.
I want every man aware and ready.
No drunkenness till it's done,
no matter how long.
Do you believe they will attack?
Place rocks, wood and fire
on the ramparts.
We should hunt them down now,
before they can turn their 50 men
into 500 men.
Fifty men can win a battle in the open,
but no army of any size
can breech this fortress.
If uhtred and ragnar's wish
is to kill me,
they can die trying at my gates.
Was I not heard?
Father, what can I do?
Go to your wild whore.
Tell her she need not feed her hounds.
Thyra?
I told you to stay out.
Your brother ragnar is here,
in northumbria.
Sven: He will attack.
My father demands
that you let the hounds go hungry.
Sven: But if you don't...
If you do not want that,
- I can tell father that...
- I have no brother.
I have no brother.
Get out.
Get out!
I see three on watch.
The rest will be
huddled inside their furs.
There could be more,
behind the tents, sitting low.
I don't have a good feeling about this.
Which tents are full, which are empty.
Ragnar: And in which tent is sigefrid
and which is Erik?
We are blind.
Aethelwold: Tafl.
The game, tafl.
The king is positioned
at the centre of the pieces.
I would say that tent there is the king.
From any other mouth
it would make perfect sense.
It is perfect sense.
- I will go in alone.
- Aethelwold: I think you should.
No, we go in as agreed, together.
We cannot risk the both of us
being killed.
Yes, we can.
This is for Alfred.
You must save your sword for kjartan.
If it is for Alfred, I will go with you.
Finan: And me.
It was my bastard plan.
And I shall wish you all
the best of luck.
- If you get caught?
- Do nothing.
Ragnar, think only of our blood feud
and of thyra.
I hope you're light on your feet,
big man.
http://hiqve.com/
You want to kill me, uhtred ragnarson?
- That was the plan.
- You don't like me?
I can be a funny man.
Raiders! Raiders!
Raiders!
Steapa: Necessary.
Stand clear! Let them see me!
Let them all see me!
They will be
slaughtered where they stand.
And you with them.
You save your sword for kjartan.
Erik, I swear I'll kill him
and be damned what follows!
No one is to move, no one! Stand still!
Sigefrid: Kill him!
Kill him. Kill him!
No one is to so much as
raise their sword!
Uhtred! You will spare him!
Steady your men!
Back! Hold!
Uhtred, you will spare my brother.
Name your price.
Kill him, Erik! Kill him, I say!
Erik! Haesten!
Sigefrid, there will be another day,
- another time!
- Kill him!
Uhtred, name your price!
It will be done, I swear.
I give you my word.
Kill him and you kill yourself.
- Your word?!
- I swear! Believe me!
You will take one ship
and you will leave northumbria.
One ship! You will not return!
For my brother's life, this is done.
And I swear that I will kill you,
uhtred ragnarson. This is not finished!
I see you are a funny man.
We are here at the request
of Alfred of wessex!
The king will wish to see us!
Uhtred: Open the doors.
- Beocca: Uhtred, I will speak first.
- Uhtred: Father, you will say nothing.
Uhtred.
Guthred: Father beocca, I...
I had heard that you were close.
I... I had not realized how close.
- Lord, king Alfred has sent us here...
- Father beocca!
You will allow king guthred
to speak first.
I had also heard
that you had been recovered, uhtred.
I am glad,
believe me.
Guthred: Well, if you are here
to kill me,
I don't blame you, I would kill me too.
But it would be a mistake,
another mistake.
Lord guthred, I am lord aethelwold.
I come in king Alfred's stead.
We have gifts...
Uhtred: Sigefrid's sword hand.
The brothers won't trouble you again.
They are... dead?
In return you will give me your army.
- You will ready them to march.
- But...
You will do as I ask, guthred,
or I shall kill you.
He does not know what he says, lord.
Steapa, no.
I will kill you
and take every consequence.
What you did to me,
What you did to halig,
I could never forget.
I shall never forgive.
Uhtred: You will ready your men
to march.
How do I know that
the brothers are gone?
How do I know that this hand
belongs to sigefrid?
Like your uncle,
I would have preferred a head,
- two heads...
- Another word, lord,
and it will be your own head.
You will do as my brother asks or I will
take eofenlvic and the army for myself.
Beocca!
The king has a decision to make.
He's either with us
or against us.
Huh.
You are lucky. Nothing's broken.
It'll hurt wielding your sword, though.
Well, we cannot wait for the wounded.
You'll not have to wait
for the wounded.
We should kill him.
Hmm-mm-mm.
Guthred, the turd king.
- Do you never tire of menace?
- I do not.
If we are successful in taking dunholm,
who gets to keep it?
Guthred. Guthred, naturally.
He has eoferwic.
Ragnar should have it.
Beocca: It is Alfred's wish
that it goes to guthred.
Alfred has never set
one foot in northumbria,
it's not his decision to make.
Kjartan built dunholm
on the blood of ragnar the fearless.
It belongs to his blood-son, ragnar.
As long as my sword finds kjartan's
heart, I do not care.
Brida: I care.
- The arseling is right... for once.
- Aethelwold: He is wrong.
Uhtred, you say Alfred has never
set foot in northumbria. He has no need.
We are here, all of us,
to do his bidding.
And he knows how each of us will think,
what each of us will do.
Eofenlvic can never be the seat of power
in northumbria
whilst dunholm remains strong,
and so he allows uhtred to attack.
He allows nothing. I'm here
because it's my business to be here...
Uhtred, you are his man.
You more than anyone will bring about
his dream of an england.
Alfred's wish is for guthred to become
the one true lord of the north,
and you will make that happen.
- I say it as I now see it.
- You have shit in your eye.
I see it as a king would see it.
Male: He was crying like a baby
so I just thumped him.
Guthred: Uhtred.
Uhtred, will you join me, please?
Guthred: Please?
I am a little afraid of you,
uhtred of bebbanburg.
Envious.
I am king because the Abbot
claimed to have seen my face in a dream.
But it was your face
that he assumed to be king
and...
I feared that you would take
my newly found power.
I gave you my word.
Guthred: You did.
But you made me a slave.
- Guthred: Yes.
- Hmm.
Yes, but, in my defense,
I was meant to kill you.
- I spared your life...
- Uhtred! No!
You were my friend and I betrayed you.
My sister is well?
She's my wife.
Good, good.
I shall write to Alfred,
I shall inform him that...
That your journey to dunholm
is my instruction.
And I do hope that you can one day find
a place in your heart to forgive me.
I still consider you my greatest friend.
What did he say?
He said dunholm is yours, brother.
Sihtric?
- Lord.
- You lied to me.
Lord, I... I would never...
You told me dunholm has no weaknesses.
Yet last time I was there,
I saw a door along the east wall.
Access to a water spring.
Yes, lord, but you could never bring
an army through it.
I would not be bringing an army.
This is madness.
The rightful king of wessex helping to
avenge the death of a big, hairy viking.
It would make a good song.
Should you die, aethelwold,
I shall have it written.
Oh. Oh.
Shh. This is where we part.
Ragnar: We will show ourselves only when
we know the east door has been opened.
We will attack.
Then it is up to you to save us.
We will be theirs to slaughter.
Lord. May the gods be with you.
Er, god. May god be with him, us.
You just watch over ragnar.
Good luck, little brother.
See you all in dunholm.
We move quickly,
we must be in place before dawn.
Sihtric: This path
is fit for goats only.
Be quiet and watch
where you're placing your feet.
Bless you.
That ram we have dragged,
it will not work.
It will not force open the gates.
But it will work...
In its own way.
We rest. We wait.
Go on. Now.
This will be the day,
kjartan or Valhalla.
The day of days.
Ragnar.
Brida: Their signal.
It begins.
Now?
Shield! Wall!
Warriors at the north gate!
Guard: Warriors at the north gate!
To the end.
Every man to the ramparts!
Ragnar: Keep together!
Ragnar: Stay close!
Back!
Ragnar: Back.
Kjartan: Use the fire!
Burn the bastards!
- Uhtred: When we attack, steapa...
- Steapa: I know, lord, to the gate.
Guard: Behind you, behind you!
Hild! Hild!
Courage. We stand.
Every man is to stand.
Lord! Breach!
With me now!
Steapa! To the gate!
Kill them! To the gate!
We must get to the gate! Kill them!
It is to the end!
Next group, go! Glory or Valhalla!
Protect the gate!
Uhtred: Full force!
Uhtred: Full force, ragnar!
Pull back! Pull back!
Pull back!
Kjartan!
Where are you?!
Shield!
Wall!
Pull back! Come on!
Thyra.
Thyra, please. Please.
Please.
Sven: Thyra.
Thyra: Kill...
Thyra!
Sven!
Ragnar: Kjartan, you are beaten.
Either you die alone,
or together with all your men.
What is it to be?
You wish to fight me, baby ragnar?
No, I wish to kill you.
Drop your weapons, it's over.
- Shield!
- Brida: Ragnar, no.
No, ragnar, don't give him the chance.
Burn the bastard! Ragnar!
- Uhtred: Brida!
- You and me.
Move!
We make this square.
Your sister made a good whore!
Kjartan: She still does!
Only now we have to tie her down
to keep her from scratching,
when we hump her all night.
Come on, ragnar!
- Ragnar!
- I killed your father!
- Brida: Get up!
- Uhtred: Get up!
- Ragnar!
- I burned your mother!
Go, ragnar!
No! No, give me my sword.
For Valhalla you must give me my sword.
- I won't beg you!
- Die.
Give me my sword!
Yes!
Stop. Stop.
Ragnar.
Ragnar, it's over! It's over!
Uhtred: Shh... shh...
It's thyra.
You left me. Both of you, you left me.
Thyra, no.
I swear, we did not know you were alive.
You are no better than the bastards
who whored me.
Thyra, please.
The price for my life is yours.
Thyra.
I forbid it.
Beocca: Please.
Please...
Let me help you.
I am a friend.
I have not seen you
fight like that before.
That wasn't fighting, that was...
Well, killing him was not enough.
It can never be enough.
But it's done.
We've honored them.
Yes, so, er,
what now? Bebbanburg?
Wessex.
It must be wessex or steapa will have
instruction to kill me, I'm sure.
I need peace for a time.
I need my woman.
And what of thyra?
Whatever else, she's safe.
I will not hurt you, I promise.
You do not know me,
but I have known your brother, uhtred,
since he was a small boy.
I am beocca.
This place is ragnar's now.
You have no need to hide.
He and uhtred have wanted for so long
to find you.
You have shown
incredible strength, thyra.
I would say god-given.
Bless you.
Stay.
Uhtred, he... sa... saved me once...
Before, from sven,
when he was your little boy.
Yes, he would do that.
http://hiqve.com/