I am uhtred, son of uhtred.
Lady aethelflaed has followed
her father's wishes
and married aethelred,
the lord of mercia,
bringing king Alfred's dream
of an england ever closer.
Lord, love should be gentle and kind.
In a happier union, father beocca
has married my sister, thyra.
Excuse me, lord uhtred.
I am osferth.
You are Alfred's bastard.
After failing to convince me
to join them,
the northmen brothers,
Erik and sigefrid,
have taken the city of lundene.
You say you are sworn, yet you
float into daneland and back again.
How am I to trust you?
Alfred put aethelred
in command of his armies...
Tomorrow we ride.
I would like you to travel with me.
To battle?
And we were sent
to take back the city
but found not a soul.
If we wish, there is a way
to raise the greatest army
these shores have ever seen.
Lord, it's a signal that can be seen
from a mile or more.
- Thyra.
- Death is coming!
- The forest! The forest!
- Uhtred: It's a trick, I know it.
And I fear terrible consequences.
Destiny is all.
No, no. Please god,
let this not be true.
- Thyra!
- Steapa: Lady aethelflaed!
Thyra!
- Please be alive, please be alive.
- Steapa: Lady aethelflaed!
Beocca: Thyra!
Thyra, please!
Thyra!
Steapa: Lady aethelflaed!
- Not a single man left living.
- Nor woman.
She is the daughter of king Alfred.
They would not kill her.
They would not.
Thyra!
Please.
Thyra: Beocca!
- Beocca!
- Thyra!
- Thyra: Beocca!
Beocca!
I thought you were dead
and I wanted to die!
Thyra. Thyra.
Thyra... where is aethelflaed?
- You will answer.
- Of course she will answer!
I do not know.
- Did they take her?
- We ran and...
Then she was... gone.
We will continue the search, lord.
Uhtred:
They've taken her, they must have.
Why else abandon the city,
why raid the camp?
She is the daughter of the king.
They wouldn't dare.
Aldhelm: We will scour
the camp and beyond!
We are looking for the lady aethelflaed!
- Where are you taking me?
- You have found your voice.
- We're headed to beamfleot.
- And then?
- A ship? A cage?
- I'm still to decide.
I have given up lundene for you.
Erik, how does she feel?
As she should.
She is our pathway to glory.
What will you say to Alfred?
What can I tell him but the truth?
He will ask why she was with you.
She should never have been there.
I am aware of that.
You say she insisted, begged.
You're so enthralled by your bride
that you could not deny her.
Make myself appear weak?
It is a choice, lord,
between appearing love-sick or foolish.
Beocca: Uhtred?
Uhtred, where are you going?
I'm going home to coccham
where Alfred has asked me to remain.
And where I left my wife.
But the king, he may need you.
The king, in his wisdom,
has all but banished him, father beocca.
Aldhelm:
You should also raise the question
of how the northmen came to know
of aethelflaed's situation,
of where she would be.
Man: Move on.
If you believe her to be alive,
you will not abandon her.
You will not. That is a fact.
So what is the real reason
we're travelling home to coccham
and not to Winchester?
There's nothing to be said
in Winchester.
I won't be part of a whispering court.
We will go when I have something to say,
not before.
- Sihtric.
- Lord?
Take rypere there
and go to beamfleot.
That is where Erik and sigefrid's
fleet lie. That is where they'll be.
We are to spy?
You're to confirm lady aethelflaed
is alive and how they're treating her.
Send rypere back to me at coccham.
You will remain there
and yes, you are to spy.
Sihtric, I will need to know
every part of beamfleot,
every blade of grass
that surrounds their fortress.
Yes, lord.
Sigefrid: See this?
Warriors join us by the day.
With word of your capture,
there will be more.
All waiting for war.
You have my thanks, lady.
There will be many men inside.
They will want to get close to you,
look you in the eye.
- They'll want to frighten me.
- They will.
Sigefrid: What did I say?
I told you I would invite
king Alfred's daughter,
and she is here!
I swear to the gods that this prize
will not be sold cheaply.
There will be wealth and glory
for every man here!
Yeah!
Erik: It is the best we have.
These are my own men,
they will watch you.
You will have a guard at all times.
You will be safe here.
And my companions?
My servants from the camp?
Any woman who is not aethelflaed
will have been killed or claimed.
Claimed is most likely.
There's a bucket in the corner.
A royal bucket, no splinters.
Aethelred, I was expecting a messenger,
and not for days.
My news is too important
to trust to a messenger.
- Lundene has been reclaimed.
- 0h, praise god.
Not a single Northman
has been left alive in the city
but... this great victory
has come at a significant cost.
It is the way of battle.
It concerns aethelflaed, lord.
What of her?
We fear that she has been... taken.
- We pray that is the outcome, lord.
- By the northmen?
- Odda: Aethelflaed was with you?
- All the things they will do to her.
She was there?
- You took my daughter into battle?
- There was no battle, lord.
She was not part of the attacking army,
lord, of course not.
- She was a good distance away.
- But clearly not a safe distance.
Admittedly, I was weak,
but she is headstrong and eager.
- She asked to travel a part of the way.
- You are her husband!
She makes it difficult
for me to refuse her.
Is she alive? Have you seen her alive?
Answer me that.
She must be alive, lord.
What reason would they have to kill her?
But you do not know for certain?
How they knew she was with us,
we do not know.
Uhtred believes
they may have returned to beamfleot.
- He knows them well.
- Uhtred has returned to coccham, lord.
He was following
your earlier instructions, lord.
After hearing of events and...
Excuses...
What I now require are facts.
I have men across the land.
I will send word and ask for word.
That is all I can do.
That is all we can do. My dear.
Lord, you have my word!
I shall recover her.
Do you know what you've done?
Possibly not, as you are
as useless as you are arrogant.
I have done nothing
but carry out the king's orders.
You have put at risk
the entire kingdom.
All kingdoms!
You're a toad. A fool.
An idiot with ambition
far above your capability.
And if I can see this,
be sure Alfred can see it.
You have made your position clear,
lord odda.
- We will forgive your insolence.
- You will forgive me?
You will not address my lord
in that manner.
May I suggest that you take a wander
for yet another cup of wine?
Father beocca, steapa,
come with me.
You will tell me every detail
from the moment you left Winchester.
- With me!
- Yes, lord.
"Lundene has been reclaimed
and not a single Northman
has been left alive in the city."
You began so well.
I will be reminding the king
who it was who travelled into daneland.
that your friend uhtred
has been called king of mercia
and I shall remind him
how fond you are of his seat.
Do that.
But allow me to remind you of this.
The only man capable
of cleaning up this puddle of shit
is the man you are desperate to blame.
Uhtred, king of mercia.
What is on your mind?
I am thinking of aethelflaed.
If she lives, you will be her hope.
Alfred is her father.
You will be her hope,
uhtred of bebbenberg.
It should not be for you to resolve,
but you will do it.
By sending sihtric,
you have already begun.
- Stay with me.
- No, I am hungry.
- I will help you.
- No, I'm doing it!
I think I have something.
Supper at last!
He's a sea monster.
Lord. You said I should find you.
- Who are you?
- He's Alfred's bastard.
I am called osferth, lady.
I am simply called osferth.
Every person in every town
has been instructed to pray
that she is alive and kept well.
Then she will surely be alive,
kept well, and will be free in no time.
Alright, say goodnight.
- You do not believe, lord?
- Oh, I believe.
But in the true gods.
And in fate.
- You wish to serve a heathen, osferth?
- God is in all good men, lady.
And my uncle leofric told me often
that your husband is a good man.
- A great man.
- He said that?
Yes, he did, lord.
And yet this good man here will let you
join him for one reason only.
To embarrass Alfred.
It's true.
That may be the reason
you allow me to join you, lord,
but I will give you reason
to let me stay.
You have been brought here by fate,
osferth.
If all they have in Winchester
is prayer,
then they will need something more.
- We will go to Winchester.
- We will not.
This is what you want to do,
so why be childish about it?
We will go when I have news.
From beamfleot.
My men tell me you are refusing to eat.
- I am. I would like to wash.
- You have a bowl, you have water.
I would like to bathe.
I would like to breathe cool air.
I am beginning to feel sickly.
My brother suggested you bathe
inside a barrel in full view of all men.
Lady.
I will arrange
for you to bathe with privacy.
But in return
you must eat the food we provide.
Very well.
Ag Reed.
Thank you.
I feel she is alive, in my heart.
But what might they do to her?
She has her mother's courage
and that is the very reason
that she will survive this ordeal.
Lord king.
Although I would usually prefer him
miles away at coccham,
would it now be appropriate
to recall uhtred to Winchester?
- I accept he will never know god...
- Icannot
but if you sent him to beamfleot,
if she saw him...
- You know I cannot.
- Perhaps her spirits would rise.
- She believes in him.
- Our belief is in god. In prayer.
It is.
I will leave you to your letters.
We have our proof, rypere.
You will go to uhtred. Now.
Why so many guards?
Are you afraid of me?
You're a prize, lady.
Even when unwashed.
She's the daughter of a king.
You will all turn away.
- Show her the backs of your heads.
- Lord, where is the harm in looking?
The back of your heads!
http://hiqve.com/
Haesten: You were right, lord
- she has beauty.
- She does.
More than that, she's worth ten times
her weight in gold and silver.
I'm thinking we should fatten her.
- Does this game have a name?
- Stones.
And why's it called that?
Clapa: It's rypere.
Finan:
He must have news from beamfleot.
I'll go and tell uhtred.
Uhtred!
Uhtred?
Lord, if the northmen from beamfleot
are now raiding into mercia
to feed their army,
how long before
they come to wessex?
Is it not time
to consider raising the fyrds?
Aethelwold, as you have no estate, it is
not your place to talk of raising fyrds.
As for the ealdormen with estate,
for each of you,
there is a harvest to be gathered.
This must be done quickly
and stored within the nearest burh.
It must be protected.
Should they raid,
we shall not be overrun
and importantly, we shall not feed them
so much as a single grain.
Wessex is fortified.
Once the harvest is gathered,
the fighting men of the fyrds
shall be free of labor,
should they be required.
Should they be required, lord?
Mercia requires them now!
The heathen must be dealt with!
The heathen hold a hostage,
lord selwine.
Would you have
the lady aethelflaed killed?
Lord king,
I do not wish to cause distress,
but if the lady was in fact alive,
surely they would have made clear
their demands?
They want us supplicant, selwine.
They want us afraid.
They do not know of our faith, lord.
Father pyrlig?
Excuse me, lord,
but uhtred of this parish is here.
He is asking to attend.
Can he be trusted?
Lord, are we sure of uhtred's position?
Lord uhtred's position
is that of an ealdorman of wessex.
Lord, it is my own view
he should be admitted.
- Odda: And mine.
- Man: Allow him in.
Aelswith: Lord king.
The ealdorman uhtred may join the witan.
Pyrlig: Yes, lord.
Lord.
Lady aelswith.
- I am here with news of aethelflaed.
- From the northmen?
From my own spies
who sleep within the walls of beamfleot.
Lord, aethelflaed is alive.
My men have seen her
with their own eyes.
- Praise him.
- Praise him to the heavens.
Selwine: Then why have they
not made clear their demands?
They've been spreading news
of their hostage, lord.
Boasting? About seizing a woman?
Boasting of the army
they will raise with the ransom.
This is what I fear, lord.
No man in this hall
should be in any doubt.
When their demands arrive,
they will be considerable.
As will be the consequences.
Of course
they will make outrageous demands.
That is the purpose
of strong negotiation,
to ensure there is agreement.
- You intend to negotiate, lord?
- I intend to recover my daughter.
Selwine: Regardless of the price, lord?
Mercia is not a land of plenty.
Far from it.
Wessex shall pay its share of silver
and if necessary, its share of blood.
I will do what needs to be done.
If that means negotiation,
then I will negotiate.
Uhtred: Lord, I would advise that
you don't attend the negotiations.
The presence of the king and father
would only increase their price.
But if not the king, then who?
There will be silence!
Aethelred.
- Yes, lord?
- It must be you.
This is for mercia to resolve.
You must go to beamfleot.
- Of course, lord.
- And a representative of wessex, lord.
As the burden of your daughter is
to be shared between the two kingdoms.
I will suggest that the lord uhtred
represents wessex.
Agreed.
Forgive me, lord, but I do believe
he is your only choice.
Lord?
- Uhtred, you will accompany aethelred.
- I will do all I can, lord.
Lady.
Beocca: Uhtred!
Uhtred, forgive me,
but I have asked the king to excuse me
from this journey to beamfleot.
For my sins, god has always
placed me at your side
and I feel... shame for abandoning you.
No, beocca, your place
is in Winchester with thyra.
Bless you.
Uhtred, you have given me so much,
but giving me the courage
to approach thyra,
that was your greatest gift.
- I will be in your prayers, no doubt?
- Perhaps.
Always.
My men are restless.
Hunting is not enough.
I may go across the river,
spill a little blood.
Across the river is wessex.
Then if I see Alfred, I will tell him
that my brother is humping his daughter.
- I can see that you like her.
- I would like to ride her, yes.
Then ride her.
One tiny cock isn't going to hurt her.
- Haesten, what are you doing?
- Shut your mouth, dagfinn.
You saw nothing.
What do you want?
What do I want?
I'm here to remind you
that you're a woman and a hostage.
I like the paleness of your skin.
Show me. Take off your clothes.
Does the lord Erik
know that you're here?
It was the lord Erik that sent me here.
Now remove your clothes
or I will rip them from you.
Dagfinn, hold her!
Get up. Get up!
Lord, she's a hostage!
- Get up onto your feet!
- She is... a hostage!
She is precious!
She's of value!
Release her.
Leave us.
All of you.
This should not have happened
and it will not happen again.
My apologies.
It is not the first time
a man has mistreated me.
Who else?
Not here.
Before here.
Now I know what to do
should it happen again.
I... I will use my night bucket
and a knife.
You should.
You are precious, lady.
Sleep well.
Safely.
Odda.
It is late.
I was about to sit, contemplate.
As is your habit, lord.
I have been waiting for you.
Lord, I hope you will forgive me
for what I'm about to say.
My intentions are for wessex,
for the hope of an england.
You spoke of paying for aethelflaed's
release in one of two ways.
- Silver or with blood.
- I did.
There is a third way.
Should the ransom be too great,
should the likely loss of men
be too great,
should wessex wish to emerge with
honor, lord, and greater strength...
Then should she not be encouraged...
To take her own life?
For the good of the kingdom.
Some might say it would mean martyrdom.
I hear you, odda. I'm glad you feel able
to proffer this advice.
Now, I wish to sit. You will leave me.
Lord.
Look around you.
See the sacrifice that has been made.
Hundreds upon hundreds
of men, women and children
have given their lives
for what we now have.
They have given their lives, odda,
they did not take their lives.
And there will be reward in heaven
for each and every soul.
- That is what we believe, is it not?
- That is what I say, lord.
There will be reward enough, in heaven.
You are a king before you are a father.
I know my place.
Now you will leave me.
Lord.
I thought you'd like
to breathe the night's air.
Thank you.
I was born on a night of a whole moon.
My father wanted to call me mani,
after the moon god.
But mani is chased each night
across the sky by hati the wolf.
My mother did not want me
to be chased by wolves.
I saw the moon, the clear sky,
and I wanted to share it.
I'm glad you thought of me.
It was either share it with you
or with my brother.
The choice was difficult, I admit.
I have never seen
a face like this before.
Now I see it,
even when I close my eyes.
- Your husband is a fortunate man.
- My husband does not see me.
Then he's blind or stupid.
He is not blind.
And he is not gentle, I would guess.
He is the one who mistreats you?
He is not the man
I would choose to be with.
You. You!
Aethelwold.
Odda, you are drunk.
I sincerely hope so, I can barely see.
At your age, it is not good for you.
What is your opinion
on paying a ransom for aethelflaed?
Do you have an opinion?
Not one I am prepared to say aloud.
Is there much, or any,
of your father in you?
- The king past?
- I'm disappointed you need to ask.
I have both my father's blood
and spirit, the Danes know it.
Even the dead know it.
I am becoming more like him by the day.
Observe the clean tunic.
He was a great man.
He was my great friend.
If you are indeed his son,
I may need you.
You may need me for what?
I believe you need your bed, lord.
And a pillow.
You should employ a craftsman
to fit a spoon in place of the blade.
The leaves are falling. I want
the ransom paid in full by winter,
an army by spring.
A king's crown by summer.
They will want the same:
Answers by winter.
How does she ride?
Oh, you wouldn't like her,
she's bony and she squeals.
She passes the time.
And if you put a pup in her belly?
Then Alfred will get
two for the price of one.
And viking blood to strengthen
his line, eh?
What will happen
when we reach beamfleot?
Will there be a ritual? A toast, a meal?
There will be a heathen sacrifice.
The youngest member of the visiting
party will be split with an axe.
They will want to humiliate us.
- In what way?
- An insult, a challenge.
- Why?
- Because they can.
Man: Hey!
Haesten. We're travelling to beamfleot.
- For Alfred?
- For Alfred, yes.
I am here to take you
on to the fortress, lord.
You and two others.
I will travel with half my number,
no less.
Ag Reed.
Aethelred:
The lady aethelflaed, she is well?
There'll be no negotiation
until I have seen her.
She is well. My lord Erik sees
that she is... most content, lord.
- Ride on and we'll follow.
- Oh, you will not be needing horses.
Lord, I have a question.
What is it we want from this meeting?
You have to ask?
What we want is to free aethelflaed.
Yet instead,
if what transpired was war, what then?
It is a question, lord, that is all.
I would be without a wife, no doubt.
As that would be the cause of war.
War will occur regardless,
that is certain.
The only change that there can be
is the size of the army
that we will face across the field.
- We will be ready.
- But what is it we want?
Alfred wants his daughter,
that is plain.
But is that best for mercia?
Is that best for aethelred,
lord of mercia and lundene
and more perhaps?
My advice to you, lord,
is rescue her, by all means,
but not at a price
that will cut our throats.
- Sigefrid: You will all kneel.
- We will not.
We have come here in peace
and as equals.
You've made us walk
a good distance to meet you.
That is respect enough.
You should have joined me, uhtred.
If you wished me to join you,
why have a dead man tell a prophecy?
- Why didn't you simply ask?
- Me, you would refuse. But the gods?
The king of wessex sends his greetings.
He hopes you have enjoyed
the company of his daughter.
Enjoyed her?
Oh, she's not his favorite.
Why else would he have allowed her to
marry the pig's arse standing behind me?
Before any negotiations take place,
the pig's arse wishes to be certain
that his wife is well.
And if she's not well, what then?
What will the pig's arse do? Fart?
Will you fight me?
- Will you fight my brother?
- I would like that.
- You alone will kneel.
- I will not.
Kneel!
I have come to negotiate.
I demand respect.
If you do not wish to hear my price,
then I will leave, happily.
- Aethelflaed.
- As you can see, she is well.
- I would like to speak with her.
- Then do it.
- They are treating you well?
- They are.
- You have not been... touched?
- I have not.
What I must now do
is secure an acceptable price
for your release.
There will be word games played.
Do not be alarmed by what I may say.
I assure you, once this is over,
they shall pay
for what they have done to us all.
Thank you, lord.
What is your price?
It must be fair or you can keep her.
You talk of your woman
like you do not care.
She is important to me, of course,
but she has a price,
beyond which I cannot go.
I will not go.
Then name it. Name this price.
One hundred pounds' weight of silver.
My lands can afford no more.
- Does this man speak for Alfred?
- He does not.
Hmm.
Weland!
Wh-where is weland?
I do not see him. Weland!
Weland!
Ah. Weland.
This... man here.
Hit him.
Uhtred: She is a daughter, not a son.
Unloved and, in truth,
banished to mercia
to spend life being humped by a husband
you have so generously put to bed.
Like her husband,
Alfred's not minded to pay a great sum.
- Alfred's price is what? Say it.
- I will.
Separate from the 100 pounds' weight
of silver offered by the husband,
Alfred will add another
200 pounds' weight of silver.
- Three hundred pounds in total.
- A good price.
The daughter of a frankish king was once
bargained for a similar price. Pyrlig?
This is true, it is a good price.
No. No, no, no, no, no, no.
No, Alfred is not a frankish king
and it is not a good price.
- I say it's a good price.
- Like the pig's arse, you have farted.
Yes! And it stinks.
By the gods, does it stink!
- Open the doors.
- It is a good price?
- I think it's a good price.
- You insult me!
If Alfred is minded to offer so little,
then I am minded
to bring her into this hall
and allow each man here
to take his turn.
I swear, she will be tied to a cart
and she will travel the kingdoms.
Is that what you want... Saxon?
- Do not insult me.
- I'm not insulting you.
Do not.
The king has given me
some discretion to increase the price.
What a surprise.
So, say it.
Lord, if I may,
and to save both time and ink,
perhaps you might name a price.
An acceptable price.
Not an impossible price.
Say it.
Ten thousand pounds' weight of silver
and one thousand pounds' weight of gold.
- Delivered by Alfred himself.
- Of course.
And he shall arrive with a stoat upon
his head and an apple in his mouth.
With respect, sigefrid,
you fart louder and longer
than the pig's arse and I together.
I need to take a piss.
It's going to be a long day.
Aethelred, lord of mercia!
If yourjaw is not broken, join us! Eat.
Yes, I will. I would enjoy that.
- Business is done.
- Done?
A bargain has been made
and not a good one.
Say nothing.
Uhtred and father pyrlig have gone
to see how your lady is, lord.
- Then I will go to her.
- Hm-mm, no.
You will wait here. You will sit.
With me.
- To silver and gold.
- And lots of it, lord.
Drink.
Erik: She's praying.
Give her time with the priest
and then you will see her.
Twenty-six ships.
By the next moon, there will be more.
And more still the moon after.
Alfred will pay for his own destruction.
You should not underestimate
Alfred of wessex.
Never. But he will pay
what you have agreed?
- He will.
- Even for an unloved daughter?
Alfred is suffering.
He loves her dearly.
Her husband does not.
I was surprised at your anger
towards aethelred.
- What purpose did it serve?
- It was a mistake.
It was. You made it clear
that you care for her.
I cannot let her go.
I cannot give her up.
We have just settled on a price.
There is agreement.
With my brother.
- Lord uhtred.
- Lady.
Your father sends his affection.
He will be sleeping at the altar,
I'm sure.
I have arranged your release.
You will soon be coming home.
Have you spoken with Erik?
I have.
What has he told you?
- Lady, he's a Northman and a pagan.
- He is a pagan as you are a pagan.
Any hope that you have
of a life together is nonsense.
- It will fail.
- It will not.
Merely because it's what you wish for?
Lady, it can never happen.
- Well, it must.
- What of your husband?
I will not talk of my husband.
I... I do not care for him.
- And I will never care for him.
- He will not stand by.
I do not care.
Sigefrid will not stand by
and your father will not stand by.
- You will lose your entire family.
- I will make a family.
- We will make a family, Erik and I.
- And they will die.
As you will die.
In a fire, at the tip of a sword.
- Then I will die happily.
- Aethelflaed, hear me.
There will be no rest. None.
A life with Erik is what I want.
It is best for me
and it is best for wessex.
I can say this to no one but you.
I can... I can ask no one but you.
Will you help us escape?
Lady, I am sworn to your father.
If I help you and succeed,
he'll have me killed.
But more than that, you are asking me
to sanction your own death.
No, what I am asking
is for you to allow me to live.
I will not be the treasure
that builds an army against my father.
That will not happen. Never.
I will leave this place with Erik
or I will not leave at all.
Uhtred, I am asking you to save my life
and with it,
the nations of wessex and mercia.
Will you help me?
Please?
http://hiqve.com/