I am uhtred, son of uhtred.
Defeated at ethandun,
Earl guthrum was baptized
and became king aethelstan
of east anglia,
while in wessex aethelwold still sees
himself as the true heir to the throne.
I see it as a king would see it.
Yet king Alfred has other plans.
I'm to be married?
A permanent bond
between wessex and mercia.
Which one of you is aethelred?
Alfred forced me to renew my allegiance.
He sent me to kill the northmen
brothers, Erik and sigefrid.
After taking sigefrid's hand,
I banished them.
You will take one ship and you will
leave northumbria. You will not return.
I swear.
And at last in northumbria,
I took my revenge against kjartan
and his son, sven,
freeing my enslaved sister, thyra.
Let me help you.
Having defeated the Danes,
I married my love, gisela,
and now all seems quiet.
But for a warrior
there can never be peace.
Destiny is all.
We're here.
Ground her ahead. Be ready.
Sihtric: She says she loves me.
- I swear. She says she loves me.
- She would.
Sihtric, she's a whore.
No. She's past that.
What she loves is your silver.
Is that the name of his cock?
I wish to marry her.
I wish you to kill Danes
and survive the night.
We're the only chance
the villagers have.
They have begun.
Elgin! Pass me the flask.
If you wish to live, boy,
take your hand away from your sword.
Uhtred: There will be
no more than 30 raiders.
We hide and we wait.
We attack on my command, not before.
You all heard the lord. We find cover.
Man: Come on! Come on!
Stay together.
You're alive, girl.
Man: Elgin!
Elgin, get up!
Help Rob the prisoners.
Keep them quiet!
Elgin!
- Are you drunk?
- Now!
Finan: We kill 'em!
Every bastard one of them!
Man: To arms!
- Defend yourselves!
- Run!
What's your name?
Her name is aethelflaed, lord.
You're her mother?
No, lord.
The king, Alfred...
He has a daughter named aethelflaed.
She's strong and brave.
You will need to be the same.
Go back to your village.
Take care of your dead.
Finan. Hang three of the dead
from the trees, visible from the river.
Lord.
Take back what belongs to you.
You're safe now.
You will go back to your rats' nest
and tell anyone who cares to listen,
"beyond lundene
the river temes belongs to Alfred.
And it's guarded
by uhtred of bebbanburg."
Now, there's a welcome sight.
My wife and my boy.
Whoa!
I think we might be
feeding you too much.
Don't forget your daughter.
She's here too.
- It went well?
- It did. Not a scratch.
You have a visitor.
He has been here all night.
Aethelwold.
How much of my ale have you drunk?
Not a cup.
Not a drop of ale has passed my lips
for ten days or more.
You've been ill?
Not ill, but sober,
which, as you know, is unlike me.
But it is important
that you accept that I am sober.
Say what you're here to say.
You've waited long enough.
The dead speak.
I have seen it, heard it.
And the dead speak.
The dead?
A corpse.
I saw him rise from his grave and speak.
And what did this corpse say?
What he said concerns us both... us all.
Hence my visit.
And what I tell you are his words,
not mine, you understand.
What did he say?
That I should be king.
No, believe me, it is true.
He said that I should be king of wessex
and that you...
You should be a king too.
He said that you, uhtred,
will be crowned king of mercia.
Bjorn heard it
through the three spinners.
Bjorn?
That is his name.
He is a Dane?
A dead Dane, yes. Therefore a good Dane.
We are royalty, you and I.
I have done my utmost to serve Alfred
but with no reward, no respo...
Where are you going?
To wash the blood off my hands
and then to bed.
Do you not believe me?
Where did you see this corpse?
Mercia. Beyond watling street.
You crossed into daneland?
I went to the part of mercia
that Alfred gifted to the Danes, yes.
You happened to wander
across watling street?
I was sent for! I was invited!
And the same will happen to you.
I know what I saw.
You will be a queen.
I may not wish to be a queen.
When bjorn is ready to speak,
there will be a messenger.
Tell me.
Do you wish Alfred harm?
No. No, of course not.
I mean, I wish him dead
but I would not harm him.
I know what I saw.
I will not outstay my welcome.
Thank you for your kindness.
You are sworn to Alfred.
To become king of mercia
you would need to break that oath.
If that is my fate.
Then you believe he speaks the truth?
No, I do not.
But I know he's not telling lies.
The truth is another matter.
We do not want an enemy such as Alfred.
And Alfred will not want
an enemy like me.
It appears to be good progress, lord.
The people of coccham
seem to be in good spirits.
It would appear so.
We shall see.
Man: Lord king.
Open the gates!
- Finan.
- What?
Lord king!
- Welcome to coccham.
- Finan.
Lord uhtred is at the fortress,
the burh.
If you fetch him, finan,
we'll be waiting in the hall.
I will, lord.
The man must have a priest
for each day of the year.
Man: God be with you.
Lord, we are crossing into wessex.
This stretch of river
is protected by lord uhtred.
- You say you have trade there?
- I do, lord.
Lord, please,
I cannot risk losing my ship.
You will keep your ship.
It's easy enough to say it.
It is a pagan's hall.
Lord, you say the same
every time we visit.
Uhtred is a pagan, as is his hall.
I find it annoying
that he will not grow.
He insists upon clinging
to these ancient beliefs.
- The beliefs of our forefathers.
- Who knew no better.
Lord king.
- Refreshment.
- Thank you, gisela.
I, uh... I trust you are well.
I am, lord, and better for your visit.
- The ale is freshly brewed.
- Ah! Excellent.
You are content in wessex, I hope.
I am, lord.
I am well, my family are well,
and there's peace.
This is all I ask.
And what of you? Are you content?
My daughter is now old enough
and will soon be gifted in marriage.
I am... apprehensive.
- Aethelflaed is a sweet girl.
- She is.
- You are fond of her suitor, lord?
- Aethelred.
He serves a purpose. He is godly.
Gisela: Well, we look fonlvard to
the wedding celebrations in Winchester.
And I wish her happiness.
The purpose of marriage
is not to be happy, my dear.
Then I am fortunate.
I pray my own wife might say the same.
Oh, I imagine she does, odda,
as she so rarely sees you.
Lord king. Lord odda.
Steapa, my friend.
Uhtred, you do not deserve
such a charming wife.
Oh, I can only agree, lord.
I was not expecting you.
There's been no message.
I'm hearing you've hanged a man.
I hanged many men just lately.
Raiders... Danes.
And already dead, lord.
I am speaking of a Saxon man,
a man of coccham, of wessex.
That is why you are here?
Amongst other concerns.
That man was a thief, lord.
Sinful to the bone.
You hanged him without trial.
He was guilty. Three times over.
It is the purpose of a trial
to determine guilt.
People must witness
justice being done.
Then I shall arrange a trial.
It's a little bit late for that, I fear.
Gisela: Has there been
a complaint, lord?
There are laws, carefully written laws,
and if you wish to remain an ealdorman,
you will adhere to them.
You shall not impose your pagan ideals
within my kingdom.
We are west of watling street, not east.
Yes, lord.
We do not cross over into daneland,
we do not cross over into danelaw,
in mind, nor body nor spirit.
No, lord.
My nephew... aethelwold.
He was, uh...
Well, he was seen doing just that.
Leaving wessex, crossing through mercia
from west to east.
Are you aware of this?
I'm not.
When aethelwold was here, he mentioned
nothing of crossing into daneland.
Hm. What did he mention?
He mentioned you, lord,
and how you took his crown.
Odda: Aethelwold is permanently idle.
My advice is the same
as it has always been.
You should put him on trial
and then kill him.
Should the devil begin to whisper
in his ear, then I may have no choice.
http://hiqve.com/
Besides the man you strung up,
how many of the raiders did you kill?
We killed about 30 men in total.
They'd sacked a village.
- Which was in mercia.
- Lord, we hear the screams at night.
Mercia is weak. Its people
have no protection from the Danes.
Mercia is disorganized
and that will change.
There will be burhs.
What is that?
- That structure, there?
- It's a place for prayer, lord.
A church, uhtred?
Not quite, lord. It's a shack...
With a cross attached.
If it is for the purpose of prayer,
then it is a church.
Lord! A ship is near.
Traders.
Perhaps you'd like a moment
to pray, lord?
I'll need to watch the trader.
Yes.
Yes, I would like that.
Lord!
I was just thinking about you.
You were in my prayers...
Is what I mean.
Thank you, hild.
Please continue.
Do not let me disturb your peace.
Would you care to sit with me...
In peace, lord?
I would, hild. I will.
May I ask...
Have you found your lasting peace?
I am near, lord.
I feel more content here with god
than with my sword.
Courage without the sword
is the more difficult path.
It must in time become the only path.
I pray you find your peace
sooner than I.
Thank you, lord.
Captain: You, stay with the ship.
Godwin... I was expecting you days ago.
Are you carrying the axe heads?
I am, lord. Frankia made.
Would split an oak tree.
- How many?
- How many do you need?
My man saw warriors aboard your ship.
Is this true?
Three men only, lord.
It is a Northman.
He wishes to speak with you, alone.
- Can I trust this Northman?
- He says that you know him.
His name is Erik.
He has a brother, sigefrid.
Finan.
First sign of trouble, fire the ship.
There'll be no need for fire, lord.
Sihtric, fetch me
a whole bunch of torches.
I like to be prepared.
Erik: Uhtred of bebbanburg.
Here you are, lost in wessex once again.
I am sworn...
To king Alfred.
That is why I am here.
Why are you here?
I'm not looking to fight. Not yet.
Can you believe I'm traveling
to meet with a dead man?
- You deal in sorcery now?
- It is my fate, or so I'm told.
You have my word that I will
make my appointment in mercia
and then I shall return to frankia.
Sigefrid is in frankia?
He is.
But not for much longer.
My brother is... restless.
We have grown strong
in the years since northumbria.
We have a fleet now. 19 ships.
Which you will sail to where?
0h, we have no firm plan,
other than to listen to bjorn.
The dead man.
You say it without surprise, uhtred.
I think you might have
gotten wind of this ghost.
He speaks the words of the three
spinners. We cannot ignore him.
- We?
- You and I.
After his defeat at ethandun,
the Earl guthrum rejected our gods
and they are angry.
They want revenge.
I believe we have been chosen.
You will receive your invitation.
You shall see for yourself, I'm sure.
What if I refuse to meet
with this ghost?
That is a matter
for the three spinners and the gods.
And what if I believe this ghost
to be a trap?
To be sigefrid wanting to kill me?
You have my word that it is not.
I swear, all that we want is
uhtred of bebbanburg at our side.
Now, am I allowed to pass
to keep my own appointment?
You are.
Safe journey.
All the way back to frankia.
Uhtred ragnarson.
You will always have my respect.
But do not forget
you were raised as a Dane.
- The broth was suitable, lord?
- The broth was a delight, gisela.
As is the ale.
You should moderate, odda. You have
a ladder to climb to find your bed.
- You can always be carried, lord.
- It wouldn't be the first time.
And I guarantee
it won't be the last time.
Lord, you make me out to be a drunk.
Though my head will be sore
in the morning, I know it.
Well, then it's ale for breakfast, lord,
the only cure.
Was my nephew drunk
when he was here last?
Aethelwold is often drunk, lord.
But this last time
he did not touch a drop.
He mentioned he had been sober for days,
which came as a surprise.
- That's a miracle.
- Not quite.
Uhtred: Aethelwold is not
a complete fool, lord.
If he's idle, then could he not
help bring order to mercia?
He fought well at ethandun.
As he is fond of reminding people.
He's as good a man as aethelred.
Uhtred, you speak of matters
you do not understand,
matters that do not concern you.
The safety of wessex concerns me.
I'm happy to hear you say it.
Which is why
we killed the raiders, lord.
Raiders who once belonged
to Earl guthrum.
His name is now king aethelstan.
That has been his name
since he became a Christian.
Regardless of what he's called,
it's his men who now break the peace.
- You are sure of this?
- Uhtred: I am.
They gather at the mouth
of the temes river at beamfleot.
It's true, lord.
Two hundred or more, we've seen it.
Uhtred: And their number grows.
If these rogues are aethelstan's men,
then they are his worry.
Until they decide
to blockade the river, lord.
Then wessex will be starved of trade.
- Aethelstan shall deal with them.
- He must kill them.
I believe we must kill them.
Alfred: What we must do
is hold the peace!
War cannot always be the answer.
Lord, forgive me but you speak of
matters you do not fully understand.
These men will not listen to aethelstan
and aethelstan will not deal with them.
For now they are rogues,
but should they find a lord to serve,
then they will become an army.
So answer me this. Where might
this lord come from? Do I know of him?
Should I fear him?
You can be sure
he will not be called uhtred, lord,
if that is your meaning.
My advice, lord, is to send
ships and men to beamfleot.
We shall maintain the peace.
They say it is an honor
to have the king stay,
but his men and his priests have eaten
almost a winter's worth of food.
Uhtred, how can you serve a man
who doesn't see your value?
0h, he sees it.
His god won't allow him to embrace it.
He dislikes me more by the day.
Then you should ask him to release you.
And we will go north,
to my brother and to ragnar.
I am content here, but we cannot
become an enemy of Alfred.
Hild: Lord.
Hild. You look fearsome.
- I think I preferred you with a sword.
- My sword has become heavy.
But you could probably
kill someone with that, though.
I need to speak to you plainly.
I would like to build a house,
a nunnery, here in coccham,
but with your permission
and that of the bishop, of course.
The time is the right time.
You have my permission. No question.
Thank you.
And you have my protection.
Always... abbess hild.
You will always be too good a woman
for god alone.
Uhtred: Alfred will be pleased.
Erik: Stow the oars! Make her secure.
- And, haesten...
- Lord?
Ensure the ships are guarded well.
Yes, lord.
The fortress of beamfleot.
And all the men inside.
They're ours now.
Even the air is rich here.
Lundene is how far upriver?
Half a day, with the tide.
We take it at the earliest.
And uhtred.
As we planned.
Beocca: Are you looking fonlvard
to the wedding, father?
I am. I am, father beocca.
I enjoy a wedding
as much as the next drunkard.
And how is your own lady, father?
The Dane.
Thyra?
She is not my lady. She's well.
She is something of a strange beauty.
Yes.
She's, uh... she's... yes.
I inform god each evening
how much I miss the company of a woman.
He sends me nothing.
We talk, thyra and I.
She's a pleasant woman.
There is no finer sight than that
of a naked woman, arms outstretched.
Almost there.
Lord! Lord?
Beocca, come in.
- Father pyrlig.
- Good day, lord.
I read of nothing
but skirmishes and raids.
What kind of a place must daneland be?
- Sinful, lord.
- Without question.
They aspire only to kill and fornicate.
Aelswith: Lord. Are we to wait?
- For a moment.
- Beocca: Lady aelswith.
Lady, I beg your pardon
for my somewhat colorful description
of life as a Dane.
We are prepared, lord.
- Father pyrlig, I have a task for you.
- Lord.
You are familiar with east anglia,
are you not?
I am, lord.
Aland of quite unremarkable beauty.
You will go to king aethelstan.
He may need help
with the reading of this letter.
Aethelstan.
He is to deal with the rogue Danes
at beamfleot and swiftly.
- If you could emphasize swiftly.
- Emphasize swiftly.
You have been allocated a guard.
They are waiting for you in the stable.
- I am to leave now, lord?
- Swiftly, father.
May I say, I was somewhat looking
forward to the celebrations, lord?
The whole of Winchester
shall be celebrating.
Swiftly.
- Yes, lord. I will gather what I need.
- Lord.
You are ready?
I am.
There's still
a little decorative work to be done.
Now, do not touch it.
You have ink on your hands.
Say what you think. Do you like it?
I have not seen anything so beautiful.
He does not deserve you.
Did I not say the same?
I hope that aethelred says the same.
Aethelred should consider himself
a very fortunate young man.
And in time, you will
grow fond of him, I'm sure.
I'm already fond of him.
0h, shush now. You've barely met him.
The last time over a year ago.
Aethelred is a good and godly man.
Who is a little too fond of himself.
Will uhtred be coming to the wedding?
Sadly, he will. I'm sure.
I consider him to be our lucky charm.
Now, now. There will be no mention
of luck or charms.
- There is god's will and nothing more.
- Praise him.
Man: It is fertile land, lord.
No greener than mercia.
Though wessex has the advantage
of not sharing a border with the Welsh.
The Welsh to the west, the Danes
to the east, and Alfred to the south.
We're surrounded.
I would say we're perfectly positioned,
at the very middle
of Alfred's idea of an england.
Pivotal.
Yes, I like that.
Lord?
Lord! Have you made a decision yet?
Have you given it thought?
Given thought to what?
Uhtred.
Well, my request to marry, lord.
I would like to have a family.
Lord, you will answer the man.
I will speak with her at Winchester
and give you my decision.
Thank you, lord.
But you're to give her no more
of your Ann-rings nor silver!
If it is not the great lord uhtred
of the small and little-known village
of coccham.
I see you're drinking again, aethelwold.
Just a cup or two, nothing more.
I have news for you.
You know where to find me.
Before you take yourself away to an inn,
I wish to speak with you.
About what?
Privately.
Uhtred, please.
Let us not rush
to make an enemy of Alfred.
And if the dead man and the gods
say differently?
Gisela: They will not,
if they are truly gods.
And also... this girl whom sihtric
loves, you will not belittle her.
She's an alehouse whore.
Gisela: And what is aethelflaed?
What is a peace-cow if not a whore?
There's a difference, clearly.
She will marry and be humped by a man
she does not know and for a price.
Where's the difference?
- It's the way.
- She is a whore in a wedding gown.
If it is the way,
then I belong to your uncle still.
I will say no more.
I'm pleased to hear it.
Uhtred!
Uhtred, as always
it begins as a joy to see you.
And you, father beocca.
- You look well.
- I am well.
Oh, I would like you to meet
father pyrlig.
Lord uhtred.
I've heard much about you.
Father pyrlig was once
a warrior himself.
Sword and spear, lord,
but a man tires of sticking ironware
into the bellies of other men.
I would have enjoyed a cup of ale
with you both, but I must leave you.
You have the letter secure?
I do, father. I've put it
right next to my ball-bag.
Lord uhtred, it was an honor.
- Unusual priest.
- Yes.
Uhtred...
There is a matter upon which
I find myself in need of your advice.
About thyra.
0h, as I say, she... she's...
Well, she's... delightful.
But my problem is this.
She, um... must leave, I feel.
Um... join you at coccham
or return to ragnar.
- You don't want her here?
- No.
Yes. I mean, no...
I do want her here.
It's just that, uh...
I simply cannot think.
I can't work, I can't sleep.
It's been like this for months.
I can barely pray.
And even when I do I pray,
I pray only for myself,
which is wrong, very wrong.
Sinful.
Wrong.
I didn't realize she had become
such a burden, father.
I mean, she's not a burden.
She could never be a burden.
Then, father, I'm lost.
Why must she leave?
Because I cannot think
of anything but her.
It is constant
and it is pathetic and hopeless,
because... she is fair
and I am beocca.
A man old enough to be
her much older brother.
You're smiling.
You're laughing at me.
No, father. I swear
I'm not laughing at you.
- I can see your teeth.
- I'm sharing yourjoy.
There is no joy.
I feel I am in a purgatory of sorts.
Thyra will not go to ragnar.
She's happy here in Winchester
with you.
- Nonsense.
- Beocca...
You are her peace, her happiness.
- Marry her.
- Marry her?
You should marry her, father,
and bed her.
And then give thanks to god
for giving us such a joy.
Praise him, father.
Praise him!
But what if she refuses?
Clapa: Is that aethelred?
Mm... from what I know, Alfred
could not have chosen a bigger turd.
I've never met the man,
but by the look of him,
he was indeed
shat out the arse of a giant.
He is to be king of mercia,
they are saying.
The ealdormen of the witan are saying.
Uhtred: Lord of mercia perhaps.
Alfred would never allow
another Saxon to be called king.
Nor would a certain dead man
called bjorn.
- He wishes to meet you.
- Come with me.
Ow! You're pinching my skin.
You're pinching my skin.
This was clean!
Why are you being trusted with
my business? Who gave you this message?
- A skald. A pagan skald...
- His name!
Uh... eilaf, eilif...
Something Dane, something odd.
Are you any wiser? No, you are not.
I'm a messenger, nothing more.
Like it or not we are bonded, you and I.
- Bonded?
- Yes!
Our ancestors were kings and yet
we are barely acknowledged as ealdormen.
We deserve more.
You especially deserve more.
As for me, I have a chamber in the
palace and that is the sum of my land.
He has given me nothing.
I am no longer part of the witan even.
Uhtred, I can see you are torn
but why should we stand by and watch
while power and wealth is given
to the likes of aethelred of mercia?
You are witness. You saw him just now,
riding through Winchester
like a peacock, like he was king...
When?
When am ito meet with bjorn?
If we leave tonight, we can be back here
in two days, in time for the wedding.
I am to take you there.
Watch him rise from his grave
and you will know that it is all true.
He will not ask again.
Sihtric: Lord!
Don't speak! Don't move!
We leave as soon as
my horses are cooled and fed.
The winds are blowing a change,
lord king.
You'll be glad to hear
that I've made my decision.
You may marry this girl.
- Lord, thank you...
- Upon completion of a task.
You'll fetch clapa, you'll go
to the stables and wait for me.
Ensure the horses
are watered and fed, but ready.
- Yes, lord.
- Go.
And thank you, lord.
We will name our first son uhtred, lord.
- No, you will not!
- No, we will not.
Thyra..
Beocca...
You... you gave me a fright.
Forgive me.
Are you coming inside?
I have supper.
There's something
I needed to say, thyra.
Something I needed to ask.
- You should ask it...
- Marry me!
I said... I said marry me.
It was selfish of me to ask,
to even mention the word.
But, uh...
I fear you have become someone
I cannot live without.
You fear?
Life without you...
Fear no more.
I'm here.
Always.
Supper?
Praise him.
This is it.
The skald's hall.
It was given to eilaf by his lord,
for great service.
Sihtric, you will go no further.
Not until we are at the hall and inside.
- At all times you will remain unseen.
- Yes, lord.
If the dead man rises,
when he returns to his grave,
you will keep watching.
What if he sees me, lord?
What if...
What if he knows that I am near?
Then you shit yourself.
You will remain unseen and keep watch.
Yes, lord.
There are men... warriors.
We are here to see eilaf, the skald.
We have an invitation.
Who leads here?
I am haesten
and you... are uhtred of bebbanburg.
You spared me at eofenlvic, lord.
You're expected and welcome.
Go take a piss.
- Who is he?
- A thief, lord.
I serve Erik, sigefrid's brother.
He sends you good wishes.
Erik is not here?
He is not.
And if I had my way,
I would not be here.
My men... are afraid.
Of ghosts?
It is not a sight you will forget.
My lord wants you to know that by now
he will be at beamfleot and not frankia.
With sigefrid?
With his brother... and with the fleet.
He insisted you were told.
And where to after beamfleot?
I can't say.
But it is hoped
that you will join us there.
Eilaf is resting, lord,
in preparation for tonight.
You... may wish to do the same.
They have a fleet. How many, I wonder.
19 ships.
That's more than 500 men,
plus those already there.
And those who will come.
Then it has started.
- What?
- The end of the peace.
You stand too close, girl.
Do not make me speak to you again.
Once the marriage is made,
you should consider
making aethelred earn his privilege.
Skirmishes and raids from the Danes
must not be tolerated.
Not one.
It should be made
aethelred's responsibility.
And the mercian ealdormen should be
invited to attend a wessex witan.
For the purpose of what?
For the purpose of bowing to the king
and watching the lord of mercia
do the same.
I do not doubt for one moment that
aethelred has dreamt... is dreaming...
Of overtaking me.
It would be a simple reminder
of his position.
Excuse me, lord.
Odda. Come in, join us.
Lord, it is about
both something and nothing...
Sit.
Uhtred has left Winchester, last night.
- And gone where?
- We don't know for certain.
- And what of his current witch?
- His wife, dear.
The lady gisela remains in Winchester.
Well, he can't have gone far.
Aethelwold is with uhtred.
- They went in which direction?
- Mercia, lord.
I think it is more than nothing, odda,
and I am wholly tired
of never-ending disobedience.
But it will not
ruin your appetite, lord.
It will not.
Put a watch on gisela.
She must not leave
until her husband has returned
and explained his absence.
Father beocca.
Lord!
Lord... lady.
I have news.
Uhtred has returned?
From where, lord?
What is your news, father beocca?
I am to be married.
The once proud and brave Earl guthrum...
He now calls himself a Christian!
He now calls himself king aethelstan,
but he's nothing but Alfred's hound,
and he's shamed us all!
He has shamed every warrior
that has gone before us!
He has shamed the gods!
The gods call upon every man
gathered here today to avenge them!
And avenge them we will!
By sunrise tomorrow,
lundene and all of its riches
shall be yours.
Believe me when I tell you
the gods are with us!
The gods are with us!
Oarsmen: Pull!
Pull!
Forgive me for not being awake
to greet you, lord.
Bjorn has given me little rest
these recent times.
We understand.
The gods are wanting true men.
So I thank you for being here,
uhtred of bebbanburg.
After tonight... I hope to sleep.
Fetch the blood.
It is time.
It's a Christian graveyard.
Haesten: Yes, lord.
Perhaps that is why bjorn
cannot rest, nor pass.
Please, no.
Please... please.
To raise the dead, lord, we need
to send a messenger across the Gulf.
- He is guilty?
- Twice over.
Man: Please, I beg you, lord, please...
I have a wife, I have children.
Please...
What did you steal?
Just a lamb, lord, for my family.
- And furs.
- For my family, lord!
I'm sorry but a thief twice over
deserves to die.
- No! Please...
- Put it in his mouth.
No, please, lord. I beg you, please.
I can fight, I can work,
I can serve, lord.
- Please, I beg of you.
- I'm on your side, lord.
What is it? Please, no, lord.
Please, no...
Haesten: Sh...
A harp string, lord.
A bridge from our world to bjorn's.
Kill him.
Please, lord. Please, lord, no, please!
Get the message into his mouth
and kill him!
Spare me! Spare me
and I will repay you with gratitude.
Please, lord...
Eilaf: Bjorn...
You have blood.
I have given you life.
I have sent you a message.
If it's peace that you want,
you shall not have it
until we hear you speak.
Finan: The harp string.
Eilaf: Welcome, bjorn.
This is lord uhtred,
who has sent a good many Dane
to the place where you live.
I do not live.
Eilaf: You have a message
for lord uhtred.
Lord uhtred. I see you now.
The gods have had their sacrifice
and the brothers have tonight begun
that which cannot be stopped.
Lundene's streets are red...
With Saxon blood.
You... are to be king.
King of mercia.
King of Saxon and Dane.
King of other kings.
You, lord uhtred.
Bury him.
Lord king?
It is done.
What we have just witnessed...
You believe it to be true?
I do.
And me.
It put a shiver
through your spine, no doubt.
So, what now? You're sworn to Alfred.
Aethelwold: Alfred is nothing
compared to the gods...
I would suggest.
Uhtred, it is our birthright
to be called kings.
Haesten!
- Lord?
- The brothers sigefrid and Erik...
Is it true what bjorn says?
They're attacking lundene?
I cannot say for certain, lord,
but that was the plan.
To sail upriver and take lundene,
which would now be your city
as king of mercia.
http://hiqve.com/