I am Uhtred, son of Uhtred.
Edward, King of Wessex, commanded me
to raise his bastard son, Aethelstan.
Protect him and take him to safety.
Teach him how to be a warrior
and all you know of the Danes.
For Aethelstan has rivals
who plot against him.
Edward's father-in-law, Aethelhelm, is
determined that his own line will prevail,
and he stops at nothing to see
his grandson Aelfweard on the throne.
If the king cannot choose
between his sons,
it may be that we need to ensure
his ally the queen does not survive.
Mother! Mother!
For many years,
my men and I protected the Mercian border,
where we serve at the pleasure
of the Lady of Mercia.
Aethelflaed has taken
a vow of chastity to rule alone,
although a deep love remains between us.
The price
we are paying is great.
I will miss you, Uhtred Ragnarson.
And she takes great comfort
in her precious child Aelfwynn.
My own daughter Stiorra has made
her bond with Sigtryggr the Dane.
We seek a homeland.
But we do not succumb to anger.
For many years there has been
peace between Saxon and Dane.
And of Brida?
Nothing has been heard
since she fled Winchester...
My love...
...and gave birth to Cnut's child.
But I fear that her anger
towards me still haunts her.
Blood has been shed. More will flow.
I will take revenge
on all those who have betrayed me
and I will not rest
until they suffer at my hand.
Destiny is all.
Years passed.
And for those years we heard nothing.
No word, no sign.
Just quiet rumors that she had died.
That she was reborn.
I hoped the silence
meant that she had found peace.
Most forgot her.
I did not.
And I knew, in time, she would return.
The reckoning approaches.
The gods are speaking.
They guide the seer to choose amongst you.
The seer has chosen.
We make this sacrifice
to bring good fortune.
Show us the moment is ripe for our voyage.
The waves...
To the waves!
We sail for battle!
Beloved friends, warriors...
the time has come to save our people!
To war!
Hey, hey! I've told you before,
codfish on top of codfish.
Lord? Do you see something?
No.
But something's changed.
The air is rotten.
That could be me eating too much cabbage.
Something feels wrong.
I don't like it.
Lord! Lord!
This one says he can't pay.
Sea raiders robbed me.
Let me guess.
The Great Rognvaldr seized his silver.
He wants to trade the border,
he pays Mercia a toll.
He says you still have to pay!
In coin. No produce.
And no tin from Cornwallum
pretending to be coin.
Iron Lord there.
We have soldiers to feed.
It could be a lean winter.
All the more reason
to celebrate while we can.
It's Blood Month festival.
I need ale and you need
to hump the tall girl from Frisia.
The tall girl from Frisia's too tall.
It's border country, Lord.
You don't get to be too picky.
Aethelstan!
Why have you left your post?
- His first hunt, Lord.
- It's good luck for Blood Month, Uhtred.
You think you're ready
to slaughter a beast?
You know I am.
Aethelstan says he's ready.
What do you say?
Yes?
- For Blood Month!
Be careful.
The animal will fight to the death.
Or try to hump you.
Let's go kill the swine! Kill the beast!
- Blood Month!
Blood Month!
Blood Month! Blood Month!
Blood Month! Blood Month! Blood Month!
- Away with you!
- Blood Month!
Blood Month! Blood Month! Blood Month...
Leave him. He's a man now.
I should like to see it.
Lord, I, uh, need a little help.
I'll kill you!
- Come here!
- Swine!
Again?
Come here, bitch!
- Right! Hey, hey! Easy, easy!
- He's mine! He's mine!
Split it up. Come on. Come on!
Get off me, you dirty whore!
- Why do they fight over you?
- I... I'm...
I've got no idea, Lord.
Finan! Get your arse over here!
It's 'cause all the best men
are spoken for.
Keep the peace!
We're here to secure the border,
not kick the arses of drunk women!
You can kick my arse anytime.
I'm going hunting with the men.
Go on, then.
Hey!
Here, piggy, piggy!
Here, piggy! Whoa, whoa, whoa!
Woo, woo!
- Ow!
- Aethelstan, you madman, you!
Piggy, piggy, piggy!
Aethelstan!
Whose men are you?
Finish him!
Come on.
Uhtred!
Do you hear that?
Aethelstan!
Bastard?
He's here!
Aethelstan!
Uhtred!
Bastard! Where are you?
How many men?
There were three.
One escaped.
- No sign this way.
- Who were they?
Not from here.
- Are you hurt?
- No.
You took three men... alone?
Yes.
What did I say?
I told you!
Let me go downriver
and fight the sea raiders.
No. You're not ready.
Take him to the alehouse.
Celebrate his victory.
You had us worried there
for a second, boy.
Just a scratch. Come on!
- Tonight we dine in Rumcofa.
- You're the one not ready.
He's still a virgin though!
http://hiqve.com/
He will redeem us all!
You must follow. You must read this.
We will all perish. We will all perish.
God! There is one God!
You, lady, redeem your heathen forebears.
Return Jorvik to its Christian heart!
Restore the name of Eoferwic.
Danes, hear me!
There is only one God.
How long can they do this?
Every day the same sermon.
King Edward pays them well.
King Edward steals your people from you.
You are ruler here. Tell them to leave.
And signal that it troubles us?
A worthless fight.
If I am to be provoked, it will take more
than an old man trying to extract coin.
They're not just raising coin.
They poke at our gods.
Our gods can withstand it.
He's taking your kingdom
one convert at a time.
We're supposed to be at peace.
Yes and the peace means
that we are breeding at twice their speed.
We grow our town.
We build a country for generations.
We ignore old men.
Could we not have them beaten,
just for good measure?
Maybe.
Once they've collected enough silver.
They hide it in the sewers.
Think we do not know.
You accept too much.
And you too little, my queen.
Come on, Christian, fight me!
Not all Danes want to keep the peace.
Fight me!
Did Jesus cut your cock off, hmm?
- Is that my brother Rognvaldr?
- Back from the dead. Once again.
King Sigtryggr!
Show yourself!
The Great Raider Rognvaldr!
Who have you enraged this time?
No one!
I am completely reformed!
A man of peace.
We heard you drowned off Scotland.
That was last year.
I heard you needed a kick in the arse.
Letting Christians roam your lands?
Ignore them. They are harmless.
Am I welcome?
I will warn the serving women.
You're welcome.
Jesus loves you!
Wolland!
Did you miss me?
- Let's get him to bed.
- Prepare the chamber with no fire.
- That should keep his visit short.
- Bring him in!
Hella, if he tries anything this time,
I will cut his hands off myself.
Make it known that there will be a curfew
until the visit
of the Lady of Mercia is over.
Lord, it is Blood Month.
Yes, they will have to hump each other
in daylight.
Why the caution? They were just
sea raiders trying their luck upriver.
- They could have attacked anyone.
- But they did not.
They chose the eldest son
of the King of Wessex.
Who actually knows that? Up here,
he's more arseling than aetheling.
Perhaps.
Perhaps they were just raiders
in search of coin, perhaps not.
There've been signs. The air has changed.
Well, that is definitely a bad sign.
Yes. When Aethelflaed
comes for the festival,
she's bringing us a priest,
a Father Benedict.
Lodge them near the cornfield, show them
the East Well, and hide the strong ale.
But it's the festival.
She thinks Rumcofa
shames Mercia with its heathen ways.
Uhtred! A ship, it's turned in
from the sea, which we cannot identify.
Then the soldiers will be ready.
Why would anyone attack
before the lady arrives?
Line the riverbank. Prepare.
Whoa.
Right, come on. Move.
It's Rognvaldr come to slaughter.
Will you stop?
You'll unsettle all the men.
Rognvaldr is nothing.
- He's just a coward who buys reputation.
- Trust us. We've fought a lot of Danes.
Am I mistaken, or is that Eadith?
We are travelers and traders!
Happy to pay the toll!
Hindr. Look after your sister.
Hey, hey,
don't let the chickens run away.
You remember Osferth.
Yes.
And that little one is Aethelstan.
Surely not!
Oh, you were a very solemn child.
- Yes, he beat it out of me.
- Thank you.
Cynlaef.
Those two are always up to no good.
- Go and annoy Uncle Finan.
- Sidgeflaed, who's married to Sihtric.
- Hello.
- Just call me Sig.
And all the little Sigs
and Sihtrics that populate this town.
- Oh, my God.
- And this is Ingrith.
Finan's wife.
- Eadith.
- I have heard of you.
What brings you to Rumcofa?
I have learned much in Frankia
in the ways of healing.
And I hear Rumcofa
is riddled with disease.
Oh, that's all Osferth's work.
So, uh, no husband, then?
No. No, my silver's all my own.
Hey, I'd watch yourself.
Our turds have baffled every healer
from here to Frisia.
You're telling me!
Hey!
Not on your child!
Eadith, tell me, what were they like
before we civilized them?
Much the same. This one less so perhaps.
Is the king really happy with his son
living among soldiers?
We tend not to mention that.
- No shame in being a bastard boy.
- Whoa!
Yes, much has changed.
- No. Uhtred's still the same.
- What?
He's not married either.
Escort them to the lodging house.
And do not get into any fights
with any young monks.
It's not my reputation men wish to test.
I trained you for battles,
not for ale yard brawls.
Look, I know you seek
to protect me.
I know that, but you were sworn
to protect a child and I'm not.
Yet I made a promise
to your father, the king.
So, only a king can relieve me
of that oath.
Our bond holds fast. Go.
Pleasant surprise.
- Hmm?
- Eadith.
Though I'm wary of surprises
so close to Aethelflaed's visit.
Eadith is a... friend.
People can change.
The attack on Aethelstan...
I do not think it was chance.
Someone trying to get rid of him
now he's of age?
- Maybe just someone trying to frighten me.
- And are you frightened?
No. But I expect worse.
Lord, you're brooding.
My wife thinks it's the change
of the seasons getting to you.
We have scouts at every lookout point
from here to the burh at Thelwall.
Hey, hump the tall girl.
Has he finally revealed what he wants?
Not yet. He is still boasting
of his escape from the sea.
- He says the gods sent men to save him.
- He always has a tale to tell.
Do you know he pays sailors
to say they fear him?
Better a lying rogue
than a killer.
You're too tender.
Send him on his way.
And break an oath of hospitality, my love?
Wake up! You're in Valhalla!
Wolland, get him to bed.
Time for sleep.
Stop.
We do not want to see your arse.
She's cold, your woman.
We should set to feasting alone,
talk as kin.
I have learned much since last I saw you.
Changed myself.
Things have happened to me.
The gods chose to save me.
We are never divided at feasting.
We will feast, you and I.
When you are sober, we will feast, hmm?
Why do you agree
when he seeks to come between us?
Stiorra.
What he suffered,
when I left him alone in Irland...
...you too would have
a spirit broken.
He boasts because the gods
have not favored him.
That doesn't mean you should.
He is my brother and so I honor him.
For all his faults, our blood is shared.
Blame the Christians.
They have spoken too much of forgiveness.
Uh...
Oh, were you expecting a rather tall girl?
Yes!
She asked me to exchange rooms
because this bed was too short.
- That would explain it.
- Yes. Ooh!
Keep at your right hand
the souls of kings.
Alfred, known as the Wise,
and Aethelred of Mercia.
Bless my daughter, Aelfwynn of Mercia.
May she learn to resist temptation.
I pray for my brother, the King of Wessex.
Guide him well and hear my entreaty
on behalf of my mother, Aelswith,
wife to Alfred.
Why are you praying for me?
What do you think is wrong with me?
I do not think anything
is wrong with you. I...
- Does it look white?
- No, Mother, it looks quite normal.
This breeze will stiffen my neck.
Lord knows what ailments
lurk within Rumcofa.
Perhaps we should return to Aegelesburg?
Uh, the Lord wants us
in Rumcofa for festival.
Which Lord? Lord Uhtred?
Do not fight her, it wastes your time.
Is something wrong with you?
No, Mother. I am just stiff from riding.
Lord Aldhelm, Father Benedict...
Ready to bring the faith
to this dark corner of our land?
Where you lead, we follow, Lady.
In you get!
Are these people
heading for Rumcofa?
Blood Month is wild in these parts.
That's why Lady Aethelflaed wants to find
a way to make it more Christian.
Well, it falls near Martinmas.
Perhaps we could enlighten them.
They would talk in Rome
of these Northern tribes
that they could be resistant.
Is the reputation deserved?
The lady is fond of both you
and of Rumcofa.
She will not place you
somewhere you would not thrive.
Uhtred!
Lady Aethelflaed is arriving.
So, that's your cousin?
Yes. Go and help
the Lady Aelfwynn off her horse.
Of course.
Lady Aelfwynn, I'm Cynlaef.
I was sorry to miss you
on our last visit south. I was...
You were making a treaty
with the Scots, I know. Important.
Yes, it was.
Still, the timing was unfortunate.
Not much has changed here in two summers.
The soldiers thrive, so does the town.
Occasional raids, much trade.
- And you look well.
- That's life in the open air.
Perhaps I should try it.
- The Witan like to talk.
- You still look beautiful.
Behold our gift.
Rumcofa does not need a priest.
No, but Father Benedict
needs a new place to preach.
- Did he hump someone?
- No.
No, nothing like that.
He's an exceptionally gifted scholar.
He's a gambler.
He gambled all his alms money in Rome.
- Then in Canterbury. Then with us.
- So put him where he can do no damage?
Welcome to our chapel.
Aethelflaed, look.
Look how fine he has become.
Is he not the image of his father?
You have the light of prayer
shining through you.
And quite the swordsman now, I hear.
Is it true you were attacked?
By raiders, yes, but I'm being
sent to fight them on the seas.
No, he's not.
Lady Aelswith, how's your stomach?
I survive, but still, I should like us
to avoid too many commoners.
For fear of passing them
my many afflictions.
Aelfwynn!
Lady Aelswith remains cautious
in matters of health.
- Lady Aelfwynn.
- Lord Uhtred.
Is the border secure?
Yes. Aethelstan... was just thieves.
Still, we're concerned.
Uh, we've heard of a raider
plundering at sea, a Rognvaldr.
Rognvaldr is not a threat.
He's a boastful turd.
Ask his brother Sigtryggr.
We will not be seeking
the word of Sigtryggr.
- Not concerning Danes on the border.
- Why? The alliance has held.
Uhtred, we know
Sigtryggr is family to you,
but that does not mean
Mercia has to trust him.
This Rognvaldr harries north of our coast.
We fear he may strike...
Sigtryggr will not allow him to cause
real trouble. He extracts coin, no more.
Tell that to the widows
of the men that we've lost.
Thirty of them off the coast
of Cumbraland.
Men massacred and not for silver,
but to avenge the gods, they said.
I have to be more wary of the Dane.
Heathen threat. I know many Danes
live here in Rumcofa in peace.
Live in peace, trade, marry our men.
- The Danes are no danger here.
- But this Dane is.
Maybe we know things you do not.
These past weeks,
there have been stories, mutilations.
Raiders seen with white marking
on their faces.
I do not think
that is the work of Rognvaldr.
They may speak it of him,
but that does not make it true.
Who then?
We have received no word
of mourning from Rumcofa.
Yes. It did not quite work out.
- Does Aethelstan live?
- He was a tough little bastard.
Did you try?
I lost two of my best men.
Don't blame me.
Blame Uhtred of Bebbanburg.
If you have the silver,
I can try something else.
I hear the lad can be provoked
into a scrap in an alehouse.
Mm-mmm. No.
No, it's too soon.
I'll call on you when I'm ready.
In the meantime, find out what is said
among the common people
of my grandson Aelfweard.
No one speaks of him, Lord.
Then spread his name. For his protection.
I have seen enough to know
that when two boys have one claim,
both cannot thrive.
Where am I next?
The ambassadors
from the Duchy of Lotharingia.
Oh.
I can make an excuse, but you'd have
to meet a visionary from Lewes.
She saw St. Cuthbert in a cabbage patch.
What? Ambassadors it is.
She looks like
she's hawking fishes in Cheap Street.
Lord King.
The queen is playing matchmaker.
She is keen that her sisters find husbands
that will do you honor, Lord King.
Mmm.
Will you be introducing them
to Aelfweard as the aetheling?
- And why would I do that?
- My grandson is coming of age.
It would signal abroad
that your dynasty is prepared.
And alarm people
by mooting the succession.
No, I'm still a young man myself.
Aelfweard, introduce Lord Aethelhelm
to the guests on my behalf.
Explain he is a respected elder
of the family.
Yes, Father. Of course.
I'm sure they'll love your stories
from the old days.
Well, perhaps I should advise her
on making suitable alliances.
Indeed. There's nothing worse than being
landed with a spouse you come to detest.
Welcome.
Please.
My darling boy.
Did you suggest that Aelfweard
be introduced as aetheling?
Yes. Uh, he refused.
And the other aspect of our plan
has become problematic.
Aethelstan fought back.
Of course.
'Cause they are training him to become
a killer who will one day come for us.
Calm yourself.
All of Wessex
favors Aelfweard as aetheling.
That will sway things if there is
any contention in the matter.
For now the king looks more
to other women every day.
Ah, I shall remove her.
Like you removed Lady Aelswith?
Lady Aelswith's...
...strong constitution
is a blessing to us all.
My grandfather, Lord Aethelhelm.
You have recovered.
Indeed, and my regret if I broke
the conditions of my welcome.
I am sworn from ale these days,
but...
...sometimes...
What is it you want?
Stiorra.
He only visits when he wants something.
Make your demands and then leave us be.
You are right. She sees everything.
I seek safe harbor for some of my people.
They have been accused of raiding
and, I believe, unfairly.
I wish for them to prove
their innocence here, under Danelaw.
And I have agreed.
I will send out Wolland
with some guard to bring them in,
ensure they cause no trouble.
As you command, Lord.
The Saxons always look for reasons
to make incursions.
This will show them
that our borders must be respected
and that we govern here
with justice under the law.
Mmm. And remind the Christians
you're not to be moved.
And that we intend to rule here
for many years to come.
My lady, a dance?
Why so troubled?
I wish you had stayed in Aegelesburg.
And miss Blood Month festival? Never.
You did not come for the festival.
What did you come for?
What is here that is not there?
Some say I came to see you.
I wish that were true,
but I think it is not.
- Is there a threat to you I should know?
- No more than the usual.
You're certain?
Yes.
Besides, you have protected us well here.
You have scouts on the bankside
and on every road.
We would not lie about a threat
to me or to Rumcofa.
Ready?
- He's not going to say prayers, is he?
- I just asked for a few simple words.
And in this moment,
Rumcofa came under God!
It may be harder than that
to douse the pagan flame.
...virgin and mother,
for these pigs...
...and these chickens, Gods!
Make sure he gives that back.
We pray for fertility, the rising of sun,
the waxing of the moon...
Why did he choose
the Lorica ofLoding?
We shall catch our deaths in this draft.
Just smile and wait for it to pass.
...defend me
on every side.
Skull, head, hair and eyes,
mouth, tongue...
teeth and their covering.
Neck, breast, side.
For the crown of my head with its hair,
be thou the helmet of salvation
on the head.
Yes!
For forehead, eyes, nostrils...
bowels...
Waist!
Oh, please.
For my limbs, for my entrails,
thou mayest thrust back from me
the invisible nails of stakes.
Eyes, triform brain...
nose, face, teeth, the chin...
...beard, eyebrows, ears, cheeks.
Make way! Move!
Stand back!
Who is it?
- Who is it? Children, stay back.
- What have they done to him?
Father...
- Help him!
- Who did this to you? Rognvaldr?
Brida.
Find her. Find her.
Raise the alarm. Now!
Son.
My son.
Lord Jesus Christ, in a rich man's house.
A fallen woman cried
as she dried his feet...
Why allow your people to be converted?
Why not keep Daneland for Danes?
Is it because of your wife?
Since when have you cared so much
for the gods?
I told you, much has changed
this last year.
I was close to death
and not for the first time.
- I am sorry that you suffered.
- But this time, I was reborn.
The gods sent men to my rescue.
They took to a land of fire.
And there I learnt how to be loyal
to them and to my people.
But you do not care for loyalty.
He blesses you and the Lord Jesus.
Have these missionaries sent
back to Wessex tomorrow. That's enough.
Lord, yes, Lord.
I... But I...
I speak here every night.
We've always been allowed to preach here.
You are too accepting of enemies.
No, I am not.
It is more difficult to live peacefully
with enemies than to fight them.
Do you pity me?
I think you suffer without my guidance.
That is Wolland.
Show me those who follow you.
This can be resolved.
Strongest bow, sharpest spear
He who rules heaven and earth
My Lord!
Sigtryggr!
Open the gates.
Are these your people?
What do you want?
Not mine. Hers.
All Danes, all pure.
Do not be afraid, brother.
She's here to save us.
Where are my men?
Valhalla!
Danes of Jorvik who turned to Christ...
we are here to return you to the gods!
Where is she?
Find Stiorra. Find Uhtred's daughter.
Brida!
We're ready for you!
http://hiqve.com/