I am Uhtred, son of Uhtred.
Aethelhelm succeeded in starting
a war between Saxon and Dane.
But his treachery was discovered.
Sigtryggr did not kill the queen.
It was the work of Aethelhelm's men.
He must be apprehended.
Seeking to weaken
the Saxon forces,
Sigtryggr marched boldly into battle
and took the fight Aethelhelm's men.
But Edward's arrival turned the tide.
I rode for peace and Sigtryggr
has repaid us with more bloodshed.
They must be saved.
While Aethelhelm escaped,
Sigtryggr was taken prisoner.
You must accept the gift of baptism.
I cannot.
And I was given the gravest duty.
You must be the one to do it.
That Sigtryggr
might reach Valhalla.
Brida's desire for vengeance
is as strong as ever.
Tell him I'm coming for him.
And a new threat
has emerged in the north.
King Constantin of Scotland
has formed an alliance
with the lords ofNorthumbria,
disputed territory he claims as his own.
This is a moment to join as one.
Among them is my cousin Wihtgar,
who murdered his father
to steal my birthright for himself.
Destiny is all!
My queen.
Do not forget me on this,
your final journey.
Your blade and my heart will remain yours.
Tonight all love is buried.
Sigtryggr, you lived as a warrior!
And you died... a king!
Sigtryggr!
We should unite in grief.
My grief is that you lived and he did not.
Leave her be.
May we die as you did!
With honor in our hearts
and laughter in our throats!
May you sail safely to Valhalla...
...where we will drink with you again!
We will meet again!
To Valhalla!
To Sigtryggr!
Have you seen Father?
The Warrior Priest of Rumcofa.
He showed great courage.
And made Osferth proud.
I have heard of your bravery.
Let us drink to it.
I bring news I do not wish to break.
Brida has struck again.
If he survives the night,
he does so at God's mercy.
We're all here, Pyrlig.
You are with friends.
Uhtred... she wants to punish you.
She will not rest.
Fetch Aethelstan. We will need his guard.
We'll hunt her down. We'll kill her.
- Have they found the witch?
- No, Lord King.
And how does one woman hide
from the Mercian Guard?
I do not know,
but Uhtred and his men will find her.
And Aethelhelm,
does he still wander my lands?
Also no news as yet.
Rumors he is heading south.
Of course he is.
He will try to raise a rebellion.
- Can Pyrlig travel?
- No.
Then we shall have to leave him here.
Is it wise to leave Eoferwic
while Brida roams?
It depends on your feelings
towards Aethelhelm seizing Winchester.
That will be his plan. We must get south.
Was Aelfweard informed
of Aethelhelm's treachery?
We felt that was news for you to break.
Indeed. My son has been
through far too much of late
and to hear of this
would only wound him further.
Lord, I understand your reasons to leave,
but I must stress
I am concerned for Eoferwic.
You saw yourself
the atmosphere is febrile.
Indeed.
How differently the Danes mark death.
If we abandon Eoferwic,
then our men who died defeating Sigtryggr
will have done so for nothing.
Secure Eoferwic...
and we have the opportunity
to foray further north,
bring the entirety of Northumbria
under your command,
- fulfill the dream of every Saxon...
- It will mean nothing
if we lose Wessex to Aethelhelm.
The people here are volatile,
the mood not favorable.
Much pain is felt for the Lady Stiorra
and I fear her grief
could ferment more trouble.
- Add Brida to that and...
- The air is poisoned. I understand.
If sympathy for the young widow
is the problem, that can be resolved.
Summon Lord Uhtred.
Do not ask. We did not find her.
Perhaps she's left these lands.
Pyrlig could not have traveled far
with his injuries. She's still near.
She knows that to return
to Eoferwic means certain death.
She's ruthless, but she's not foolish.
Rest the horses. We will ride out again.
Uhtred, you are summoned to the king.
There is no news. That is the news.
Nonetheless, his word stands. Come.
Lord Uhtred.
I bring you nothing.
No Brida, no Aethelhelm,
no change in Pyrlig.
How then are the Danes?
Danes of Eoferwic.
Since when have you cared for them?
Since I became their king.
I know it sounds a little strange.
To rule Danes was not my expectation.
You've always coveted these lands.
Indeed, but my hope was
that a conquest would be peaceful,
that the people would live side by side.
That became difficult
when you martyred their king.
Yes. I see the King's widow has a grief
that would move the stoniest of hearts.
She's young. She loved him very much.
She has lost a great deal,
her future, her status, her home.
All of which she would forgo
to have the man.
Still, her grief
could become a touchstone.
Perhaps it is wise
she hide it a little better.
That is impossible.
Perhaps then I can offer her a salve.
I need to take my household south,
to sit again on the throne in Wessex.
- You fear Aethelhelm...
- I fear no one.
But I suspect Aethelhelm
will fuel dissent,
which is why I need Eoferwic at peace.
Tell that to Brida.
I'm sure she will comply with your wishes.
I do not expect Brida to comply,
but I would hope Stiorra might.
What is it you want her to do?
Tell her to swear to me, publicly,
to bring comfort to the Danes
that all is resolved between us.
The people here
have endured too much for that.
We have all endured too much.
She could lead the Danes
as your sister led in Mercia.
It could give her some purpose.
It could restore something...
As long as her purpose
is not to lead them against me.
I do not think
she has an appetite for rebellion.
But she will not take a baptism.
My father ensured
she was baptized as a girl,
so she is already saved.
I see no need to do that again.
I must be acknowledged
as the true overlord of Eoferwic.
And in return, she has your protection?
- Yes.
- Then I will tell her to comply.
Thank you, Lord King.
It is an honor
I know my daughter will not be expecting.
If we cannot honor our greatest warriors,
we cannot be great kings.
God is merciful. That is her horse.
She will be close by.
Wait here in case she returns to it.
We will look for her.
Lady Aelfwynn? It is you.
You are Aelfwynn of Mercia.
You... you confuse me for another.
Surely not. I am... I am Glaedwine.
I too am of Mercia.
I was errand boy to your mother.
My heart grieves for your loss.
If you did once serve my mother,
then do as I ask and leave me alone.
My lady, are you in trouble?
My grandmother would imprison me
in a convent for my own safety.
Then it is well that our paths
have crossed, my lady.
I have been tasked to serve you
and to protect you.
Tasked by whom?
Someone who cares for you very much.
Cynlaef? He lives?
- He's been searching for you.
- I thought he was...
Well, let us make haste.
I fear Lady Aelswith's guard are near.
Where is he? Where's Cynlaef?
This way, my lady.
Go on.
Lady Aelfwynn?
I thought you said
Cynlaef was going to be here.
Never trust a handsome man,
my lady Aelfwynn.
They only want to hump you or rob you.
There. The elder is the man
who approached me in Aegelesburg,
who offered me silver for Aelfwynn.
We have met before, have we not?
Lady Eadith.
One alehouse whore is much like another.
She is no whore.
It is unwise to insult a lady
who travels defended by Mercian Guard.
She's no friend of yours.
She took silver from me
in exchange for news of your whereabouts.
Then may your charity be returned
in exchange for Aelfwynn.
This is no business of yours, witch.
Perhaps not of hers,
but as Aelfwynn is my granddaughter,
it is most definitely business of mine.
Lady Aelswith, I did not recognize you.
It is an honor to keep the company
of your granddaughter.
You may keep the silver
as reward for finding her.
He was too reasonable.
You underestimate how men crumble
in the face of Alfred's widow.
Anyway, fear not. Our guards are close.
It would be ill-advised
to cry out for help.
I ask for just one moment!
I wish only to speak to her as a brother!
And yet the word of her father
must come first.
Please tell me Brida is your captive.
I cannot.
Then tell me she will be mine
so that I may punish her.
She is the source of all our sorrows.
Then do not think on her.
Better to think on the one who started it
than on the one who dealt the final blow.
I'm in grief for Sigtryggr, too,
and you know this.
You have been wronged by many things,
but this anger will destroy you.
Destroy what?
I am nothing.
A wife to no one, a queen to nowhere.
Yet you are still a daughter...
with a father who would do anything
to make this right.
I cannot raise the dead,
but I can raise you from your grief.
I think you could find
some solace in comfort.
That is all I want, Father.
And so there is an offer.
Edward proposes that you be lady here
and rule for him in his stead.
You would not be queen,
but Eoferwic would look to you.
What does Edward want in return?
- You must swear allegiance and forgive...
- I do not forgive. I cannot in my heart.
Then forgive with your mouth
and let your heart keep silent.
I am no more an oath-breaker than you are.
Yes, but you are a woman alone
and I am not.
As your father,
I can offer some protection.
- But the day will come...
- When you'll be called elsewhere
and I will be left as a target,
as was always true.
Please, see that you need to do this.
For you to thrive, I want you to accept.
Who are they? Why have they taken us?
Your uncle wants you concealed
so you do not threaten the Mercian throne.
No, my son is shrewd
and if he felt she was a threat,
he would keep her close.
Not use hired men on the road.
Only a wealthy coward would pay men to...
Oh, you foolish woman.
Aethelhelm.
He is as rich as he is cunning.
Only he would be so bold
to arrange the seizing of a lady,
a former queen and a...
Well, he did not know
you were going to be here.
- That is a great comfort.
- What would Aethelhelm want with me?
I do not know, but I am certain
I have no wish to find out.
How do we resist?
We have no weapons, no plan.
That is not completely true.
People have come for my life
on other occasions.
Of course I am schooled
in how to protect myself.
Aelfwynn, do not fear.
They look at us and they see
weak and feeble women,
but therein lies our strength.
Aethelhelm and his men
are fools to underestimate us.
We have pledged our allegiance.
Why does the king not let us leave?
He is swinging his cock around.
I'm not even certain he has a plan.
Do you think
there will be war with Wessex?
No.
Peace serves both kings better.
We stay here, kiss arses, go home.
That old goat's not of Northumbria.
Just another lord whose balls
hang lower than his coin purse.
Lord King.
They call me the Dane-humper,
but I'm fairly sure they're assassins.
You Edward's ambassador?
I am from Wessex, yes. Lord Aethelhelm.
Well, show me the gift.
My humble apologies, Lord King,
there is no gift.
No toe of St. Cuthbert
or bread from the Last Supper?
The king is not sure you appreciate
holy relics in Scotland.
Hmm.
Did he tell you to say that?
To insult me?
Forgive me. I'm just the messenger.
I've heard of his conquest of Mercia.
Does the treaty I made
with Aethelflaed still stand?
The king has not spoken to me of a treaty.
Then he intends to come north?
Again, not something he has spoken of.
Why send an ambassador
who claims to know nothing?
What game is this?
Does he want me to cut your head off
and send it back?
Lord King, you seem to be a man
who knows the quality of mercy.
I therefore throw myself
upon your compassion.
I come to give you fair warning.
Of?
I fear King Edward's eye
wanders northwards...
to Northumbria and to Scotland.
And these ambitions are not shared by me.
So you're telling me this
out of the goodness of your heart.
No.
I do not need warning.
We are already prepared.
Half the lords of Northumbria
are sworn to me.
So if it is war you wish to avert,
you have picked
the wrong king to dissuade.
You misunderstand me.
I do not come for peace.
Well, what, then? What is this trickery?
It's a bluff.
I know Edward is your family,
husband to your daughter!
And that...
that is the thing.
Forgive me, Lord King,
for she was murdered!
News of the queen's death
had yet to reach my ears.
Edward would have Wessex believe
it was Danes.
So...
it is vengeance you seek?
Lord King, if I...
The king is merciless
in his pursuit of land.
You see that
from his disposal of the ealdormen,
his behavior toward Sigtryggr.
He sees enemies everywhere,
even in my grandson, his heir,
Aelfweard, a sweet Christian boy,
whose ambitions would stretch
no further than Wessex and Mercia.
What plan are you trying to sell me,
Lord Aethelhelm?
You help me raise rebellion
against the king,
we put my grandson
on the throne in Wessex.
Aelfweard, under my guidance,
guarantees no incursions into Scotland.
Your lands are safe, as are his.
I have no interest in playing kingmaker
in Saxon lands.
One king is much like another.
Which is why we would offer
more than just a treaty.
We would offer half the profits
from the lands of Mercia
through a marriage bond
to the Lady Aelfwynn.
The lands are
prosperous and fertile, as is the girl.
Edward is dangerous
and committed to expansion.
He is haunted
by this dream of his father's,
to unite the kingdoms
in one so-called England.
If you do not strike now...
the opportunity may not arise again.
Leave me to dwell on it
and speak to my commanders.
But do not go far.
You have intrigued me, Lord Aethelhelm.
And that is no inconsiderable feat.
I can do it when they're asleep.
They will know nothing of it.
We let them live, it will not be a guard
chasing us. It will be an army.
Killing royal women does not end well.
This I know.
But you are right.
If we do not, we will be hunted.
They are planning to kill us.
We do not know that.
We are too powerful
to be left to tell the tale.
They know what forces I can raise.
If we are going to act, it has to be now.
I, um...
I must...
I have no polite word for it.
Take a piss?
That oak needs watering.
Where she can be witnessed?
It wouldn't do well
to deliver your cargo soiled, would it?
Walk.
Now.
- Where are you taking us?
- Sit down.
To whom are we to be delivered?
Answer me.
Sit down.
Or I will make you sit down. Huh?
Do not fight it!
Death is the destiny of all men.
We are not men,
and we are not so easy to kill!
Did you see?
I felt like Saint Michael the Archangel
when he slew Satan's armies.
Begone or I shall slay you also!
Aelfwynn! Run!
No! Grandmother! Help me! Grandmother!
Have them prepare for a ceremony.
Invite whichever Danes
are most appropriate.
Stiorra can swear as they bear witness.
It should calm the waters.
It's a wise plan.
Why is there not a place set
for Lady Eadgifu?
It was my understanding
you had sent her away.
No, that is not correct.
Well, her servants were told
not to unpack but to turn back.
- Why did they not unpack?
- My Lord.
My Lord, I am returning to Cent.
I am not at ease here.
My love, I would not bring you
somewhere that was not safe.
It is not any danger I fear.
It is your wrath.
So, please, let me on my way.
It is for the best.
Why do you flee me now?
I'm not fleeing you.
I am sparing you the trouble
of sending me away.
We have been both blessed and cursed.
No, it cannot be. It shall not stand.
There can be no more bastards.
I understand, which is why I leave.
Why do you speak so coldly?
Would you have me weep and bawl?
I am not a mewling babe.
I knew what I did...
and...
I take my punishment proudly
to give thanks to God
for the small time we have had together.
I said...
there can be no more bastards.
God has blessed us.
I know not why, but...
perhaps this is the reason
we have suffered so much grief.
Perhaps the taking of Aelflaed
was part of this design.
Perhaps he decided that we are to be wed.
Let us fetch a priest.
Love is patient and is...
The love kind.
Love not copies.
Not being boastful. Not arrogant.
Amen.
- So soon, Father?
- Aelfweard.
My mother replaced
while she lies warm in her grave?
God has sent us an unexpected blessing.
So I am to be replaced also.
Aelfweard, return.
I command you come back here!
Allow him to grieve his mother.
Find him. Comfort him.
But remind him of his duty.
I shall not stomach a disobedient child.
http://hiqve.com/
I have been asked to comfort you.
There is no comfort, Father.
The king loves you.
Talk with him and you will know it.
His actions speak differently.
He does not want me to be king,
and he felt no love for my poor mother.
What can I do, child?
Heal your spirit, hmm?
Seek help from me and you will find it.
There is one thing, but you will refuse.
Ask.
I need to travel from here.
If I journey with a priest, I am less
likely to be questioned or troubled.
Journey to where?
To join my grandfather.
I cannot help you.
I do not know where he is.
But I do.
I know how to find him,
I know which men he pays and who to ask.
I only request
that I do not travel to him alone.
Much as I seek to soothe your troubles,
I urge you to stay.
And I would urge you
to pay your debt to my grandfather.
He tells me of those who are his men,
who owe him favors.
I am not Lord Aethelhelm's man.
Would the king see it that way?
If I told him of the debt...
- Are you prepared?
- No.
Why must I be paraded like a prize?
It is a show of unity, nothing more.
Do this one thing and it is over.
You can resume your life here,
live as a lady.
I know how hard this is,
but pride is what drove Brida
to the darkness.
Kneel before your king.
I know that it is wise for me to kneel.
But my heart will not allow it.
I am sorry.
I was told you were agreed.
I was trying to honor my father's wish.
But to honor him
is to dishonor my husband.
And it is a destruction of everything
we have built here in Eoferwic.
I do not believe
you will let Danes live here in peace.
If you will not show loyalty to the king,
then you will face the consequence.
- Do not do this.
- You have done this to humiliate me.
I returned to you your dignity.
You would have lived in comfort.
The only thing I want
you cannot give to me.
- Stiorra, this is foolish...
- N o!
I will not crumble just to be protected.
I will be free.
And if that freedom is only to face
the executioner's blade, then so be it!
- I shall join my husband.
- N o!
Lord King, you gave your word
on the battlefield
that her life would be spared.
You and all who follow you
are to be exiled from Eoferwic.
Those who wish to stay live at my behest!
But if you are not gone by sunset...
I will not be so generous.
- Stiorra!
- Bring Rognvaldr to me! Have him kneel!
Put a sword to his throat if he does not!
Give me time. I can make this right.
Rognvaldr will betray you.
- You know this...
- Then I shall execute him
and find another and another and another
until I can turn my back
on this wretched town forever.
I advise you do the same.
Stiorra.
Edward now offers Eoferwic to Rognvaldr.
You want this for your people?
He will make war, take tribute,
use the children as his slaves,
just as he meant to
when he brought Brida here.
You give this to him,
you undo all we have fought for.
He abuses the people and the people
leave in search of their true queen.
Rognvaldr will rule nothing.
They shall come to me.
Please do not lose everything
in a futile pursuit of dignity.
I am your daughter.
I was bred to follow honor.
Do not make me do things
that you would not.
Swearing to the Saxons
pulled you from your destiny,
made you the plaything of Brida
and the arseling of the House of Wessex.
- What?
- That fate will not be mine.
Hey, drop your sword!
- Please go to her. Speak with her.
- She will not listen to me.
Her heart is broken, as is her spirit.
- I will pray for her instead.
- Why is she doing this?
What made her so headstrong?
Do you really not know?
Lord, it's Brida.
- She has a message for you.
- Speak it.
It was to meet at Loidis.
Come alone.
That's it? Loidis? Nothing more?
- No.
- I know where she is.
Lord...
Lord, do not do this alone. It's a trap.
Of course it is a trap.
Our destinies have been entwined
since we were children.
Either she kills me or I kill her.
Take a moment to consider this.
Oh, believe me,
it has been on my mind a long while.
Kill her and her death will haunt you.
Instead you can choose compassion.
I have compassion
for the innocents she kills.
- If I had taken her life before then...
- It is not our place to reason why.
Only to forgive Brida in spite of it.
Hate only begets more hate.
Every death she has caused
since I spared her at Tettenhall
is blood on my hands.
Then you must absolve her of blame
and yourself.
Or you will never find peace.
Swear to me.
Swear to me you will not kill her.
Take her captive.
Make her face those she has wronged.
Father, do not kill her.
I will take no pleasure in it.
It is just the way things must be.
Open the gates!
Good, you are both here.
Lord King, I think our discussions would
be wisest had between the two of us...
We've agreed the principles. Lord Wihtgar
here will help us with the practicalities.
You will escort Lord Aethelhelm
to your fortress as a guest.
There he will prepare the betrothal
and await my arrival.
You will give him every courtesy
because he has promised me much
and would not be so foolish
as to not deliver.
We swore allegiance to you,
Lord King, not...
Lord Wihtgar...
I cannot place you.
I'm presuming your fortress
is one of strategic use.
You've probably heard of it.
It's called Bebbanburg.
You are the man that torments Uhtred?
I had expected someone different.
Brida!
Show yourself!
You dig your own grave?
Mine...
or yours.
I'm prepared.
Either way, it ends where it began.
It did not have to be this way.
Funny.
That's what your son said
when he begged to keep his balls.
At some point,
I will see you on the battlefield.
I won't hesitate to kill you.
It does not mean you do not love me.
Uhtred! Give me death.
Vibeke is waiting for me.
Stop this! It is over.
It is never over!
Uhtred.
Uhtred! Uhtred, kill me. Come on!
Come on. You must kill me.
I have nothing left to live for!
I won't stop. I won't stop, Uhtred.
Something has died
within me, Uhtred.
What are you waiting for? Kill me, please.
No!
I will not kill you.
If my son could forgive you
after what you have done to him...
...then I must do the same.
No. No, come on. No, no, do it.
Do it, you coward.
Do it. Do as I ask for.
Send me to Valhalla.
- Do it!
- No!
To kill you
would be to kill part of myself!
We were bound as one!
We were the same.
As there was hope before,
there can be hope again.
How?
We can't go back.
Everything good we ever had is destroyed.
There's nothing left, Uhtred.
You're talking through your arse.
Now you sound like the girl
who I chased through these woods
and humped amongst these trees.
The girl that I loved.
She's there still.
Is she?
I can't find her.
I will help you.
Trust me.
Brida.
What have you done?
Only what you could not!
I'm sorry.
I...
I'm cold.
No.
Ragnar.
Brida.
No!
Brida!
Brida...
http://hiqve.com/