I am Uhtred, son of Uhtred.
Urgent news has reached Eoferwic.
- Aelfwynn was captured on the road.
- By who?
We believe them to be hired men.
We suspect an association
with Lord Aethelhelm.
And my fate
has altered accordingly.
Lord Aethelhelm is fomenting rebellion.
He has made an alliance with Constantin
and has offered him the hand
of Lady Aelfwynn.
Where will we find him?
In a fortress north of here,
name of Bebbanburg.
My birthright, stolen from me
by my cousin Wihtgar.
Your name will be forgotten!
Now I have a chance
to take it back.
I lead the men of Wessex, and we push
the Scots back over the border.
Meanwhile, Aethelhelm will be forced
to surrender and Aelfwynn returned.
But King Edward has
a different plan.
In exchange for marrying Aelfwynn
and isolating Lord Aethelhelm,
we will divide Northumbria in two.
The lands around Bebbanburg
fall to the Scots,
and Aethelhelm is disposed of.
Yet he could find no support.
I gave your sister my word
that I would keep Aelfwynn safe.
- I stand with Uhtred.
- We stand with Uhtred.
Aethelstan, my boy, what do you say?
I will follow Lord Uhtred.
Not sure things are going your way,
Lord King.
I will brook no more defiance.
No one will leave on penalty of execution!
Destiny is all!
Come on! Quicken the pace!
Sunrise comes swiftly.
Hey, perhaps don't kill me
just before departure.
Move!
- Any word if the king will relent?
- He has shunned all his advisers.
He wouldn't turn swords
on Saxons, surely.
Tell that to the Mercian ealdormen.
We leave at sunrise.
Do his men still bar the gate?
Yes, and the Mercians
seem set on departure.
I fear neither will back down.
Another person who cannot sleep?
I am not in the king's favor tonight.
I told him he should not turn his back
on Northumbria, and he was not pleased.
No man enjoys hearing the truth
from the woman he loves.
Hmm.
All the same, when it must be delivered,
God is with us.
My orders are still defied.
Prepare the men of Wessex.
All must gather at the gate.
Yes, Lord King.
Lady.
Edward, do not turn on other Saxons.
Eadgifu, you should be returning
to Winchester.
Now is not the time to become allies.
We are not allies,
merely the women who love you.
I swear, I will say the truth as I see it
and then leave.
Your plan, to forsake Aelfwynn
and make a bargain with the Scots
is not without merit.
It could bring peace, yes,
but at the cost of dividing the Saxons.
Do not risk sundering Mercia from Wessex.
You should be advising Lord Aldhelm.
But I shall not,
for I agree with Lord Aldhelm.
Aethelflaed would follow Uhtred.
I am the king. I do not follow.
You are a king
who is choosing not to lead.
A choice so strange, I ask myself why.
And I only have one conclusion.
Fear.
- I do not fear Aethelhelm, Constantin or...
- No, but you fear Alfred and his legacy.
So I will tell you one thing.
You are strong enough to be the man
to fulfill your father's dream.
You do not have to leave it
to your descendants.
You are worthy to live in the chronicles,
as the one who unified England.
- It is not fear that holds me back.
- I am your mother...
and I know when you are afraid.
So I am here to tell you
that I believe you are deserving
of this moment.
You are as good and true
and faithful a man as your father.
And for that, God will favor you.
This is your destiny.
Seize this moment.
Leave your posts!
Rejoin the army!
Wessex have stood down.
Edward's men
no longer defend these walls.
We ride.
- Open the gates.
- Lord. Yes, Lord.
To Bebbanburg then, Lord Uhtred?
Let the king have his moment.
If that is your command.
I will need someone loyal to hold
the border lands in Northumbria.
We confront the Scottish king on the road!
We break his alliance with Lord Aethelhelm
and make a bargain
for Aethelflaed's daughter.
We retain Northumbria
for the Saxon people!
To Bebbanburg!
Are we expecting to be besieged?
No, we are expecting to decamp
and go south for battle.
We shan't avail ourselves of Northumbrian
hospitality any longer than is necessary.
As soon as Constantin's army arrives
and the marriage is consummated,
we will be on our way with our supplies.
When do they arrive, this army?
Soon.
He does not know.
For all this bluster, he does not know
when these Scotsmen will come.
He just hopes they do.
Does your cousin Uhtred still fight
for the king of the Saxons?
Yes.
Which is why
we will not be leaving these walls
whatever promises we have made,
whatever alliance.
Look who I found
on the road ahead.
Cynlaef. You're late.
Lord, I've had a momentous journey,
so much to tell.
First I found myself lost
- by the broken bridge in...
- No! No, not the time, Cynlaef.
What news do you bring?
Just what was seen
by scouts two nights ago.
Constantin's men preparing a boat
near his port at Dynbaer.
One boat will not transport an army.
It could be an advance guard,
sailing with Constantin himself?
Constantin is a great king.
He would not arrive into a fortress
by the sea gate like a trader.
He could be bringing a gift
for the wedding feast?
No, this endeavor is a show of strength.
He will lead as many men on the road
as he can gather.
I agree. It is unlikely
he will arrive south by sea.
Constantin is strategic. He will know
how changeable the tides are,
the risk of summer storms.
All right, we stay with the plan.
With luck,
his full army will take days to gather.
Onward.
Each man is to report back
three times daily.
When King Constantin's army appears
on the horizon, set fire to that church.
Mother.
This is where you will stay.
Imagine that is a line you do not cross.
Oh, Edward, my life is unimportant.
Your bloodline is safe,
and that is all that matters.
How far is Bebbanburg?
Five miles, but our journey is longer.
At dawn we head west through the woods,
go around the fortress at a distance.
Make our ambush on the roads above it.
I am not one to ask military questions,
but surely word will spread
of a mighty army camping nearby?
There comes a point
at which we cannot hide.
We just have to pray that God is with us.
You will stay here and not foolishly
go out onto the battlefield?
- If the injured need my help I may...
- She will not.
We know our role in this.
Some moments men must face alone,
and this is one.
Alert our lord.
It is the king.
A king would choose a finer ship.
Except for perhaps this one.
My men disembark at the sea gate.
A king arrives at a fortress
through the front.
Here they come.
Stand alert
for the king of the Scots!
Lord King. You are a little in advance
of what we had planned.
I like to catch people off guard.
I was hoping your arrival
would be a little more clandestine.
I did not become a king
to hide in a forest.
Yet we have on our side
the most precious asset
one can gain in war,
the element of surprise.
Squander that
and we risk Edward learning of...
There are spies everywhere.
He will hear soon enough.
Indeed, but his weakness
is his impulsiveness.
When he learns of our alliance he will...
I will not sit and wait for an attack.
It is cowardly.
I thought we had agreed
an attack would be launched
once you had cemented ties with Mercia.
And I am a man of my word.
Is that the boy who'd be
king of the Saxons?
Indeed. Aelfweard,
come and bow to King Constantin...
A word of advice from a king
to a future king.
Trust no one who advises you.
Understood.
Well, let's eat.
Ask Lady Aelfwynn to join us.
No!
I should prefer to meet her alone,
after we've dined.
Never meet a bride on an empty stomach.
Eh?
Hey, what do you say, Lord?
Lose the deadwood, jump on some horses,
ride up to the gate, just the three of us,
teach your cousin a lesson?
Riding up to the gate
is something I've tried before.
Perhaps better your way than to drag
all of these people to their doom.
Ah, come on!
They want to join you.
This is what they've been waiting for.
They'll tell stories
of this their whole lives.
"Bebbanburg, my part in its conquest."
Hey.
Lord, the news is heavy.
Our plan to ambush is mistimed.
Constantin is already within the fortress.
The spies say he came by sea.
- I am at fault. I counseled this.
- You're not.
Much of this is judgment
and we misjudged it.
How many men were in this boat?
We think only a household guard.
As Uhtred predicted.
Do not assume it is a sign.
We simply make another plan.
It is a sign we should attack.
Before his army arrives...
- No.
- Our targets are all in one place.
Storm the fortress now
and we trap Aethelhelm and Constantin.
Aelfwynn is within. She will be forced to
this marriage and they will threaten her.
Yes, they'll try to use her
in a bargain, but...
But we trust Aethelhelm
to act with reason when he's in a corner?
If we'd got to Constantin,
then it would be a negotiation,
but now we give him nothing to lose.
We have hundreds of men.
Bebbanburg is well defended, yes,
but we will surely outman them.
His own daughter died amidst the fury
of his scheming.
We cannot risk Aethelflaed's child
in the chaos that will engulf Bebbanburg.
There is another way.
I will leave with some of my men.
Wait until you have word from us.
We shall get Aelfwynn out of the fortress,
then you can attack.
- How?
- The sea gate, Lord?
No. There is a route to Bebbanburg which...
It cannot take an army,
not even half a dozen men.
I had dismissed it as too perilous, but...
with a tiny number, maybe it is possible.
What happens when this tiny number
meets the Household Guard of Bebbanburg?
Pyrlig, are you strong enough to join us?
Are you strong enough to stop me?
Lord, let me be a part of this.
Whatever the danger,
I'm man enough to face it.
Four is a number
that's always served us well in the past.
Stand the men down.
Do not attack until I signal.
Enough evasion. What is the plan?
If it works, we will return with Aelfwynn.
If it does not?
Then this will be the last time
we speak together.
We go north, past Bebbanburg,
on to the next cove.
We will seek the help of someone I know.
What if help is not forthcoming?
Then Finan will have to think
of something.
What?
We have work to do.
No flirting with the nuns.
We'll leave that to you, Uhtred.
http://hiqve.com/
If you had written,
we would have brewed some ale.
- You are here!
- You are lucky.
I've been on the island most of the month.
You should have sent word.
I did not know I was coming.
- But the Gods had other plans.
- Have you come for Aalys?
She's in much better spirits,
though she does still dream
of the queen's death.
I come for Bebbanburg.
Is it the time? Have you the men?
Edward has an army south of here.
Huh. Normally we hear of such things.
First, I must get into the fortress
with a small number of men
to secure the Lady Aelfwynn.
Ah. Have you a plan?
One is forming, yes, but I will need help.
Not yours.
- I will need the help of...
- No!
No, he's too young.
Not his help. No, not his at all.
Is by any piece of luck
the trader Haesten still in these lands?
Uhtred, truly the gods are with you.
Come.
He refuses to leave
because he's making such good coin here.
We've become quite the marketplace.
I will find you.
Steal from me and you'll regret it!
- Uhtred!
- I've come to offer silver not to take it.
I'm not in need
and I have already done your bidding.
Yes, I know, and now I want more.
I am to enter Bebbanburg
and you are to help me
by distracting the Household Guard.
No. No, absolutely not.
Not today, not any day.
It is an unwise choice.
I will retake my lands
and then we will return
to punish you for this refusal.
Threaten me and I shall go to Bebbanburg
tonight and warn them of your attack.
No, you will not.
I'm busy making silver.
Tell me.
Will Valhalla welcome a man
who sells relics to fools?
My ancestors came to these lands
to become rich, Uhtred.
I'm merely living my birthright.
You will not even need
to wield your sword.
All I ask is that you draw the guard
to the shore.
And for that, I will pay you... handsomely.
You do not have the coin.
And yet you know that I will
when I retake Bebbanburg.
And in the contest between Wihtgar and me,
you know who will win.
I'm not known for my loyalty, Uhtred.
It is not wise to put this in my hands.
It is not simple
to lure a guard away from their defenses.
- It will cost you.
- Yes, I know.
Finan is outside.
He will explain the plan.
Pyrlig can borrow our smallest boat.
If they spot him on the water they should
just assume he's part of the pilgrimage.
Make sure you return it.
I will do all I can.
Good luck.
I wonder... Perhaps I should join you.
No, please do not.
You have things to protect here.
I'm never certain Haesten can be trusted.
Am I making the right choice?
It cannot be wrong
to protect the Lady Aelfwynn
or to seek a home for your children.
Whether this is the time
that has been chosen for you,
that I cannot say. I hope it is.
But your motive is pure
and so my God will be with you.
Get it done as dawn rises.
And tomorrow will be the first day
of a new world.
- Does everyone understand the plan?
- Yes!
- Yes.
- Hey, do it for him.
He draws the guards down
to the beaches before the tide turns,
giving you a very small
and frankly slightly reckless opportunity
to get in by the guards' room
before they return.
You're forgetting the bit
where you sit on your ass.
Yeah, I... I sit on my ass in the boat.
- Hmm.
- Get them out when the signal comes.
Excellent, we're all agreed.
Night approaches
and there is still no word from Uhtred.
Lord King, be patient.
He has never let you down.
Never before
was he fighting for his own lands.
As much as he speaks of Saxon
unity, we know what brings him here.
- I do not think that is fair.
- Perhaps not.
But who has the best interests
of the Saxon people at heart,
- Uhtred or me? I will not...
- Lord...
Spies north of here say the Scots have
left a camp and march in this direction.
- How long until they reach Bebbanburg?
- Unclear.
It will depend on whether they stop
to meet reinforcements
- or if that is the full force.
- And what of Uhtred?
No word, no sighting.
We cannot track him.
What is being discussed
that we should know?
- What is being kept from me?
- I fear he is going to attack.
Without Lord Uhtred?
He does not seem to care
if my father lives or dies.
Talking to him of Aelfwynn has no effect
and he has no thought for Lord Aelfweard.
Edward is lost.
To be so enraged
by Aethelhelm's treachery,
he would risk his own son in a siege?
Something has gripped him.
It is as if he now believes
he has divine blessing.
My lady.
Lady.
I may have been too emphatic
in my encouragement of the king.
Come, ride with me south.
No! I will not flee the battle.
I will stay where I may be of use
to injured men.
I am not suggesting we flee,
but if you want to avert a slaughter,
then follow.
Do you plan to jump
and swim away?
Perhaps.
Well, do not be fooled by the calm.
The tides here change quickly.
You'd be dashed on the rock.
I do not care. My life is over.
Are you the king of the Scots?
Are you the bride?
So I'm told.
Why are you not married?
You're older than my father.
Which father would that be?
My apologies, it's an unkind joke.
- You already hate me?
- Yes.
Why?
Because I do not wish to marry you!
It is a simple truth.
This is being forced upon me.
I do not wish to marry you either.
- Then free me from this bargain.
- No.
Because I have given my word.
I am being traded.
That's just the way of things.
You will be rich and well-cared for.
- It is not a terrible curse...
- You have no idea! None!
Who is it that you're fond of?
I'm sorry?
Who has your heart
that fosters so much resentment?
Lord King, I'm pure.
I'm not asking that.
I will not share the content of my heart.
Well, um...
as we... we will be married,
I feel I should offer you my trust.
I am in love.
The woman is married herself.
Yet she is mine.
And I have no wish to betray her
by humping a girl of noble blood.
So...
you will be my wife.
You will live in comfort
in whichever fortress best pleases you.
I shall enjoy the riches of your lands
in Mercia.
I may visit,
but not your chamber.
In short,
the marriage will be barren,
and I will never love you.
Lord King,
that is the first time someone
has been honest with me for quite a while.
Thin fellas were they,
your forebears?
How long will we have to get in and out?
Haesten makes landfall
and all goes to plan,
long enough.
My lord.
The seas have betrayed another ship.
This shore is the land
of Wihtgar of Bebbanburg.
You know this.
We do not seek to trespass,
only to wait for our cargo and salvage it.
Who travels with you, Nun?
A trader bringing relics to Lindisfarne.
Name yourself.
Haesten. Allow us to wait for the tide
and you can have some spoils.
Wait here.
The path has gone.
Is there another way?
Can we go back on ourselves?
There's no time. The tide is turning.
Men will be leaving their posts.
You always wanted to die at Bebbanburg.
Less talk. We climb.
Offer no help. Now is not the time
to be distracted by acts of local charity.
Lord King,
we have extended much hospitality
to you and Lord Aethelhelm.
Allow me to claim the spoils
as recompense.
What's the cargo?
Salt and relics.
When the tide comes in, more may follow.
On my land, I take what washes in.
That is indeed the custom.
You may do as you see fit.
But...
I'd be wary of a ploy.
Danes send men to observe
in the weeks before they attack.
Once we have departed south,
you may be at the mercy of sea raiders.
Then you'll seek to welcome us.
You men, to the shore.
You men, to the courtyard.
You may take your fill as the tide turns.
- Is that the cousin?
- Yes. There's not such a resemblance.
I know a greedy man when I see one.
You should have much in common.
You should be able to keep him talking.
Thank you for allowing us
to gather our treasure.
We will see what else washes up
and leave your land.
Not at all, consider yourself my guests.
Come into the fortress where we have fire.
That is a kindness,
but we have much to do.
I have pilgrims
I need to ferry to the island.
Too many dangers present themselves
to travelers here.
Come into the fortress.
A wedding feast is imminent
and that is a delight we wish to share.
My men will gather your cargo,
though, of course we will take a tribute.
Take your fill
of the riches, men!
Haesten is feeling generous.
Oh, Jesus!
Can you believe that?
Give me your hand! Give me your hand!
Give me your other hand!
Pull! Pull up!
Thank you.
Quickly grab what you can
and return to your posts.
And keep an eye out for more Danish ships!
I'd like somewhere quiet to dress.
Are there ladies' quarters
in the fortress?
You may find your way down to the kitchen.
There are some women there.
This one.
This repair looks weakest.
Try it.
Too fast and too loud.
I cannot hear anyone.
I think Haesten has got them to the shore.
Haesten!
Now that is a face I would not forget.
Are you the poor soul
that was shipwrecked?
- Yes.
- Ah.
I do not recall you, Lord.
No.
No, it seems you do not.
The last time we met,
you imprisoned me in Alfred's tomb.
Siege at Winchester,
it is imprinted on my memory.
And yet you lived and thrived afterwards.
We were both...
younger men.
My grandson barely slept
for years afterwards.
Well, I have removed the icicles
from my balls and will be on my way.
Stay a while, Haesten.
We have such memories to share.
Block the hole.
That's enough.
Lord.
Hey, hey.
Here. You are most likely
to be recognized.
What if one of you two gets spotted?
I've a plan for that.
Come on. Let's find Aelfwynn!
- Lord King, wait for Uhtred's signal.
- We have waited and heard nothing.
The time offered to prevail
is slipping away.
But what of Uhtred or Aelfwynn?
They will be killed!
- This is madness.
- Yes.
But we must follow.
Is that the king of the Scots?
Aye.
Lord! Lord!
Lord!
You men!
Stay in the courtyard.
Why does Constantin place his men here?
We do not discuss
what measures we take
to ensure my lord is protected.
Aye!
King Constantin?
Your man strays where he is not wanted.
He's no man of mine.
I think you've been fooled, Lord Wihtgar.
How did you get past my men?
Are you shipwrecked Danes also?
Torture them for answers.
Show them what any sea raider would face.
You do God's work, my friends.
You shall make twice this
on my next cargo.
- Lady Aelfwynn?
- Yes?
- Come.
- No!
Come! I'm trying to rescue you!
I have heard that many times before,
and it's never been true.
Lady Aelfwynn, I am Lord Haesten.
- I was a friend of your true father!
- Lord Haesten?
Tried to kill my mother! Help!
Help me! Help me! Lord King!
This man is trying to seize me.
The girl is mistaken.
If I offended the young lady, I apologize.
Our ways with women
are not the same as yours.
I'm a man of honor.
Perhaps I am misunderstood.
You're a liar.
Your plot is discovered
and your other men captured.
Tell me the truth
of why you came to Bebbanburg
and I shall take only their lives.
I will tell you the truth,
for I serve no one but myself.
I have no allies here,
and I'm part of no plan.
Have rid of this.
And fetch the priest!
Get this marriage over!
Perhaps we have gone the wrong way.
The farmer said this was east,
but now I think it is west.
I was told many have joined her,
here amongst the trees.
We know you are here!
We have seen your scouts!
Lady Aelswith.
Do your worst!
You'll get nothing out of us.
It is very foolish of you to come here.
I'm no friend to Christians.
Perhaps, yes.
But...
we need your help.
Halt!
Let me strike the first blow.
My lord!
Soldiers approach from the south.
- How many?
- Many.
I shall return. Wait.
You, secure the gate! Secure it!
Oh no, no, not yet.
Come no closer!
Speak!
I bring a message from Edward,
king of the Saxons
and king in these lands!
Give us Lord Aethelhelm and Lady Aelfwynn
and we will not attack.
Refuse and we will besiege
and kill you all!
None will survive!
http://hiqve.com/