I am Uhtred, son of Uhtred.
Rognvaldr has betrayed his brother
and helped Brida to invade Eoferwic.
Do not be afraid, brother,
she's here to save us.
Whilst Brida has set Sigtryggr
a task he dare not refuse.
We will find your wife, you know we will.
I will spare her life
if you bring me Uhtred.
Eadith has delivered
the gra vest news.
Lady, I fear it is too late
to save you from this canker.
I believe you will not see the spring.
In Winchester,
King Edward has found a new Io ve.
Lady Eadgifu, eat with us.
Lord King, I would be honored.
But A ethelhelm continues
to plot against him.
Inform the Saxon boroughs
not to give troops to assist him.
This is the word of the king, is it?
If asked, he will deny it.
Stiorra cannot stand by
and let her people be murdered.
Brida! You will pay for this!
Then show yourself!
We must now enter the city
by stealth and save my daughter.
Destiny is all!
Brida!
Stiorra!
Stiorra, do not do this!
Do not cross her!
See how the gods favor us, my Beloveds?
See who they bring us?
The gods will not forget
what you've done in their name.
Hold your tongue,
or my men will cut it out for you.
No. You will fight me.
You have taken my city
and murdered my people.
You will face me.
Or will you hide behind your slaves?
You have Uhtred's eyes. Perhaps I shall
keep them when I'm finished with you.
What's this?
She was helping
some others escape. She went for me.
There is no cause
for more bloodshed, Brida.
Hella is a good servant,
she can be useful to you.
Mmm.
What do you say, girl, hmm?
Will you make yourself useful?
Good.
Let her death be a warning to all of you
who would stand
beside the Dane slayer's daughter.
Keep moving!
Make the square.
Fight me, Brida.
You're no warrior.
I am the Queen of Eoferwic.
I am my father's daughter.
Perhaps you're afraid
the gods will favor me?
You know nothing of the gods.
Make the square.
Do not do this, Stiorra! Do not fight!
We're in the city.
Make a square!
Well, now I know what a turd feels like.
Stiorra.
Stiorra, don't do this!
You know what to do,
move quickly.
Don't fight, Stiorra!
We go on your signal.
Shh.
I'll get you out, be ready.
Come on, you bastards, you!
Ha-ha!
Brida!
Ah! You should not have come
for my children, Brida.
It's not like the little priest
was using his cock.
Sigtryggr!
Stiorra!
Hold back some men
to help the townsfolk.
Be ready!
Vibeke, hide until I come for you.
To the woods! Hide yourselves!
Take cover!
Vibeke!
Vibeke! Vibeke, hold on!
Mother! Mother!
Vibeke, the gods will protect you!
- Child, get back from the edge.
- Mother!
Vibeke!
Come to me.
Don't go to him.
Do not be afraid.
Give me your hand.
Jump to me!
- Vibeke. Jump to me. The gods are with us.
- Brida, no!
- Give me your hand.
- Trust me, we can do this.
You can do this, trust me.
I will catch you!
- No!
- Vibeke!
Vibeke!
Retreat! Retreat!
Take him.
I'm Sigtryggr's brother.
I'm Sigtryggr's brother!
Sigtryggr, she made me.
She made me!
I knew you would come.
You fought well, Stiorra.
Brida escaped.
Why did you let her live?
Her child lay dead.
There'd have been no honor
in taking advantage of her grief.
She'll find more to follow her.
Now is the time to end this.
We lost so many of our people.
- If you don't go after her, I will.
- I will. I will.
Finan. Sihtric.
Fetch our men from Rumcofa.
The victory feasting will have to wait.
What... What is it, Lord?
We must ride after Brida.
Now.
Uh, Lord, I must speak with you...
Fetch Father Pyrlig.
He will be with the townspeople.
Then stay here and make sure
the rest of the city is secured.
Brother, I have wronged you.
I was deceived by the witch.
You will be silent.
Wait! Please!
I fought with you!
No, you saw the tide turn
and sought only to save yourself.
I saved your life.
We're brothers.
We're blood.
To the woods!
Hide there until it's safe to come back.
These men will take you to the others.
Do not be afraid.
You might as well have a bell
around your neck, boy.
I'm sorry.
Look, bodies.
She came this way.
Maybe we should fetch the others.
I'm sorry.
Your first battle, it is common.
I emptied my guts into my brother
Ragnar's helmet after my first.
You did well.
Fetch the others,
tell them Brida is traveling north.
- I'll go ahead.
- Uhtred, no.
Brida escaped.
It was not your doing, you know that.
You must stop blaming yourself.
She did not escape.
I let her go.
Can this be true?
The priest was quite certain
Lady Aethelflaed will not see the spring.
The king has received no word
from his sister.
It seems she will not seek
the support of Wessex
before she names her successor.
She only needs
the Mercian Witan's approval.
They will all seek the throne
for their own sons.
Whoever she names
will have a bloody battle on his hands.
Mmm.
Unless she intends the throne
for the Lady Aelfwynn.
Her daughter?
What, you really think the Witan would
put aside their own ambitions so easily?
They won't like it,
but there is an argument to be made
for peaceful continuity.
It avoids the infighting,
which we saw at Aethelred's passing.
But perhaps that is not the only solution.
You have someone in mind?
Who better than my grandson Aelfweard?
He is nephew to the lady.
He is a far more suitable choice
to continue her line
and he is young enough that the ealdormen
will believe they can influence him.
They will need persuading.
Indeed.
We must proceed with caution.
Find out how loyal
the Witan are to Aethelflaed.
I can send word to our friends
in Aegelesburg.
Yes. Do it quickly.
This will not stay secret long.
Mmm. Not if that arseling priest
has anything to do with it.
Lord!
If Brida passed this way,
it was hours ago.
We could always return at daybreak, Lord.
With more men from Eoferwic,
we could spread the search wider.
It will be too late. We must keep looking.
The trail is cold, Uhtred.
We return to Eoferwic.
You will find her.
Yes, I will.
Lord King.
I've had word from Mercia
that my men never reached Sigtryggr.
Aethelflaed sent no help to Eoferwic.
I see.
I do not understand it.
Why would my sister endanger
the peace so recklessly?
Perhaps the Lady Aethelflaed has done
what Wessex should have done long ago
and cut ties with the enemy within.
No, this is not like her.
And why has there been no word
from Pyrlig?
I will send a messenger to Aegelesburg.
We are missing something.
Come on. You need to drink
to your first victory.
This is the part where we usually enjoy
the gratitude of the local women.
If Brida left any.
I was blind.
I opened the gates
and I let the wolves among my people.
You led us to victory.
Eoferwic is restored, Stiorra's safe.
They have all betrayed me.
Not just the one I called brother.
I've been weak. I kept silent
as the Christians poisoned my people.
I share your anger.
- But the truce is held...
- The truce? There was no truce.
It was all lies and trickery.
The Christians' words are as false
as the God they pretend to love.
And I was a fool to trust them.
I think you're wrong.
Why? Why do you defend them?
If Brida had threatened Christian Mercia,
do you think Edward would have looked
the other way?
But when Danes are under attack,
he turns against us.
Uhtred, we are heathens to be sacrificed,
nothing more.
Pyrlig said Edward did send men to Mercia
intended for your aid.
You have won how many battles for them?
This is how they repay you?
They dishonor you.
They abandon your daughter.
They do not have your oath.
They forfeit your allegiance.
Swear your loyalty to me.
Stand beside your kin.
Hmm?
My place is in Rumcofa.
Mmm.
Father, Sigtryggr is...
His brother's betrayal,
there's a shadow on him now.
His pride is wounded.
He needs time to heal.
It's not just his pride.
I know you see it too.
He needs your guidance.
He'll listen to you.
Will you stay?
Drink this.
It'll help you sleep, Lady.
You have a slight fever.
I shouldn't sleep
until Father Benedict has visited.
My mother was never going to let me
travel home without a priest.
Benedict is here, my dearest.
The lady should rest tonight.
She is weakened from the journey.
She will be healed by God's grace,
not your potions.
Will you help me
with my robe, Eadith?
The sacrament of healing will restore you.
"And the apostle said
unto them, 'Is any sick among you?
Let him summon the priests of the church.
And let them pray over him,
anointing him with oil,
in the name of the Lord. ""
God is good.
Per istam Sanctam
unctionem et suam...
Piissiimam misericordiam...
indulgeat tibi...
Dominus quidquid per visum...
deliquisti.
Our friends in Mercia have sent word.
They say the Lady Aethelflaed
has allies among the ealdormen,
but there are more who harbor bitterness
at her successes.
Then they will name Aelfweard as Lord
when the time comes?
I believe most
will be led by their greed.
Mmm.
You must leave immediately.
Make sure the Witan feels...
...adequately respected.
What if the lady returns
before I reach the ealdormen?
That cannot happen. You must reach
Aegelesburg before she does.
I will follow with Aelfweard
once I have broken the news to the king.
The palace is stirring.
I must not be seen here.
It is early yet.
Your wife has engaged me
in duties of the court.
I believe I am to divert my energies
towards the art of embroidery.
Ah.
I hear she is greatly enthused
by a farm girl
who was blessed with a visitation from St...
Cuthbert, I think.
The queen wishes the ladies of Winchester
to construct a grand tapestry
in the saint's honor.
Of course she does.
In truth, I think she wishes
to keep an eye on me.
- I will deal with her.
- No, there's no need.
I do not wish to cause her pain.
You will return tonight?
Is that my king's command?
It is my hope.
A thousand pardons for the hour...
Lord Aethelhelm.
Well?
There is no easy way
to deliver news of this kind.
I have received sad tidings from Mercia.
Your sister is gravely ill, Lord King.
She is not long for this world.
Impossible.
- There is no doubt.
- No.
Why would your spies learn this
before the king?
We have seen in the past
how the matter of the Mercian succession
can give rise to disorder.
I imagine the lady wished
to keep the matter of her condition secret
for as long as possible.
It cannot be.
I am deeply sorry.
Of course this explains why
the lady did not raise the Mercian army
to aid Eoferwic.
In any case, there are reports
that Sigtryggr has recaptured his city.
A small mercy.
Thank you, Lord Aethelhelm.
You will travel to Mercia?
Forgive me.
I will intrude on your grief no longer.
- Lord.
- Finan, did you find Pyrlig?
Uh, I searched until nightfall.
There was no sign.
He must have traveled back to the king.
That is not like him.
Uhtred, forgive me. We... We must speak.
We go after Brida.
We can talk on the journey.
It's the Lady Aethelflaed.
Lord Aldhelm!
She lives but her strength fades.
She doesn't want her condition to be known
until matters are resolved.
She will need your help
to enter the palace.
She...
She will not see the spring.
But she was in good health in Rumcofa.
You must be mistaken in this, Finan.
I-I wish I was mistaken.
She does not have long.
And you concealed this from me?
Eadith begged me to wait until
the battle was won before I told you.
Your mind was on your daughter.
It would've been wrong
for me to add to your troubles.
I'm sorry, Uhtred.
It cannot be.
You have loved each other for many years.
We've all seen it,
even if the lady cannot speak of it.
So I know the pain you've carried
since she took her vow.
She would want you to be with her, Uhtred.
You must go to her.
I thought one day we might...
I thought there would be more...
There is so much I should have said.
There's still time.
We ride to Aegelesburg.
Stiorra!
Father?
Lady Aethelflaed is dying.
I'm so sorry, Father.
I must go to her.
If Mercia finds itself without a leader
once more, you must be careful.
You could come with us.
It could help
heal the rift between your lands.
No. My place is here with Sigtryggr.
Yes, it is.
http://hiqve.com/
We must keep moving.
What about the last one?
Should I kill him here?
Um...
He comes with us.
The gods delivered him to me.
They will show me why.
Mother?
I am here.
Aelfwynn.
Where... Where is she?
The child should not see you this way,
dear one.
Let us wait until you are a little better.
Aelfwynn must be named as my successor.
If she is on the throne,
she will be protected.
I will fetch Lady Aelfwynn.
He's here.
He's here. Come look! Come!
Hey!
Lady Aelfwynn.
Your mother.
Is this about
how I brought shame on her in Rumcofa?
What more can there be to say
on the matter?
Lady Aethelflaed only wishes
to speak with you.
My mother wishes only to chide me
for doing what she cannot.
Your mother has given
everything she has for Mercia!
To protect her people,
to protect you, her only child.
You're not just her hope for
the future of this kingdom.
You're her heart, Aelfwynn.
She thinks only of you.
Come.
She is eager to see you.
Do you understand?
Knowing my daughter will be Lady of Mercia
in my stead, it is all I wish.
It will mean you are safe, Aelfwynn.
You must agree to this.
- I'm not ready.
- Listen to me.
Word of my condition will spread.
There are those who would seek to take
the throne for their own advancement.
If they are successful,
the first thing they will do is ensure
my daughter is disposed of.
You frighten the child.
She needs to know the truth.
There is no time...
It fades.
Mother.
Do you suffer greatly?
Do not be afraid.
I know there is much you must sacrifice.
It is a choice I also faced.
I do not pretend it was easy.
But you will not be alone.
I will be strong.
I'll do as you wish.
I'll serve as queen when you're gone.
The Witan will stand behind you.
I am sure of it.
Come now, Aelfwynn.
Let us visit the church together.
Mother?
You must rest.
It pains her
to see you this way.
It is a dreadful thing to...
to face the loss of a child.
I hope you know I am grateful.
Oh, uh...
...Lady, there's no... no need.
Will you do me one more service,
Lord Aldhelm?
Anything.
My daughter is young and willful.
I know she is not ready.
You must be her guide.
Her adviser.
She needs you.
Mercia needs you.
Of course. It will be my honor.
No one has served Mercia more faithfully.
We must act quickly.
I will
seek out the ealdormen.
Thank you, Aldhelm.
If this sad news is true,
how is it Wessex has learned of it
before the ealdormen of Mercia?
Lord Aethelhelm has many friends
across the kingdoms.
All of you know the young Lady Aelfwynn
is not fit to rule.
Does your master propose
an alternative solution?
He does indeed, Lord Burgred.
One he trusts you will all find...
...advantageous.
We are greatly blessed to welcome
Aalys and her pilgrims to Winchester.
Indeed.
This is the young woman from Lewes?
You see, the tapestry tells
of the deeds of St. Cuthbert,
the saint she was visited by.
Hmm, remarkable.
It is important the people see
your recognition of this miracle, Edward.
Are you pleased with our work?
God's glory shines through your laborers,
my Lady.
We will be glad to carry your offering
to the Holy Isle.
- You will take this to Lindisfarne?
- With your approval, Lord King.
You see, when I heard Aalys was making
the pilgrimage to the Holy Isle,
I knew you'd like to make
a king's blessing to their offering.
It means so much to your people.
Of course.
God be with you on your journey.
Do you understand
that your show of piety may be seen
as Wessex laying claim to the Holy Isle?
King Constantin wants Lindisfarne
for Scotland.
He could see this
as a deliberate act of provocation.
I did not know.
You did not ask.
Lady.
God knows your heart.
He feels your pain as his own.
I will pray for you.
That you will know God's will
for your life and his peace in your heart.
This is not the moment
for you to provoke the king's displeasure.
He disrespects me.
And you will bear it
for the sake of your son.
He is the only reason
we have a place here.
I am aware of that,
but I'm tired of waiting...
Aelfweard will be Lord of Mercia
within the week.
There will be a Witan
when the Lady Aethelflaed dies.
And my grandson will be named
her successor.
He has bribed the Mercian ealdormen.
It is the only explanation.
How long has he known
of my sister's plight?
What will you do?
Lord Aethelhelm.
I will ride to Aegelesburg.
God willing, my sister will be spared
long enough to receive us.
A wise decision, Lord.
I think it would be right if your son
were to travel with the delegation.
Aelfweard is very fond of his aunt.
Perhaps I could accompany him?
He may be some comfort
to his cousin Aelfwynn.
The poor girl.
You'll see her, Lord.
We'll not be too late!
Sigtryggr! Brother!
Sigtryggr!
Brother!
Sigtryggr! Brother!
I know it is not an easy thing,
to condemn your brother to die.
We are family!
You are tenderhearted.
That's why I love you.
I know I must act.
He must answer for his crimes.
But all my life,
I have protected him.
I do not know what to do.
He does not deserve your mercy.
Perhaps we could let the gods decide.
Brother.
Brother!
We are decided.
You may choose a quick death here,
or you may trust your fate
to a public trial,
but you must choose now.
A trial?
It's what you pretended to want
when you came here, wasn't it?
A trial for your people under Danelaw?
I know you.
I know you are just.
You're merciful.
You will not condemn me.
Choose!
You brought them here!
The prisoner will take the bar
in both hands!
He will take nine steps,
for the nine nights Odin hung
on the great tree.
If he succeeds,
the gods have favored him
and he will be pardoned.
But if he fails, the gods have cursed him.
And my sword is ready!
Brother, I...
We begin!
http://hiqve.com/