I am uhtred, son of uhtred.
I was born a Saxon lord,
but raised as 3 Dane,
until the Eve of my sister's wedding
when my family were murdered.
I am a warrior,
but when the Dane's attacked
Alfred's stronghold of Winchester,
all a man could do was run.
Some faster than others. Including
my enemy, young odda.
And so guthrum took Winchester.
Aethelwold pledged his allegiance
to the Danes.
Though guthrum
still feared Alfred's god.
I could only hope my now-distant
wife and child would be safe.
We had no choice but to hide,
and pray for a miracle.
Iseult, my virgin queen,
saved the king's son,
but at a cost only she could see.
She gave Alfred strength.
With the king alive and well,
there is hope for wessex.
Destiny is all.
We have fired
a good number of ships.
- A fleet.
In the meantime, we left hundreds
of Danes stranded in wessex.
Wulfhere, I do not believe
their intention was to ever leave.
And in a few months there'll be
more ships, more men.
- Now is the time to fight.
- To fight with what?
We're without an army,
the Danes will number thousands.
The men are out there and they're
waiting. What they need is the call.
Indeed, but...
What if I suggest we escort you
to frankia?
That will not happen. I will not hide.
Not here nor in frankia.
But my lord...
I've prayed daily for guidance.
The only way I see to save wessex
is with what we have begun:
One defining battle.
We shall be leaving the marshes.
Courage and faith.
- Amen.
Amen.
It will not be recorded that king Alfred
was a weak and frail man
in mind, body and soul,
unfit to be called king.
- Nothing of what you say is true.
- But it would become true.
Never.
Now, you, my love, will remain here.
- If I fail, you must go to frankia.
- Not without you.
You must save and protect
our children.
For me...
There can be no other country
but england.
No other wife but aelswith.
Father beocca.
I'm not saying I know everything,
but the king must continue to trust me.
- The arrival of asser may change him.
- Brother asser has given him strength.
The brother is not a warrior.
Now is a time for warriors.
Never thought I'd say it,
we need odda the younger.
He commands the largest fyrd.
It's the beginning of our army.
That is where we're headed.
Uhtred, I will do everything I can
to help.
I will be at your side.
I'll be a flea in Alfred's ear.
- Thank you.
- Your father would be a proud man.
As am I.
I shall ready my men
and by tomorrow have horses waiting.
You believe the Danes
can be defeated?
I'll see you across the water,
ealdorman wulfhere.
You will.
Aethelcod. Aethelcod, my friend.
A man who would be king
ofvvessex.
Thank you, thank you
for coming to see me.
- It is aethelwold...
- Yes. Please, sit down. Sit down.
I want you to tell me
everything you know
about Alfred.
I've told you, lord.
He thinks with his dick. Heh.
He can barely keep his breeches on.
Heh, heh.
- Hear the question, boy.
- Not everybody enjoys a fool.
Alfred...
Though he may be afflicted by pain,
he's as strong a man as you will find.
He is also as clever a man
as you will find.
I was ready to have him as my advisor,
until he stole my crown.
His strength, lord, I believe,
comes from his faith.
From god. Heh, heh, heh.
Do you believe...
I believe in myself.
Why did Alfred steal the crown?
For silver or to be
a stronger king to the people?
No. Umj... um...
- Yes, in part.
- Which is it?
Unfairly, I was not seen as a man
to follow, by some.
I was not a man to fight Danes,
it was said.
And which is true because
I know the Danes will win. Heh, heh. Yes.
Whereas... whereas Alfred...
Alfred believes that he can win.
- Even now?
- Yes.
He's wrong, of course, but his faith...
That god will not desert him,
will make him believe that he will win.
Then you have to kill him.
I must kill him?
Than king aethelcod
can walk into Alfred's camp
and be welcomed as a friend?
Shh—shh.
Wulfhere and his men.
God, save me. Stay away! I have skills!
Put that piece of tin away, boy.
Oh, thank Christ. You're English.
I thought you were one of them.
What with the hair.
Where is the ealdorman wulfhere?
Gone, lord.
- I am halig. I take care of the horses.
- Gone where?
Now I'm thinking on it, he did not say.
I thought you would know.
- Wulfhere, where is he?
- He's gone, lord.
My lord, it's you.
- Where?
- He didn't say.
- He has left you horses, lord.
- We keep moving.
Without wulfhere?
Our plan doesn't change.
We make our way to odda's estate.
We cannot use the Roman roads.
We can make our way to my farmstead,
from there, across covered ground
to odda's.
- And that is the safest path, leofric?
- It is, lord.
Let's return to the others.
There is pain here for you, my love.
- Do you know them?
- Tenants.
We shall Bury the dead
- and pray for their souls.
- When you are ready...
I would like to say a prayer
for uhtred, son of uhtred.
I will search for mildrith.
She may be dead and unburied.
Uhtred, no, no.
She has buried your son with care
and she has left this place.
It was no longer home
for her anymore.
Believe me.
Your tears on the earth
will show him that you loved him.
Lord, may I ask what you're writing?
The first of many letters.
Each will say the same:
The men of wessex and beyond
shall gather at egbert's stone,
and together we will fight.
When you send out your messengers,
lord,
might I suggest that you hand them
the letters personally?
Perhaps place a hand
on their shoulder.
It will embolden them, I'm sure.
Thank you, beocca, I will do that.
You know I did this to you,
when I saved the king's son.
- You did not.
- I knew an innocent would die.
I'm tired of being like this.
I've seen too much. I know too much.
I want to see no more.
Mildrith?
Lord, you should be resting.
We should all be resting.
I'm tired of resting.
I spend too many days doing nothing.
Sit before you become unsteady.
- Where is my wife?
- She's resting, lord.
My son?
- He is away, lord.
- Still?
Important business demands time.
It is not a betrayal.
No, it is not, lord.
Look what I have done to you, child.
- I am content enough, lord.
- Look what god has done to you.
You deserve so much more
than the clothes of a nun.
I have purpose, lord.
My child is with god
and I am close to god.
There is joy in my days, at times.
Do not fear the Danes.
You will be protected.
My son will ensure that.
You are Earl skorpa?
You are here to surrender
and not waste my time.
- I am here to negotiate.
- Surrender and you will live.
- Talk too much and I will kill you.
- Of all the ealdormen of wessex,
I am the man who can assemble
the greatest fyrd, the greatest army.
I now have to make a choice,
whether to side with guthrum
or with skorpa.
One Dane looks like the other
to me.
I am occupying your land.
Why should I not simply crush you?
Accept my invitation.
Eat with myself and with my father,
and I will tell you all about my land,
the range of my influence.
I am sure an agreement
can be reached.
Neither of us need lose any men.
Neither of us need be weakened.
- Eat?
- And drink. At my hall.
I assure you this is no trap.
I will arrive at your hall
after the new moon.
I shall expect you.
Then we have peace,
at least for a time?
Oh, we do.
You have lost much.
Fathers, mothers,
and a son,
lovers.
I have you.
I have a brother.
- Ragnar.
- Yes.
Your sister, thyra.
Yes?
She is alive.
No, she's dead. In the fire.
Uhtred, she lives and is being held
in the north.
It is the truth.
Skorpa told me.
I thought at first it could be a lie
to torment you.
Hearing it from me
would have made it true.
But now I know that it is true.
She lives.
You've seen it?
Yes. I've seen her.
But I will see her no more,
the gift is fading.
When this battle is done, uhtred,
your path leads north.
It will be time to face your past.
And you'll be with me?
Always.
Lord,
if god's help is required, how could he
look favourably upon uhtred,
a non-believer?
God is good.
Yes, lord, but in following the heathen,
what does that say about our beliefs?
Death could be waiting
over the very next hill,
and it will be uhtred
who stands in its way.
No doubt. A Dane will always protect
his plunder. The king is of value.
He is here to protect the king,
something we can't do.
- He is a man without a soul.
- Then I will be his soul.
I will pray for him. I will ride
beside him always and into battle.
- I will be his conduit to god.
- And if you fall in battle?
With the help of your prayers,
I shall become invincible, I'm sure.
Brother asser...
I should like you to be
the first of my messengers.
Morning.
Sleep well?
- He means did you hump well?
- I know what he means.
Sleep well, lady?
If I may speak to you all.
We are yet to complete
the first segment
and reach odda,
it's important we begin the second.
Word of our army's gathering point
must be dispatched
to the further reaches of our land.
Brother asser here will be
my first messenger.
- Halig.
- Yes, lord.
- You will also be my voice.
- I will, lord.
And me, lord.
Hild?
Lord, she is a woman.
I'm as good a horseman
as anyone here.
If it means more Danes will die,
then I'll do it.
Yes, hild.
You will.
- Your horses belong to whom?
- Lord odda.
- You'll let us pass?
- You selling or buying?
Selling. To the Danes.
There is a peace.
- Did you not know?
- That odda has made a peace?
No, I did not.
Odda is loyal.
We shall see for ourselves
what is true.
My lord.
Lord, you should remain out of sight...
Until we can be sure of your safety.
Odda is not a danger.
But who sits with odda?
- I will not hide.
- Lord. Hear the advice.
You are a symbol of wessex,
the standard around which
our army will gather.
You can't be put at risk.
Very well.
I must see this with my own eyes.
- Lord, that is not advisable.
- I've made up my mind.
If there is treachery,
it is something I must witness.
- I'll go with you.
- I do not require a nursemaid.
- I am a priest.
- And I a king.
You will wait here with iseult.
I am aware of the care I need to take.
Nuns should not be so pretty
nor have lips that demand to be kissed.
- I see you agree.
- When is it you're leaving?
When I am rested, lord.
Lord?
What is it?
Have the Danes arrived?
Leofric, he is outside.
Then bring him inside. He's our man.
Bring them both to me.
Leofric, uhtred.
My prayers have been answered.
God is good.
It is good to see you both
safe and well.
Leofric,
- you are home.
- Where in god's name have you been?
- Hiding, lord. And killing Danes.
- Hopefully not on my land.
We have been sent by
the king. We bring orders from the king.
- What king?
- King Alfred?
- Who else, lord?
- Wessex is full of kings.
There is guthrum,
who is king of east anglia,
who now sits in Winchester.
There's aethelwold, who'll tell anyone
who cares to listen that he is king.
Where will it end?
- I have Alfred's order.
- It means nothing.
- You are to raise the fyrd.
- It is over for Alfred.
Alfred gave up on wessex.
He decided to save himself.
No man has been more loyal to Alfred
than my father and I,
but he has failed us!
Danes surround us and he is hiding.
Alfred is king of the eels,
slippery and elusive.
I see it's true.
You have sided with the Danes.
What has skorpa promised you?
Are you to be king, odda?
- Leofric, are you still my man?
- Am I right?
I asked you a question, leofric.
I am still your man, lord.
Then you will finish the business
you have with this Dane and kill him.
You have my order. Kill him.
- Lord, I cannot do that.
- I'm Alfred's messenger.
I will not tell you again.
Should any man try to kill me,
that man is a traitor to the king.
You will kill him.
Alfred is no longer my king!
- I will not do it, lord.
- My son.
Father, you will not interfere.
May your mother forgive me.
And may you be forgiven
for your treason.
Lord, forgive him.
Let him die a noble. Forgive him.
I ask you this as your servant.
Odda...
You will do as I command.
You will raise the somerset fyrd.
Lord, forgive my son. Please!
I will not forgive what I have seen.
You will raise the fyrd.
Yes, lord.
I will need 20 horsemen...
To take word to all men
able to carry sword, hook or spear.
The word is that Alfred is king.
And will fight alongside the swords
of wessex to his dying breath!
May we speak...
_aboutourson?
You know?
Then there is nothing left to say.
I'm sorry that his death was something
that you had to face alone.
I was not alone. Being without
a husband does not mean I am alone.
Then I am sorry for the life
that I've given you.
I've found peace.
I hope you can do the same.
Was there sickness?
- I would like to understand.
- Children are frail.
You will have other sons, I'm sure.
With your queen.
- Is she here?
- Yes.
I would like you to leave me alone.
Never speak to me again.
We have nothing that binds us,
nothing.
Avoid me. Please.
Uhtred ragnarson.
Should I be pleased to see you?
- Skorpa of the white horse.
- I am expected by the lord odda.
The lord odda's in the ground,
buried as a traitor.
So, what now?
Do I speak with you?
Does the truce stand?
For today it stands.
Tomorrow we'll kill you.
You will kill me with what?
I have almost 1000 men
to call upon.
Your ships have been burned, skorpa.
By Alfred.
- He's gathering a great Saxon army.
- I am aware my ships are gone.
And I will have my revenge.
You should return to guthrum
and prepare to die.
Did your queen tell you...
That your sister
is being humped in the arse
each and every night
by one-eyed sven?
Did your mother tell you that
she should've kept her legs closed?
I will look for you first
across the battlefield.
I will be there
and I will not be difficult to find.
- He will go to guthrum?
- I believe he will, lord.
Then the battle is one step nearer.
Beocca, you should wash out
your mouth.
Yes, lord, I will. With ale.
- How many men?
- Four hundred. No more.
And this is the great Saxon army?
Their numbers will grow.
We need to march. There needs
to be a story of a slaughter.
Only days ago ragnar
was asking if the war was over.
Skorpa is right,
there must be a slaughter.
We must take the fight to Alfred
and his god.
And you are ready to kill your brother?
If it comes to that, yes.
Then we shall face one great army
with another.
Once the armies are
assembled, I shall speak to them as one.
Each man should know
this war is not only about land.
Should the heathens win,
then Christ is defeated.
When you speak to the men,
lord, you cannot make it a sermon.
Then what do you suggest I say?
Tell them that you'll die
for them, that's good.
Tell them that we'll make the Danes
pay in blood
and that they'll be rewarded in plunder.
I am to talk of revenge and greed?
They are men, lord, not angels.
- We shall stop for a moment.
- Hold!
It is egbert's stone.
Within these next few yards,
we will know if we have an army...
Of angels or otherwise.
I will go alone.
If no one is there, what then?
I see.
Not a single one.
Not a single man has answered my call.
Then we wait.
We must wait, lord.
- A Dane's knife.
- This thing?
Yes, I took it from a Dane.
A Dane I killed.
- Where?
- Winchester.
This is before you
grovelled to guthrum?
Before I presented myself to him, yes.
I was not, however, treated in a kingly
manner, and decided to escape.
A king under the Danes is no king.
Uhtred, I do like you,
but I rather tire of your preaching.
- You ever thought of becoming a priest?
- Ever since I was a boy.
That's a lie. I baptised him twice.
He's still not a Christian.
For luck.
Then I'll need a lock from you.
- Where's Alfred?
- Watching.
Waiting for his army.
I think I shall go and sit with him
a while.
You are fond of him now?
For luck.
http://hiqve.com/
I thought you would like company.
What do you see?
What do you hear? Tell me.
- I hear nothing, lord.
- No, no.
There is a change in the shadows.
In the air. They are out there.
I see nothing but grass, lord.
- And beyond the grass, trees.
- There, there.
It's men.
And more men there.
They have answered the call.
The swords of england, they're coming.
It's the swords of wessex.
The swords of england.
Today is a day for warriors.
A day to kill your enemies.
A day we make the pagans wish
they had never heard of wessex.
Today, we fight for wessex!
And not only for wessex.
We have men here from northumbria,
from mercia, from east anglia.
And why are the pagans here?
They want your wives
for their pleasure.
They want your children
as their slaves.
They want your homes as their own.
But they do not know us!
They do not know our swords.
They do not know our axes or Spears.
They do not know our courage.
And today, we kill them!
We shall make the ground red
with their blood.
We shall strip them
of what they have plundered.
We shall make them cry out for mercy,
and there will be none! No mercy!
No mercy! No mercy! No mercy!
Should I fail, you and hild are to take
my horse and ride clear of here.
- You will not fall.
- Everything I have
is packed in my bags. It's yours.
You will not fail.
I fight for you.
No mercy! No mercy! No mercy!
Then no mercy it must be.
Should you meet uhtred in battle,
there can be no doubt.
No mercy.
None.
We should not be holding back, lord.
We should attack with every man.
I will decide how we fight.
You will follow my orders.
Yes, lord.
No mercy.
- Form our lines.
- Form our lines!
Shields up!
- Advance!
- Come on!
Forward.
Hold the line. We work as one.
Shield, block.
Halt! — halt!
Wulfhere, I will have your guts,
you traitorous bastard!
This is our land!
Second!
First in line, as you wished.
Here they come.
Keep the wall tight!
Have that, wulfhere, you bastard.
Leofric!
Up to your feet. Leofric!
Leave him! Leave him!
Close the gaps! Keep the wall tight!
Forward! Three, two, one!
No mercy!
No more ground is to be lost!
Follow me!
- Hey!
- God have mercy.
We fall back as one!
- We ease! We ease!
- Ease! Ease!
Hold! We hold here! We go no further!
Edge backwards with me at my level!
And...
Uhtred ragnarson!
- Can you hear me?
- I hear you, skorpa.
- Do you wish to surrender?
- I have a gift for you.
Your queen!
No mercy!
You will be struck down with my spear!
And you will spend eternity
in the fires of hell!
Uhtred!
Take the horse.
Lord! What are your orders?
- Lord?
- Did you see that?
- It came as the priest said.
- What, lord?
Their god is with them.
What are your orders?
No, lord.
No mercy!
His grave is to be marked
like that of an ealdorman.
I shall see to it.
Uhtred.
Iseult is whole. She has been wrapped
and made ready for burial.
I want her to have a pyre.
Then she shall have it.
For all that you have done,
for all that you have shown me,
thank you.
You have given everything.
You are the man I always hoped
you would become.
In the year 878, at ethandun,
king Alfred defeated guthrum
of the Danes
and drove them from wessex.
I am indebted, uhtred of bebbanburg.
Wessex is indebted.
There can be no negotiations, lord.
Only surrender.
- That is your advice?
- It is.
Ihearyou.
Peace was secured with
hostages, including my friend brida...
And my brother young ragnar.
Peace was further secured
by Earl guthrum's baptism
and acceptance of the Christian god.
Do you renounce the devil
and all his work?
- I do.
- This water cleanse you
and make you worthy
of god's blessing.
- Guthrum, you are now a child of god.
- Amen.
As for uhtred the godless...
My journey continues.
My path leads north,
to blood feud,
to revenge...
And to bebbanburg.
Destiny is all.
http://hiqve.com/