I am uhtred, son of uhtred.
I was born a Saxon lord,
but raised by Danes as a warrior.
I now serve Alfred,
the Saxon king of wessex
and protect this last kingdom
of england from guthrum
and his viking army.
But not all believe in the king.
I am my father's heir.
To some, I am seen
as an enemy within.
With luck, he will fall in battle.
It is a court withoutjustice
where I will always
be seen a pagan,
even through the eyes of my pious
and now distant wife.
And so to pay off the debt on my land,
ip/undered, as a viking would.
And I found a pagan queen, a seer,
whose gift is linked to her purity.
She's not to hump.
I am now called a traitor.
I, brother asser, swear these oaths.
Alfred's court
decided I should be executed.
I request that he dies at my sword.
You will fight to the death.
Destiny is all.
Get out, you drunk bastard!
Is he here?
With a woman who's not his wife.
Drink it up.
Your friend is here.
May I sit?
Or will I spoil the gift of a last night
of freedom?
Do you believe I have betrayed you,
arseling?
-Idont - make no mistake,
odda had 20 men or more
ready to swear against you.
I am here to tell you that I am better
than you right now. I will kill you.
A warriors' death is all I can give.
Forgive me, but I am trying to forget
you are my friend.
As long as you understand.
If you have more to say,
you should say it.
Leofric! Leofric!
This isn't a fight I want.
I've been allowed my freedom tonight
and if I could slip away, I would.
But I cannot do that.
Reputation is all.
- I know it.
- I have feuds to settle,
promises to keep. I must live.
Then you must kill me.
- And you me.
- I intend to.
I will have the advantage.
The king's wife is praying for me.
- God loves her.
- Someone's got to.
It's been good to have you
as my friend.
I'll make your death quick
and painless.
- And then hump my queen?
- And your wife.
But you will be without your balls.
- I will see you tomorrow morning.
- — you will.
What are you thinking?
What goes on inside this head?
I was thinking how I would like
to lie with you,
you were?
- I cannot.
- Yes, you can.
I cannot. You know I cannot,
I will lose my gift.
Who cares?
The future is fate, it won't change.
And if today I die?
I have not seen your death.
Uhtred!
- The king wishes to speak to you.
- — about what?
He is unsure what to wear this morning
and needs your advice. With me.
Are you going to eat all of this?
- Or shall we save half for Edward?
- Heh, heh. He is a baby.
Is he really? I had quite forgotten.
- Uhtred.
- Lord.
Shh—shh—shh.
- I trust you slept well?
- I did not.
My son is coughing
and two of my best warriors
will today try to kill each other.
Today is the feast of Saint cedd.
We have decorated the great hall.
- Do you know of Saint cedd?
- No, lord.
Well, I like to think of him
as a symbol.
He worked in east anglia and mercia
and he died in northumbria,
your part of the country.
- A man of all england.
- Exactly, uhtred...
Which is why I am loathe
to shed Saxon blood
on his day of days.
Resume your debt,
despatch your "queen"
back to cornwalum,
and there need be no bloodshed.
Those are my terms,
they will not change.
If iseult returns to cornwalum,
she'll be killed.
I am prepared to resume the debt,
to save leofric,
but iseult must stay with me.
She is plunder and must be returned,
regardless of her fate.
I cannot abandon her!
The queen stays with me.
You are a fool.
You are a sinner and a heathen and I...
I have lost my Patience with you.
The fight will go ahead.
May your soul
receive its just reward.
Make way. Make way.
Silence!
Your majesty, lords, ladies,
great unwashed and stinking people
of Winchester!
We are gathered to witness justice.
We are gathered to witness a fight
to the end. That end being death,
that end being the fires of hell.
We are here to witness a battle
between uhtred, the godless...
And leofric of Winchester!
Take your shields.
Warriors.
Are you prepared?
- I am.
- Yes.
It is to the death,
no matter how death occurs.
May god choose his Victor.
Swords.
Begin!
Brother asser, I wish you well
on your return to cornwalum.
- You do not wish to see the outcome?
- No, I do not.
My dear, will you ask the nurses
to fetch the children?
I wish to walk with them.
Unh! Unh!
Ah!
Danes! The Danes are here,
they have breached the city walls!
Save yourselves!
The fight is finished,
arseling. Come on.
Stand to a man!
They are not to pass.
They are not to approach the palace!
Father, they will hack
the likes of us to pieces.
The king! Where is the king?
The king will have to make
his own arrangements.
And what of me? Odda! Odda!
Leofric, this way!
Go, quickly.
Hee-yah!
There'll be nothing left in the stables
but horse shit!
Let's go this way.
We hide here, wait for nightfall.
Am
I want the king and I want him alive,
crawling on his knees!
Follow me out front!
Keep away!
Stand back, I warn you.
God will protect me.
God will... ah!
Only guthrum can save you.
Guthrum is your god now.
- Should I spare you?
- Please.
Please.
Go in peace.
Find Alfred.
You are guthrum, great warrior.
I am aethelwold.
Son of king aethelred
and rightful king of wessex.
Alfred stole my crown.
This crown.
As king...
I am prepared to negotiate.
End of negotiation.
You smell like you've shit yourself.
I've not been well. Unh!
I pledge to you my allegiance. Unh!
No! Let go of me!
No! Ha, ha, ha.
No! Get off... no!
Lord, you are with me,
you will not desert me.
I feel nothing, except your love.
Iseult.
- Look out!
- Ah!
They are gone,
they are gone now. It is over.
They are gone.
We need to be gone ourselves.
Put on a helmet. We are Danes.
- Again?
- You will not leave me.
No, we will not.
You are prisoners.
Uhtred the Saxon.
What's this?
- You mean to do me harm?
- I haven't decided.
- Good to see you again, brida.
- Leofric.
How did you manage to get such a big
head into such a small helmet?
It was necessary.
Why are you doing this?
- Where's ragnar? Is he here?
- He's almost ready to travel north.
- To kill kjartan?
- What do you care?
The guards at the gates will be drunk.
Your way is clear.
Tell ragnar I am still his brother.
I'll tell him you were here
and that you left.
Arseling.
Brida has changed.
She was always angry.
Now she is nasty.
Either she has changed
or I have changed.
She once loved you.
Not anymore.
Even I could see that much.
I hate the forest.
Where is your wife?
I know you are married
to the lady mildrith.
She will have sought refuge...
With the church.
She used to come to the nunnery.
I would pray with her.
I watched her as she changed.
Why does a woman become a nun?
Because of her love for god.
God will never abandon her.
You were being humped
against your will.
He sent you.
- Is the king likely to have been killed?
- The king is not our concern.
If the king is dead,
then wessex is dead.
- Where are you going?
- I need darkness.
She needs darkness for what?
To see.
Leofric, where are we?
We are at the marshlands
of the severn. The swamplands.
I have never seen lands
like this before.
Hurry. They've seen us.
The boat won't wait.
- Priests.
- Come quickly, we need to leave.
- In fear.
- God preserve us.
Time to fight, arseling.
Ah!
Uhtred!
Arseling!
I have your sword.
We'll get you!
I hope you're carrying silver, priest.
We've saved your life.
I am saved by ghosts, it seems.
- Thank god you are unhurt.
- I was blessed.
- And your family?
- Are safe, they are in the boat ahead.
Hoping to find sanctuary
in these marshlands.
At the palace, lord,
they came from nowhere.
- They did.
- They came
because they were allowed to.
Where were your watchers?
Your spies?
On their knees, no doubt.
You should show respect.
Wessex allows its warriors
to kill each other
and spends too much time
on its knees.
Too much money on its churches.
If guthrum were Christian
and not pagan, there would be no war.
- But he's not.
- You do well to remember I am king.
- King of what? Look around you.
- He is our king.
Like every kingdom before it,
wessex has fallen.
He's Alfred, a man.
King of nothing.
http://hiqve.com/
Lord god, allow your blessed oils
to penetrate
and take away any
and all fever and sickness.
Restore health and strength
to the child
and to his ever watchful parents.
- Amen.
Amen.
Shh-shh-shh.
Lord, I have prepared a tonic.
For the pain.
For the pain you suffer here.
You pass blood? From your arse?
It is nothing more than what grows
from the earth, lord, drink it.
- It is good?
- Oh, not at all.
- Thank you.
- There will be more tomorrow.
He will become lost, I guarantee it.
Were you worried
that I would lose my way?
One path looks like another.
- You have explored?
- A little.
What do you notice about this place?
It is wet.
There are no horizons.
No sense of something beyond.
My priests have visited here
once or twice, to preach.
The people are oblivious to god.
You look tired.
Sleep has been a rarity, yes.
My wife would like us to take a ship
to frankia.
- To become another king in exile?
- So you admit I am still a king?
We dare not travel.
My son would never survive it.
You should send out word
that you are alive,
asking men to join you, to follow you.
And then what? Fight?
- Is that what you would do?
- It's what a king would do.
I have given it thought,
of course I have,
and this much I know:
If I am to fight, it would have to be
a single battle and soon.
Before yet more Danes arrive,
before wessex crumbles,
skirmish by skirmish, raid by raid,
piece by piece.
Therefore the first task would be
to somehow convince the Danes
to hold
one great and deciding moment.
- A single defining battle.
- Yes.
Who should I send?
Out into the country
with the news I am here.
It would be your priests, all of them,
each in a separate direction.
Their prayers are needed here.
Your son grows weaker despite
their prayers.
For that I am sorry.
Every breath is an effort for him.
I don't know whether to make him warm
or keep him cool.
Shh. — we will...
We will remain here until he is well.
Shh. Shh.
Shh.
Will the child die?
Can you save him?
There is a way...
Though it is not a good way.
If it is the only way, then you must.
You are feeling a little better, lord?
Iseult is a healer.
She could help your son.
Thank you.
If you help, then you better succeed.
If the child dies, you will be blamed.
- We cannot do nothing.
- That is not what I am saying.
Iseult is a pagan and a woman.
She will be blamed,
regardless of her meaning well.
If it is true that Alfred
is in the swampland,
how long do we wait for him
to come out?
If he is hiding in the swampland,
we would be tools to go searching.
Have you ever seen anything like this?
- Monasteries keep words like this.
- No, no. Not like this.
What does it all mean?
- What does all this speak of?
- I cannot say I care.
Whatever Alfred found out
about his enemies, he would write.
Yeah. It's magic. Yeah, it is.
- You are laughing.
- It's a weak kind of magic.
No, you are wrong.
This is words without sound.
This is voices without people.
I'm going to learn how to use
this magic.
If we took Alfred, he could teach you.
Only a fool would march an army
into a swampland.
Are you that fool?
Are you that fool, ragnar?
No, I am not.
Then we wait.
We need to be closer.
Uhtred.
The water is rising.
- Lord, you had one task.
- Oh, no. I am sorry.
I've never cooked before,
and never again, I fear.
- Are they burned?
- They are done well, lord,
a challenge for your teeth
and stomach.
I've seen a fleet on the severn.
They carry skorpa's colours.
- How many ships?
- Twenty or more.
That's over 1000 men.
- Guthrum will have the same.
- More.
- God save us.
- We can save ourselves.
We must believe it.
Will the lady be joining us, lord?
No. She will not.
She is angry with me still,
for sending away the priests.
Sending out the priests
was the right thing, lord.
Let us pray you are correct.
If you will excuse me.
If the child dies, it will take the fight
from Alfred's bones...
And we will never save ourselves.
You must end this silence.
The priests will fetch men.
Without men, safe passage to the south
and frankia will be impossible.
At best, our children
would be taken as slaves.
You are eating meat.
Why?
These last few days,
the pains have abated.
Meat does not agree.
I could not cope with further sickness.
In the mind of brother asser,
she is a witch
and yet you gladly drink her potions.
- It is a tonic.
- I can read you.
You wish to put our child
in the hands of the devil.
Our prayers are not being answered.
Is it any wonder we find ourselves
living in a muddy puddle?
Father, please.
Come and sit by the fire.
I bring word. From the king.
He lives?
Wessex lives and breathes,
wulfhere.
Thank god.
Oh, my goodness.
She has the nerve to approach.
She has helped me.
Thank you.
I for one do not wish
to hear your voice.
Do not speak a word.
Is there something
you wish to say, iseult?
If you wish, lord,
I will try to help your child.
- We do not wish.
- Tonight is a good night.
We do not wish.
- Tomorrow it will be too late.
- What kind of talk is that?
What kind of talk is "too late"?
Are you saying that my child
will die?
- Aelswith. Aelswith, please.
- Get her away from me.
Get her away from me!
Get out of my sight!
- Stop.
- Get her out of my sight!
She is offering help.
My priests told me
that you are a witch
- and they are correct!
- She is no witch!
- Aelswith, please, no more.
- No, please, no!
You are upsetting yourself
and you are upsetting the children.
Please. No, no, no. No.
Please.
Go. Go. Please.
Iseult, you must prepare.
It can only be tonight.
She will be ready.
Shh-shh-shh.
The child will pass from one chamber...
To the other.
From near death to life.
What is it?
If this child is to live,
then another, somewhere, must die.
I will be taking a life,
a stranger, an innocent.
Iseult...
This must be done.
Lady aelswith?
Leave me.
Icannot
- leave me. — lady...
You need comfort.
When a child suffers...
The mother suffers.
I know this.
I know the pain you feel.
It's almost unbearable.
Even for a queen.
I will stay only for as long
as you need me,
for a moment or a year.
He is dying.
She is a pagan.
And yet she has helped the king.
I am to trust a stranger with my child.
There is good in iseult.
I don't know what is worse,
when he cries or when he is still.
When he is still,
I feel the need to prod him awake.
- It is retribution. God is punishing me.
- For what?
For aethelwold for taking his crown.
Aethelwold is a fool,
he could never be king.
Your god is testing you.
Lord, give Edward to iseult.
If god will not cure Edward,
what makes you think that
he would allow a pagan to succeed?
Who is to say that god is not working
through us all?
Did he not make the pagans too?
Beocca would tell me that
god's ways are known only to himself.
You have been brought to the marshes
for a reason.
You have this one chance
to save your son,
and you will have one chance
to save your kingdom.
The two are bound together.
Edward is your heir.
If he lives, I would say it is a sign...
Wessex will live.
Shh.
There is barely a heartbeat.
Let me give the child to iseult.
May god have mercy on each of us.
Where is he taking him?
Am I allowed to know?
To iseult.
God is watching.
Lord?
Good morning, lord.
We received your message
and came as quickly as we could.
- Father beocca? Is that you?
- Yes, lord.
- You are here?
- I am, lord.
- You have brought men. Wulfhere.
- Lord.
- Well, how warming it is to see you all.
- It's good to see you again, lord.
And many more are nearby.
Guards, men,
even the brother, asser, is here.
We have all been saying prayers
for your health and safety.
- Praying? Yes.
- And for Edward, of course.
Every priest in the land
has been instructed
to hold service for his recovery.
For Edward, I am blessed.
How is the boy, lord?
Lord?
What is it, lord?
Oh, please, god, please, god, no.
Say he has not been taken from me.
No, lord, this is not his grave.
- He is well, lord.
- What?
- And he is healed.
- Healed?
Lord, what is this?
- It's good news, father. Rejoice.
- He is well.
He is well. It is true. He's...
He is well. He is cool.
He is well, beocca.
I can feel his heart beating strongly.
- God has not forsaken you, lord.
- Fetch aelswith, fetch his mother!
The prayers of the whole of wessex
have been answered.
- Indeed.
- Every mass, lord,
every mass said by 100 priests
or more has been heard.
- Look at him. Look at him, he is well.
- God is good. Praise him!
Yes, praise him, father beocca.
You did well. Why the tears?
They are for the stranger's child.
- You are wet, arseling.
- I am.
Wet, tired, but I have a plan.
Lord, the ships are guarded
by no more than 60 men.
The rest of the army will be inland
looking for food.
We kill the men, we burn the ships.
You really believe skorpa will then
go to guthrum?
I do. One army, one battle.
It's the only way, lord.
It begins here, in these waters.
You were brought here for this reason,
lord.
They need to give chase and they
need to believe they can reach us.
We stand our ground
until the very last moment.
Then we stay on the safe path and let
the land half kill them before we attack.
And if they do reach us?
Ready?
Remember, don't kill them,
just make them mad.
Are you wishing to die?
Who are you, you piece of shit?
- You want me to spill your guts?
- Here I am, I am waiting.
- We'll send each of you to corpse hall!
- Hit the big bastard!
Come and fight. Are you afraid?
We stand our ground.
Now!
Now for the ships.
A new horizon, lord.
A beacon of hope.
God has tested you, lord.
He has put you into the fire,
as a Smith would his steel.
And like the steel,
you have emerged stronger.
- Praise him.
- Praise him, lord.
You are right, beocca.
God works in the strangest of ways,
known only to himself.
http://hiqve.com/