Boy!
The tide is on the turn!
I'm not warning you again!
Ships! There!
Danes.
The devil's turds.
- Are they traders?
- No. They come as vikings!
We go!
Hold on!
Where's my son?
Uhtred. Take half a dozen men,
ride to the river.
There are pagans there.
Watch them, see how many.
- Of course.
- Do nothing more.
- Yes, father.
- Osbert.
- What is it?
- Ships. I saw them.
- What ships?
- Danes. They're heading for the river.
God and his saints preserve us.
They have no soul.
- We must pray.
- We must act.
Uhtred. Do not fight them,
not a single one.
- Be back by nightfall.
- Yes.
They are sent by god to punish us
for our sins.
They're here to support the viking army
in eofennic.
Instruct the priest
to pray for our deliverance.
- Aelfric!
- Lord?
- Get them inside.
- Take in the women and elders.
The rest to higher ground,
out of sight.
Rouse the country.
I want every man in this fortress.
And every man
must be prepared to die.
Port side ready to row!
- Port side ready!
- Starboard side ready to row!
Starboard side ready to row!
- Rest your oars!
Taste.
- Sweet water.
- Yes.
What else do you see?
Earl ragnar:
I see a clear river,
fish as big as a man's leg.
I see a forest alive with meat.
More than that,
I see a place to grow fat and old.
Horses.
Yeah. And I see spies,
shitting themselves.
We'll meet sword with sword!
You are pagans!
We have the greater god on our side!
Kjartan. I think
we should teach this boy a lesson.
Taking her in.
- At speed!
- Pick up the speed!
- Come back with me! Move it!
- To the fort! Come on!
Grab the children! Move!
Why do I leave
the villages unprotected
and bring the men inside?
Is that your question?
A village can be rebuilt,
a warrior can die only once.
The Danes may be heading south
to eofennic,
but they will kill
whoever they can on the way.
Now, go and find the priest.
Yes, father.
Come in, osbert,
don't skulk in the shadows.
He wants to know if you're ready.
Almost.
Do you know what I'm tasked with?
- Um, a letter?
- A response to a letter, this letter
from king aella.
Asking your father for his support,
his army,
to help recapture
the city of eofennic.
This is why it's important
to read and write.
Father can't read nor write.
Yeah, well,
for your father it's too late.
King aella could have sent
a man on horseback.
Who's to say the man on horseback
speaks the truth?
Or has remembered
the true message?
What these letters will represent
is history, facts.
Your father is informing king aella
and king osbert
he will be alongside their armies
at eofennic.
And the Mark of bebbanburg
will guarantee the truth of it.
Why do we fight for eofennic?
Well, we fight for eofennic
because we do not wish to see england,
piece by piece, become daneland.
Heh, heh. I heard it said
that we were pagans once,
that woden and Odin are the same.
We saw the error of our ways,
looked to Rome.
I heard the pagans
had fierce gods of war.
Well, we are right
and they are mistaken.
Osbert, we are blessed.
I should make you swear
on st cuthbert's comb
never to mention
the likes of woden again.
But what if I had a hound
called woden?
- What would you do then?
- What if you had a pig called Thor?
- Come. Let's go see your father.
- A pig called Thor.
- Is it really st cuthbert's comb?
- Of course it's st cuthbert's comb,
and his holy hair
lies in the teeth of that comb.
- Where was your father last?
- He was humping the servant girl.
- That's a lie, osbert.
- No.
- Are you never gonna tire of teasing?
- Nope.
Horsemen approaching!
He rides uhtred's horse.
Osbert.
Bury what's left of him.
Osbert, come on.
Remind me of the last words
I spoke to him.
You told him to watch and do not fight.
We have...
Do not fight means do not fight.
- He was young.
- No fight until eofennic.
You wanted to see osbert, my lord.
You are now called uhtred.
Uhtred, son of uhtred.
You have your stone, the Amber?
- Yes.
- The priest will show you your history,
- parchments. Make him understand.
- Lord, I...
I should like to baptise him again.
If he arrives at heaven's gate
as uhtred,
they might wonder
what's happened to osbert.
Do what you must, but do as I ask.
Lord.
We were kings here once, boy.
Kings of all the lands
- between rivers tuede and tine.
- We should be kings again.
We should, but it does not matter
what they call us so long as they obey.
Our ancestors took this land.
It's been strengthened
with our blood and bone.
And now you are the new heir
of bebbanburg. You hear me?
And you will die for it if needed.
And I'll give you the head of the man
who killed uhtred.
No, you are uhtred!
Have you not been listening to me?
Do not tell me what it is you will do,
you are just a pup.
You will give me nothing.
You will watch and you will learn.
Put him in the water before
his mother's tongue gives me grief.
She's not my mother.
Will you take him with you to battle
to watch and learn?
I need you to choose 30 men
and remain here at bebbanburg.
Protect the boy. He is the heir.
Thirty will hold, few enough to feed.
Do this for me?
I'd rather be with you,
but I'll do as you ask.
Thank you.
Come on, quickly.
Up there, go on.
Hurry, please.
Heavenly father,
receive your servant, uhtred,
into the holy kind of saints
and into the ranks
of the most bright angels.
Let your holy waters cleanse him
and make and him worthy
of your blessing,
make him your instrument
and your rod.
Let him realise
the significance of the written word
so that he may learn of your glory
and in turn may spread your word.
- Beo...
- Let him grow in wisdom
and in respect
- so he may lead in a godly manner.
- Beo...
Beocca, he's cleansed.
Amen.
Uhtred, son of uhtred of bebbanburg,
welcome to the Christian world.
Behold your people and your land.
Where are the people, the soldiers?
On the road to eofennic,
led by your father,
where they'll join
the other two kings.
- Without me?
- You are to remain at bebbanburg
with your uncle. I'm to keep you safe.
You wish to fight, we arm-wrestle.
- Where's the priest?
- With your father. Eat.
You have work to do, uhtred,
in the stables.
Thankfully, we've been left
some horses.
- You should eat.
- I'm not hungry.
We have work to do.
Horse shit to shovel.
Come and find me
when you've finished.
Scallion,
if my brother falls in battle,
the boy must fall.
All this way and no reception party.
Earl ragnar.
Guthrum.
- How are you?
- I'm fine. I'm hungry.
- And your boy?
- He's coming.
- Ragnar.
- I brought men, horses.
Good to see you. You well?
You made a gift
of his own son's head?
How did this lord react?
He did nothing.
He brought his warriors
into the fortress, kept them inside.
- It was not cowardice.
- Restraint.
He is saving his men.
That man is uhtred.
One of the three kings
of northumbria.
- Warrior king.
- Other two are fools.
They'd rather be fighting each other.
- This is true?
- King aella and king osbert,
they both lay claim to eofennic.
They have the strangest of names.
- So when do we fight?
- Soon, I hope.
I'm still to decide.
Fools or not, they have three armies.
- They have numbers.
- But are divided.
Three kings, but only one
who can lead them. This uhtred.
Kill him and northumbria is ours,
all of it.
Listen to him. Listen to the boy.
He reminds me of me.
Yeah, when you were younger.
Heh, heh.
Of course when I was younger.
- He's just a boy.
- Just saying.
- Ubba...
- Did you say I was old? Storri.
- No.
- I'm not getting old.
I have seen the land outside the city.
I have a plan in mind, a good plan.
And my son would like
to wet his sword with you.
So do we fight?
The signs are good.
Only this morning, I saw a raven
fly towards the Saxon camp,
and it was asking me to follow.
- I'm sure of it.
- Mm.
Then we fight.
We fight!
What kind of hell is this?
It's a pagan's hell.
We outnumber them.
There are more. There must be.
Nothing changes.
We attack with half our number,
second half to follow
once we have the measure of them.
- They have conceded higher ground.
- King aella,
yours and lord uhtred's armies
will attack in the first wave.
Prepare! Prepare!
Shield!
No. No, not without me.
Come nightfall,
we'll be rid of this plague
and counting our share
of the plunder!
My shield.
http://hiqve.com/
The wall is holding.
Go! Hands below
your shield and drive! Drive!
Ease.
Ease!
- Ease!
- Push!
Keep pushing! It's working!
Drive them!
They're tiring, can't fight back.
We're winning, look.
We're winning.
Follow!
Drive on!
Not yet! Not yet!
Dear god, no.
Shield!
Dear god of infinite mercy, not this.
Legs! Legs!
Protect your legs!
Lift up your sword
and spare these men of england
who fight in your name.
Let the heathens' hearts
crumble and wither.
Bestow your power
upon these men of england,
so they can glorify your name
with the blood of the devils.
Have mercy now, lord.
Do not forsake us.
Do not forsake england.
Follow me! Follow me!
Close the shield wall!
Close the wall and take him!
He's like a wasp. Ha, ha.
- Wasp has lost its sting.
- Yeah.
Argh!
Ow!
Unh!
Are you sure he's a Saxon?
He fights like a Dane.
Yeah.
Get up!
Leave her.
She is to live.
Some of these young ones
can come in useful.
Father, here's the boy I spoke of.
The one who almost killed you?
You're leaving him with me?
I've never seen a man
get the better of you yet.
Cut me some chicken.
Careful, the blade is sharp.
It can kill a man.
The chicken is on your platter.
Have you always been blind?
Oh, I see enough.
So who have they
been killing below?
Prisoners.
Just now a king.
Did he die well?
- No.
- Then he shouldn't have been king.
Tell me,
who sits in the middle of the hall?
Is it the big man and a small man?
Yes, and a grey man
sits in between them.
If you get to live, you should
beware of the big man. Ubba.
My advice for you
is to never cross ubba
and never, never fight him.
- If I get to live?
- He listens to no one but the gods.
Men who take their orders
from the gods are unpredictable.
What did you mean
when you said if I get to live?
You're my prisoner.
The grey man will be egbert.
He's a Saxon ealdorman.
He has pledged allegiance
and now calls himself king.
He is king of nothing.
Soon all of the kings in england
shall be kings of nothing.
Northumbria is ours.
Mercia will soon by ours.
Then east anglia, cornwalum,
and then the greatest prize
is the last kingdom, wessex.
I've heard of wessex.
Anything will grow in wessex.
Tell me your name.
I'm the ealdorman of bebbanburg.
- You are, huh?
- I am. I own lands to the north.
How long have you been
an ealdorman of these lands?
Your father chose to fight us
and is now dead.
He... he was not fond of me.
I now understand
why my son spared you,
uhtred of bebbanburg.
You are a warrior.
Have some ale.
Here.
Take it up there.
I'm thinking of keeping them both,
the boy and the girl.
Can help your mother.
- Disagree?
- No.
But we did kill his father.
If he's an ealdorman,
we could sell him for ransom.
Perhaps.
Brida, be careful not to spill the water.
You'll turn the floor to mud.
Uhtred, wood needs to be chopped.
Brida, you can do the goats.
Will there be time for uhtred to play?
Only when work is done.
I don't like our daughter
having to play with slaves.
- They're only children.
- They have a place.
Heh. Grumpy.
My horse.
Hey, ragnar ragnarson.
Hey, uhtred of wherever.
How about you teach me
how to use a sword?
We don't teach slaves how to fight.
That tongue of yours
will be your death, boy.
Now, get back to work.
What does the play involve?
We built a hall in the gorge.
I'm the mistress
and uhtred is a warrior.
Not a servant?
It is a game.
A wolf. Uhtred.
That's it, a wolf.
Boar. Watch out!
I saw it.
Its sharp teeth and yellow eyes.
- Don't let the wolves get to me, uhtred.
- Use the fire to keep them away.
I see them. They're as big as ubba
and smell worse.
Did you see that?
Stay up there.
- Uhtred, what is happening?
- Stay up there, thyra.
- It's sven, he won't hurt you.
- But he'll kill us.
Argh!
He'll kill us! Run!
That was a real sword.
I saw it.
- Ah! Uhtred!
- Thyra.
Uhtred!
Ah!
What's this?
You been fighting again?
- Yes.
- With sven?
- Kjartan's son?
- Yes.
- Uhtred, he's much bigger than you.
- He's a turd.
- Why do you say that?
- Who started it?
- Who began the fight?
- I began the fight.
For no other reason
than that he's a turd?
Danes have murdered for less.
Uhtred, that's enough.
- You want to be sold, boy?
- I wish to eat.
- Speak up.
You want to eat?
You know what?
I say you starve.
Fighting is expected,
disobedience is not.
Sven began the fight.
Kjartan!
Earl ragnar, let me first say,
he's a good boy.
He brought a sword onto my land.
I will have words with him.
- In time, he'll serve on your ship.
- He has offended me.
- He will honour you. He meant no harm.
- He meant no harm?
He looked
at my daughter's nakedness.
And he was punished.
Your Saxon slave cut him.
Shall I make a square of branches?
Are you gonna fight me for your son
or fetch him?
Sven. Come out here.
- Tell him what you have to say.
- I'm sorry.
- He can't hear you.
- I'm sorry, lord, for what I did.
You laid hands on my daughter.
You stripped her naked.
- Half-naked, lord.
- He's at an age, lord.
Is this true?
- Half-naked?
- Yes, lord.
Then I shall only take his one eye.
- No, lord, please.
- Ah!
Kjartan, you are banished from my land.
I have something for you.
What is it?
An amulet. Thor's hammer.
- — But, uh...
- But what?
You're Christian.
- I can't.
- Don't you want it?
- I do want it.
- Take it.
- I'm trying.
- I don't think he wants it.
- I do want it.
No, I don't think so.
Thank you.
Tell me about Denmark.
Your home.
What can I say about Denmark?
It's wet.
The ground is so flat and Sandy,
you can't grow a fart.
Which is why we're here in england.
To grow.
And why young ragnar
will soon be going for Ireland.
You leave to fight?
To make my wealth.
If you want land or silver,
you have to take it.
You made me proud today, uhtred.
You made me proud.
I don't know you.
You don't have the appearance
of a messenger,
- and ubba's payment's not yet due.
- No, lord.
I was a ship's master.
Well, I have no ships.
I need no ship's master.
I have news
that you will want to hear.
- Well?
- I would want something in return, lord.
Not now, not coin.
But perhaps we can continue
to help each other.
Perhaps.
Two days south of here
is Earl ragnar,
the man I used to serve
until he banished me.
He has a slave, treats him well.
This is a slave you're entitled
to buy back if you wish to.
- Buy back?
- It's your nephew uhtred, lord.
He lives.
What if I'm against being ransomed?
Your family has discovered
that you're still alive
and they wish for you to be returned.
But they must pay.
- Pay ragnar?
- Ubba takes more than half.
It's normal.
But I have no family.
Keep them over there, tether the horses.
Scallion. Him.
Are they treating you well?
- I am fed, yes.
- Good.
Good, that's all we ask.
What is that around your neck,
some symbol?
- Oh, this? They make me wear it.
- May I see it?
Look, I will speak plainly.
Your uncle will kill you.
Right? You cannot go back
to bebbanburg.
You must escape.
He wants to be the ealdorman,
wants to be king.
Like the pathetic egbert over there.
A puppet king for his Danish masters.
You should go to wessex.
Seek out for that real king aethelred
and his brother the prince Alfred,
they're good men,
good Christian men.
That's enough
whispering in his ear, priest.
- Uhtred.
- One more word,
I'll have your ball bag for a purse.
I'll meet you there.
That will not be necessary.
What did he say?
He... he asked
if you were treating me well.
- How much?
- Three hundred.
That is a ridiculous amount.
How can a boy be worth
300 pieces of silver?
Because I say so,
because he is a lord and an ealdorman.
No, he is a boy.
I am the ealdorman of bebbanburg.
I carry the seal and banner.
That seal is my father's,
which is now mine.
You be silent.
You are for sale, nothing more.
- For ransom, lord.
- That's what I said.
My lords,
I have given up land, horses.
I've offered a generous supply of food
as well as my sword.
All I ask in return
is a fair price for my only nephew.
What would you say is a fair price?
- I'll offer a hundred pieces of silver.
- Two hundred.
My allegiance and 100 pieces
is surely a fair price.
It is not.
I will give 120 pieces of silver
for the boy.
Heh, heh, heh. Not enough.
Very well.
Two hundred pieces.
I agree to your terms.
The boy is sold to Earl ragnar.
- What?
- Ransomed, lord.
That is what I said.
The matter is closed.
My lords, I have come a long way.
I have offered my allegiance.
Which is why
you're allowed to breathe.
If you have an argument,
it's with me now.
If business is done,
- we have ale to drink.
- And king egbert needs to sit.
Am I not for ransom anymore?
You heard ubba, I bought you.
I thought I might sacrifice you
to Odin.
You bought me for how much?
- Too much.
- How much is too much?
My sword's weight in silver.
I agree I may have been robbed,
but we like you, boy.
We're going to keep you.
Does this mean I'm a Dane?
It means you're uhtred ragnarson.
- You are a son to me now.
- Ah!
Brida, not that way.
Take the goat out the side.
Next time, I promise.
- Mother, look.
- It's beautiful. It really is.
I can't believe
I'm losing you already.
I will be living across the field.
If he doesn't treat you well,
come marching back across that field.
Oh, look at this place.
Uhtred, do you like
my wedding necklace?
I do. Very pretty.
He doesn't know anything
about necklaces.
You might as well ask me.
Uhtred, with me.
You can help me slaughter the goats.
- I've only just washed.
- Ha, ha.
The goats will be pleased.
Later you can sweep the floor. Unh!
Ha, ha, ha.
Move over.
This is an excuse to talk, that's all.
With thyra to be married,
maybe it's time you got together
with brida.
There are men, good men,
asking about her.
So you have to decide
what you are to her.
- What you are to each other.
- Heh, heh, heh.
- Brida has her own mind.
- She has.
But I see the way she looks at you.
She's watching the charcoal tonight
in the woods.
Take my horse and join her.
- The earth will be warm.
- Heh, heh, heh.
Why not?
I just thought in order to be
a real Dane, I had to marry a Dane.
Come on.
I love you like I love young ragnar.
What are you doing here?
Do you ever think
of your English life?
Who you were
before we came to ragnar?
Do you?
- I think of who I...
- Shh.
Voices.
Men below.
Danes. Who are they?
That's kjartan.
Remember him?
And that must be sven.
This is wrong.
We need to tell ragnar.
They're between us and the hall.
Then we go up and around.
We leave the horses and run.
In front of the door. That's it.
Ragnar, smoke.
Fire! Thyra, wake up!
All them! Wake up!
Fire!
Come on! Come on!
This way. Ravn.
- Help me!
- Come. Come, quickly.
Come.
- The door is blocked.
- So is this one.
Be ready.
This one's open!
This one's open. Come on, follow me.
This way.
Take the children.
Take them all.
Archers!
Don't go up there. Wait for me.
Come. Come.
- Unh!
- Ragnar.
Close the doors.
We have thyra. Let the rest burn.
Take her with you to Valhalla.
Yes. I will meet you there.
Argh!
No. Oh, no.
Find the silver.
They're searching
for ragnar's wealth.
- They'll never find it.
- Search in the back.
Come on, we're leaving soon.
You thought I'd left you,
marry someone else.
But do you know
what I will do with this body?
This mouth?
I will do all I have dreamt of
and more.
And who will call a halt?
Earl ragnar the fearless is gone.
And with him,
uhtred, his Saxon pet,
a pile of ashes.
Anything.
- Shh. Get down.
- Look at that man, the Saxon.
His name's scallion.
He works with my uncle.
- He'll tell him that I'm dead.
- Let him do it.
- I see him with kjartan.
- Burn it to the ground.
Maybe they're in it together.
And what makes them believe
they can do this without punishment?
Shh. They will be punished,
but not by you.
Uhtred, listen to me,
we serve ragnar best alive.
We tell the story.
- I need to kill someone.
- No.
And I choose him.
Uhtred, no.
Come on!
The main thing
is to keep the horses together here.
Don't leave any weapons behind.
Move those over
and we'll look in the back.
Don't leave anything in there.
Just bring it all out.
A little bit more.
Yeah. Over here!
Hey, come on.
Yeah. You know who I am?
It's me you're looking for.
You remember me?
There's no more.
- We're going.
- Come on.
Bring the horses.
By right it belongs to young ragnar.
Yes. But we spend what we need
to spend. We stay alive.
We tell the story and then what?
We find a new lord to serve.
I will not stand by and have
everything that's mine taken from me.
I'm going back.
Where?
To the beginning.
- Is it scallion?
- No, my lord.
- He looks like a Dane.
- Could be one of kjartan's men.
I am uhtred of bebbanburg.
I shall take what is mine!
Bebbanburg's mine!
Horses.
http://hiqve.com/