My name is uhtred, son of uhtred.
I was born an ealdorman
of northumbria.
The rightful heir to bebbanburg.
But fate decreed
I would be raised as a Dane.
That was my life
until my family was murdered.
Word was spread
that I was to blame.
A Saxon slave, he killed his master
at a wedding party.
And so, with brida, I fled to wessex.
To Alfred,
a man who would become king.
- Though not all agreed.
- I am my father's heir.
I swore an oath to this king.
An oath that lost me brida
and prevented me
from joining my brother ragnar.
But destiny is all.
You don't deserve to marry.
That woman is a lady
and you're a heathen.
You could bathe all day,
you'd still stink.
Have you been watching me, odda
the boy? Should I be marrying you?
Ten pieces of silver
for you to walk away.
Does your father know you're here?
Eleven pieces.
How about my sword's weight
in silver?
Nonsense.
Then I'll marry the girl.
And tonight, I'll plough her.
- Why must you talk of her like that?
- Perhaps you'd like her for yourself.
You want her beneath you.
Am I right?
You're impossible to reason with.
Everything is a game.
I hope for mildrith's sake,
your time on this earth is short.
You are not an ealdorman
and never shall be.
Hey! Here!
I wasn't allowed to meet her.
I haven't seen her.
It is the way.
I was unaware of her existence
till yesterday.
- She'll be plain and pious?
- Oh, she'll be pious, all right.
If she was a leg-spreader,
Alfred would have been on her by now.
Have you seen her?
A distance away.
"Plain" is a fair description.
How much was the bride price?
Thirty-three pieces.
Which I have paid
to her godfather odda
and which I'll make sure
she receives.
I've made promises.
Revenge and such.
Why are you here? Do you know?
She brings land.
I'll become a lord under Alfred.
I'll be able to make wealth, gather men.
- Take back what's mine.
- All reasons enough.
Plain or not,
she serves her purpose.
The promises you have made
will stand.
Blood feuds last a lifetime.
What you do, arseling, is you
keep living each day until the last.
The priest has arrived finally.
Let's get this done.
You do not need to "get this done."
I will make a plea to Alfred.
She's here, praise god.
You should stand and look respectful,
if not entirely clean.
- How does she look?
- Terrified, I bet.
If you could be brief with
the ceremony, father beocca,
I'd be grateful.
I have business with the king.
The bride has been given her price?
She will.
You are witness.
Thank you, lord.
If the betrothed couple
would like to join me at the altar...
- And join hands.
- Be brief.
May god in his heaven
look down with mercy
upon his devoted servants,
uhtred and mildrith.
May he bless their union
with love, and children, and wealth.
And may they, in turn,
be sure to give thanks and praise,
and live each day
according to his holy word. Amen.
- Amen.
You are now joined as man and wife
in the eyes of god.
Tears of joy.
Allow me to help you with that.
Thank you, lord.
I'm a lucky man...
To have such a beautiful wife.
There must have been
many suitors, I'm sure.
You're kind to believe so.
Am I right?
None suitable, lord.
My name's uhtred. Call me uhtred.
Arseling, time we were on our way.
Or from time to time,
you may wish to call me "arseling."
Lord.
Danes.
Why are we stopping?
Who are they?
Foragers, most likely.
- But Danes all the same.
- Will they attack?
We walk on.
They're following us.
We walk on. They won't attack.
Then why have you
drawn your sword?
To show them at least
one of them will die.
One or two.
- Foragers are deep into wessex.
- They're guthrum's men.
They're a long way from lundene.
Lord, the marriage has taken place.
They are now on the road
to the farmstead.
Good news. Thank you, odda.
We shall see how he responds
to the challenge.
Now it is done, lord,
I do fear for mildrith.
She will have to give him the facts.
Oh, he will bark at her,
odda, I'm sure.
But his real anger
will be reserved for you and I.
He will not like being beholden
to god and to king.
But if he is to become
a true ealdorman,
he must accept his burden.
That is the test.
Yes, lord.
Mildrith is his beautiful consolation.
Was he struck by her?
He was, lord.
Why are you not already married?
You're old enough to have had
two or three children by now.
Lord arseling.
There is a time for such questions,
and it has past.
Why has Alfred gifted me
such a beautiful bride?
Has a debt, I'm guessing.
It's not my place to tell you.
How much?
My father wanted to find favour
with god
so he devoted a tenth of his land
to the church.
They do not own it,
but they are entitled to its yield.
Indeed, they demand its yield,
even when crops fail and Danes raid.
God is good.
So the bishop took my father to law.
How much is the debt?
The church is the law.
And the law decreed that my father
owed to them a huge sum.
- Quite beyond his ability to pay.
- How much?
He died soon after.
It is a substantial amount, lord.
It increases yearly.
Alfred could remove the debt.
He has chosen not to.
The amount owed
is 2,000 shillings, lord.
Damn him.
Damn everything he stands for.
- Damn his church and his god.
- Lord, I don't like your blasphemy.
My name is uhtred!
Though by all means, call me "arseling"
for not seeing this sooner.
Your new home.
The land is good.
The buildings need repair.
Families who live on the land
come to wish us well.
Send them back to their homes.
They've come to wish us well.
I have known them my whole life.
Lord. Lady.
Oswald manages the farmstead.
He lives nearby.
Welcome home. And may we offer
our good wishes on your marriage.
Thank you, oswald. Thank you.
And how kind of you all to gather
to greet me and my lord uhtred.
We have prepared a table, lord,
for your pleasure.
You have my thanks, but we're tired.
Of course, lord.
Thank you, oswald. You're kind.
I have a wedding gift for each family.
- It is silver.
- Thank you, lady mildrith.
- For your kindness and your loyalty.
- Thank you so much.
For taking care of the land
in my absence.
Now, there's a welcome sight.
I was expecting there
to be a hall, and I find this.
Pay off your debts,
and you can build a hall.
Didn't I tell you the bastard thinks?
Alfred.
If he believes he can make me beg,
he can think again.
He doesn't want you to beg.
He wants you to obey.
Never.
If you have need for me, lord,
I'll be resting.
It seems I am tired.
I'm 2,000 shillings in debt to the church,
and you hand out silver to your tenants.
It is my silver.
- Have what's in my purse.
- I don't want what's in your purse.
Then why scold me?
The stoat. Your farmstead master.
- Oswald.
- He'll need to be watched.
- He was trusted by my father.
- He lives too well.
- I'm on my way to the barn.
- You can sleep in the house.
I prefer the barn. Thank you.
It is your wedding night.
Good night, lady.
Arseling.
May I leave now?
How many pieces of silver
did you receive as your price?
Eighteen.
Is that correct?
- The price was 33.
- I'm sure it was an honest mistake.
You were robbed,
as I was robbed.
That price is your security,
and you will have it, all of it.
May I rest?
I'm sorry the day has been
a disappointment for you, lord.
You have a good heart.
Gifting your silver.
Odda owes you 15 pieces more.
I'll see that he pays.
And the debt's not something
I blame you for.
It's Alfred's deceit.
I should have been wiser.
Though I was blinded by you.
You should eat.
I should eat.
But I don't want to eat alone.
God has made me your wife.
There must be a reason.
God is good.
What is it you're looking at?
There's a scar across the land there.
The never-ending line
of Danes on the march.
Ragnar.
By the time word reaches Alfred,
it would be too late.
They would need wings.
Oswald, what town
lays in that direction?
If they keep going west,
in a day or so,
they'll come
to the fortress at wareham.
Take your family and the others to
the hills till they've passed. Do it now.
- And the lady mildrith?
- She travels with me...
To Winchester.
Yes, lord.
How many do you see?
The question is,
how many will follow?
Wessex is being invaded
and we're told to wait while he prays.
God is his strength, uhtred.
He needs to be on horseback,
not on his knees.
- I hate this place.
- It grows worse.
I was not told you were here.
How pleasing.
- Lord.
- And so much of you.
Is he ready?
The king is ready, as is his council.
You watched 300 men or more
march clean across wessex
and you did nothing?
I'm here.
A messenger could have been
sent in your place.
- A boy.
- Why did you not confront these Danes?
You have men. That's your purpose,
to create warriors.
I've been given 20 men and wives,
most work the fields.
Would've been a slaughter.
But you chose not to fight.
We'll never know.
A warrior can only die once.
Why die in vain?
The Danes have travelled
from either lundene or east anglia.
Were they not being watched?
We have been watching the ships
which remain on the tames. A mistake.
If wareham is captured,
ships will follow.
Three hundred men
will become 3,000.
- My advice is we march without delay.
- I don't recall the king seeking advice.
How many Danes did you witness?
More than 200 by far.
Warriors to a man.
Wareham will struggle
to hold them back.
The peace is over.
We have no choice
but to march on wareham
and pray god we arrive
before the fortress falls.
You believe it is an invasion, lord?
It could well be the beginning
of a great Dane army, yes.
Council is over. Ealdormen of wessex,
prepare your men.
Father beocca,
I shall pray before we leave.
Yes, my lord.
Father, I wish to
speak to the king privately.
I will ask,
but I note that you
are still to learn respect.
Ealdorman odda,
if I may speak out.
You owe my wife
half of her bride-price.
I paid 33 pieces of silver.
She received only 18.
An honest mistake, she assures me.
Is this true?
Pay him.
Ready the men
to march on wareham.
You should know
mildrith is a joy to plough.
You're a heathen.
And you're a virgin.
No, I'm not.
Yes, he is.
What is it? Hm?
Promise me
you will come back safely.
Two arms, both ears.
Promise me.
Pm do my best.
But only if you do the same.
If they come, don't shelter in a church
or nunnery. Go to the hills, the woods.
I'll come.
For both of you.
Arseling.
Kiss her and let's be on our way.
http://hiqve.com/
Mildrith, my dear,
we've been looking for you.
My lady aelswith. How good to see you,
and to see you looking as you do.
It refuses to keep still.
- Mine is the same.
- Oh, how we suffer.
I pray we both survive.
I pray we four survive.
God will decide.
I've missed you, mildrith,
and I prayed for you each day.
- Poor thing.
- Why poor?
Living with the man
they foisted onto you, the pagan.
Having to take his seed and the like.
Uhtred is decent. He treats me well.
He does.
God will bless your loyalty.
But with luck,
he will fall in battle, and soon.
Please tell me that you're hungry.
- I am a little.
- Meet me in the kitchens.
I have arranged a meal
for the pregnant.
But do not rush prayers.
No. No. Of course not. Heh.
Lord, he is not your most
humble or devout servant.
But I pray...
Keep him safe.
Let him do your work.
Let him see his child.
I was pleased to see
your lady today, your wife.
And carrying a child.
It's god's blessing.
It seems like only yesterday
I was baptising you as osbert,
and then again as uhtred.
What is it you wish to speak about
with the king?
It's between myself and the king.
He's watching you, uhtred.
Watching how you behave,
judging you.
He has no right to judge.
He's a king.
He lied to me
regarding the marriage.
Are you referring to the debt?
- You know of it?
- It's not a secret.
And I urge you
to show him you accepted,
especially as it
is owed to the church.
You must remain calm, uhtred,
respectful.
My lord.
- I requested a private...
- Have you eaten?
There are times
when I crave meat...
And other things.
But I know the gratification would be
fleeting, the suffering prolonged,
and so I suffer gruel.
Though my wife will not allow it to
be called anything other than "broth."
You will be happy to learn
that my spies have news.
- From wareham?
- From Ireland.
Ivar, brother of ubba, has been killed
there, which would be irrelevant,
but for the fact ubba
wishes to avenge him personally.
This is true?
An irishman across the sea kills
a Dane, and the world changes.
The hand of god.
Is this something ubba would do?
Abandon guthrum?
To avenge his brother, yes.
If guided by his sorcerer's story.
He has a sorcerer?
And what does this sorcerer do?
Cast spells? Perform magic?
He advises, lord.
He looks for omens.
- Signs, good and bad.
- Oh, what nonsense.
What are miracles, lord,
if not magic?
Miracles are performed
by god, not man.
Danes say the same.
Omens are gifts from gods.
And they are mistaken.
Who gave the sign
for ubba to go to Ireland?
- The hand of your god or theirs?
- There's one god.
Then he must have spoken
to the Danes.
With ubba now in Ireland,
guthrum must now decide
whether he will fight alone.
He won't fight alone.
Not that he couldn't win.
He will fear losing
too many of his men.
Yes, lord.
I am learning...
That the heathen
cares only for personal gain.
A Dane could never suffer my gruel.
"Broth," lord.
You are happy, ealdorman uhtred,
with mildrith?
Yes, lord. She's a good wife.
Though I never would have married her
had I known I'd owe 2,000 shillings.
Which increases yearly.
On your word,
the debt can be lifted.
Why should I deny the church
2,000 shillings?
- I wasn't aware I'd owe it.
- It is not a secret.
Sacrifice and penance are what
separate us from the heathen.
I have my broth, you have your debt.
Wessex needs an army,
would you agree?
A permanent and formidable army.
Yes, lord.
England, when it finally emerges,
shall need a greater army.
Garrisons of many thousands of men,
all will need feeding and payment.
It is my intention that all landowners
shall contribute
to the feeding of this army
and its commanders.
And I will need commanders, uhtred.
Men like the great generals of Rome.
Look upon the debt as a gift.
A means of proving your devotion
to wessex and to england.
- If I'd been told the truth from...
- You still wear the amulet, I see.
To remind me of Earl ragnar.
Why do you not attend church with
your wife? Why do you not pray to god?
God created everything
that surrounds me.
The fields, rivers, the forests.
The land is my church.
And I pray each day, lord...
In silence.
He cannot be tamed.
But he can be trusted.
I will not abandon him completely.
He may have a use, I'm sure.
Hear me now. Wareham has fallen.
We march at once.
Every man is to be ready to do
as the king asks.
The Danes have taken the fortress.
Wareham has fallen.
We march at once.
We could be slipping in blood
and entrails before the day is out.
Leave him.
There's enough for everyone.
Guthrum, they're here.
The Saxon army is gathering.
- Is it Alfred?
- Yes.
Is the fortress repaired and secure?
Good. He will not attack.
He doesn't need to. He knows
we'll be hungry within days.
- We can raid.
- No.
He will empty all the grain stores
in the surrounding villages.
I have found these church rooms
to be strangely quiet and peaceful.
Lord, I didn't march my men halfway
across england for them to starve.
- I shall be on the ramparts.
- We came for war, ragnar.
But ubba has reneged.
- To avenge his brother.
- But you are here.
Should you not be
avenging your father?
- When the time is right.
- Yes.
When the time is right.
We have taken the first steps
against wessex.
But ubba has left us weak.
He put all of our lives at risk.
So until ubba returns,
we have to make peace.
So if you are there...
Strike me down.
I thought not.
We are here to show them
how many we are.
how many we are!
That we are here with god.
And that this is our land.
That we are here with god!
And this is our land!
This is our land!
Our wessex!
This is our england!
And we shall murder any
heathen bastard that tries to take it!
- They wish to talk, lord.
- I know what they want.
They want time.
Odda, with your guards, you shall
go with me. Leofric, you as well.
- And father selbix.
- Yes, lord.
What do you make of the fortress?
It looks strong enough, lord.
No breach.
No signs of lasting damage.
And if we attacked?
We would suffer.
We'd be lucky
to see the inside, lord.
Good morning, king Alfred.
Guthrum of the Danes.
I, too, am a king now,
of east anglia.
You don't need to bow.
I will begin.
I propose a truce.
For any truce to occur, Earl guthrum,
you must leave wessex once again.
- And if I refuse?
- We surround you.
Yes, you surround a small fortress,
but we Danes surround
your entire kingdom. That said,
I've decided I shall leave by sea.
Therefore, I will send for ships.
- How many ships?
- No more than 15.
Very well.
Your ships have one month to arrive.
- Not enough time.
- Food and ale for one month only,
or you will walk back to east anglia.
Then I'll send for 200 ships
and hope they arrive before we starve.
- One month is not enough.
- That is my limit.
You cannot take back the fortress.
You know this.
Food and ale for one month,
no more.
By which time,
the sea storms will have arrived.
- God's storms.
- We will be gone within a month,
beginning upon
the delivery of food and ale.
Uhtred, you will come to me
following prayers.
- Yes, lord.
- Father selbix, you will pray with me.
Yes, lord.
Please sit.
Thank you, lord.
I have a task for you, father.
You only have to speak it.
As a guarantee of the peace, you will
be given up as a hostage, one of ten.
The Danes, too,
will give ten in exchange.
Lord, the pagans
do not value priests.
You might just as well offer a hound.
I hear guthrum is curious
about our faith.
I would like you
to become his teacher.
Provide instruction.
And if he refuses to be a student?
Then persist.
Gently with humour,
as is your manner.
Make no mistake...
Should guthrum
ever consent to being baptised,
then this war is over.
England is ours.
This would be
truly god's work you do.
Forgive me, lord,
but I cannot help but feel afraid.
They are not content
to simply kill a priest.
Fear is within all of us.
As is strength.
Lord, I'd be more useful as a warrior
for when the truce fails.
Oh, the truce will hold for a time.
And in that time, you will be
my eyes and ears inside the fortress.
- Listening for what?
- For ubba.
If and when you hear of his return,
you will escape.
- And if I'm in chains?
- Our men shall disband.
There are fields to work.
I'll build a beacon on the hill.
You'll escape and light the fire.
Lord, you know that escape
will be near impossible.
If ubba returns, the hostages
will be killed and the Danes will attack.
Upon sight of this beacon being lit,
other fires will start.
Wessex will be called to arms.
- If I refuse to become a hostage?
- Another man shall light the beacon.
Why can't you accept me?
I've been nothing but truthful.
Why am I always put to the test?
Why do you not show your king
respect that is due?
Because you, uhtred of wherever,
you do not see me as your king.
You do not see my god as your god.
- My lord?
- I am not finished with you yet.
Guthrum is waiting to hear
of ubba's return from Ireland.
I need to know when this occurs,
sooner rather than later. You...
Are the only man who could possibly
provide this information sooner.
Yes, it is possible that you will die,
but it is likely that we shall all die.
You will go to the Danes.
How you go, as a Saxon hostage
or as a viking warrior,
becomes your choice.
I'll do as you ask.
But if my child is born while
I'm captive, I ask that you send word.
Of course.
And should you die as a captive, rest
assured, your debt shall die with you.
Will they treat us well?
You are one of them.
If I am one of them,
then why am I a hostage?
They'll treat us well
for as long as the truce holds.
- If it fails?
- They'll kill us all,
starting with the priest. Heh!
I've made my peace. I am ready.
Good evening and god bless you all.
Poor wretches.
And us, father, what are we?
We are fortunate, lord.
We know god.
Although granted,
I'm in no hurry to meet him.
Let us pray he feels the same.
Amen.
Is this rabble
what so many are afraid of?
Come. They're like children.
Enough. Enough!
They are our guests for a while.
There's one rule only.
At nightfall,
you will gather and sleep
at the church.
The doors will be barred.
At daybreak, you will then be free to
walk, talk, jump, hump, carry weapons.
My men have orders not to kill you...
Unless you deserve to be killed.
I am guthrum.
And one day, I shall be your king.
Do you understand
what I have said?
You will all say, "yes, lord."
Yes, lord.
I did not hear you.
I understand you, lord.
Maybe I will make
a present of you to ubba.
- Should he ever return from Ireland.
- He may not. That's possible.
But then his men
will become my men,
and I will honour him
by killing you myself.
With arrows, perhaps.
- Ragnar ragnarson.
- Here.
You know this one well.
Keep him out of my sight.
Take them to the church. Feed them.
Now you are where you belong.
Now I'm with my brother.
I will remind you what it is like
to be a Dane and make you stay.
Brida's here.
I dream about you, Vixen.
I'm not surprised to hear it.
You've grown up. Heh, heh.
You should know I'm with ragnar now.
He's my man.
That's good.
You should know that I am married.
Married?
- You have grown up.
- He's married?
Yes, he is married.
Time is moving
quicker than I thought.
Tonight, we get drunk.
We must.
- I need to be inside the church.
- No, tonight we get drunk.
I'll take you to the church myself.
Or we sleep where we fall, ha, ha.
And, uh...
We must talk of the future.
We are oarsmen!
Uhtred, pull for me. Aah!
- I need to piss. I'll return.
- He'll return.
Ragnar? Ragnar?
I haven't laughed so much
in a long time.
Then you haven't been living.
Or as ravn would say,
"tomorrow we die."
When did he ever say that?
When you were out chopping wood.
Well, I actually do need to piss.
Ha, ha, what you need to do
is to stop drinking.
Tomorrow we die.
- He's happy to see you.
- I've missed him.
I miss you both.
Are you his wife?
I'm with him.
- Is she beautiful?
- Mm.
Her name's mildrith.
Yes, she is beautiful.
She carries my child.
Who decided you should marry?
Alfred.
I have the land I asked for
in wessex.
You swear an oath to Alfred.
You marry for Alfred.
You have land given to you by Alfred.
Your wife carries your child.
And yet you're given up
as a hostage by Alfred?
Are you a spy, uhtred?
At the first sign of ubba returning,
I am to escape.
But I know that when ubba returns,
the hostages will be killed.
Alfred's not fond of me.
Refuse him.
Refuse to be a hostage. Join us.
I should ask you, uhtred.
Not that it matters, but I should ask.
Is it a problem to you
that brida's with me now?
Ha, ha, no. I'm happy about it.
- I swear.
- All right.
Not that she cares what you think.
I would hump her regardless.
But...
With... with affection.
- And with my permission.
- I know.
Do you know
uhtred's to be a father?
- When?
- Soon, I'm told.
You would want to see it?
Yes. I hope to return
to my wife and child.
Ragnar.
I'll be with you to avenge our father.
Kjartan will pay.
You should have joined me
months ago with brida.
I'd sworn an oath.
To a poxy Saxon king.
Ubba wanted me dead.
There was nowhere else to go.
I've thought about
that night in the woods.
- You had a choice to be Saxon or Dane.
- No, I had sworn an oath.
You should have joined me.
I'll be with you to kill kjartan.
I will take you to the church,
to your bed.
- What is it?
- It's a son, lady.
A handsome boy.
You will be uhtred, son of uhtred.
Good morning, uhtred.
Good morning, father.
Raining again.
One day seems like the next.
It does.
Still, at least we're alive to feel it.
How are your conversations
with guthrum?
Is he a Christian yet?
I believe the time is near, I do.
I often leave him
to contemplate alone in church.
Guthrum likes to contemplate
war and kingdoms.
The kingdom of heaven
is his to share.
I've told him.
A man can change, uhtred.
Onward. God bless you.
May you enjoy a good day.
Thank you, father.
He is the king of kings.
Capable of great, great things.
Such as what?
Such as miracles.
Miracles?
Such as what?
Such as you, lord.
You are a miracle.
He has made you
strong yet merciful.
He has...
Made you proud yet humble.
He has made you eager to learn.
He has given you free will,
hoping that you will find the courage
to choose him above all else.
And I believe, I truly believe,
he will be rewarded.
- I have a message for guthrum.
- He's in the church.
- Lord, may I speak?
- Freely.
Ubba and his army
have returned from Ireland.
They are coming ashore
north of here at the severn.
And my fleet is where?
They left lundene several days ago
and are nearly here.
Every last ship will be here.
Every man will be with you.
That is good news.
I dispatch you to your heaven.
No need to thank me.
Father.
Ubba has returned?
Did they say?
Men, the peace is over.
Prepare for battle.
The Saxon hostages, kill them all.
- Catch him!
- Get him.
Cut him to pieces!
Kill him!
Leave him.
I say leave him!
Ragnar.
Please step aside.
You know all of the hostages
have to die.
Then kill him.
You're welcome to kill him.
But you have to kill me first.
I could happily manage without this.
He's a Saxon. He's a traitor.
He's an enemy.
Well, to get to him,
you have to kill me.
My men, they will not follow you.
I will give you one last charity.
Release him without a horse.
Are you all right?
I have no words.
You should go.
Go and see your child. Go.
Yes.
I'll be with you.
Both of you.
http://hiqve.com/