I am uhtred, son of uhtred.
Brida told me of my brother's murder.
Ragnar is dead!
He doesn't feast in Valhalla!
Instead, he lies under a pile of stones
at the lake near loidis!
He died
because I remain cursed by skade.
Death comes to us all.
It is her!
To help him cross the bridge
from he/ to Valhalla,
I must first be rid of her.
To fight haesten's army,
you will need an army.
My father is to join the mercians
at aege/esburg.
So with aethe/flaed, I journeyed
to king Alfred, to plead for help.
One thousand men,
and I will give you beamfleot.
I do not need beamfleot.
When Alfred denied me, his son,
the aethe/ing, Edward, promised soldiers.
Set a day for the attack,
and I will be there.
You shall have the men.
With that assurance,
I drew haesten onto the battlefield...
- Run!
- And into our trap,
where we expected the king and his men,
who lay in wait, to strike.
We wait.
Lord, where is Alfred's army?
They're being slaughtered!
We hold our position.
We cannot just stand by
and watch them die!
- I gave him my word!
- Then what will you do, boy?
You can either bleat
or you can make a decision!
What will you do?
Destiny is all!
Lord king, we cannot wait any longer.
Lord king!
Father! We cannot wait! We cannot.
For wessex! And for the king!
For the king!
Charge!
Edward! It's Edward and his army!
Stand! Every man is to stand!
Dagfinn! Every man is to stand!
It's Alfred. He lives.
Stand!
Every man is to stand!
Come on!
Stand!
She's why we are here, lord! Take her!
Down!
Lord!
It's osferth.
Osferth?
He's alive, lord.
Maybe next time we'll be lucky, eh?
Did you see me fighting, lord?
I did. It was a sight to behold.
Though I hope I killed no man.
You gave many a sore head.
I feel cold.
Because it's winter, you fool.
You were a warrior today, osferth.
Am I to die, lord? I do not fear it.
I forbid it.
You dare die, baby monk,
and I'll kill you myself.
Right, I'll try not to, then.
We will return to aethelflaed's estate,
and you will rest and recover there.
Yes, lord.
What of skade?
She's been taken by haesten.
Then nothing has changed.
We remain cursed still.
I am cursed.
It touches us all, lord.
Itconfinues.
Uhtred, lord. As you ordered.
Thank you, steapa.
I assume your vengeance
included reclaiming the seer, skade?
She is why you are here?
Instead, I returned your fortress, lord.
The victory was decisive.
You have my thanks.
I feared you would not join the battle.
I was tempted to delay the charge
a little longer.
I would have seen victory without you,
and it would have been all you deserved.
It was Edward who ordered the attack.
It needed to be Edward.
You owe him your thanks.
He fought with courage.
If I were his father, I would be proud.
When I spoke with skade, she foretold
I should not live to see another summer.
Skade preys on men's fears, lord.
Nevertheless, I know it to be true.
I know how my body weakens daily.
In a matter of months, weeks even,
I shall be gone and Edward shall be king.
He has proven himself.
He has proven that he has courage.
But also that he can be manipulated.
You used him to serve your own purpose.
No, lord, he saw a way to weaken an enemy.
The Danes' march has been halted.
They will not attack this winter.
You do your son a disservice,
all to accuse me of manipulation!
For one reason or another, you have,
it seems, earned Edward's favour.
He kept his word.
Yes.
All that I ask is that you
do not forget what he has done.
Oh, I will not forget.
Nor will I forget that his father has
taken from me everything that was mine.
You are free to go anywhere but wessex.
Bebbanburg, should you choose.
But those lands are as distant as ever.
As is england, lord.
The Danes will never leave these shores.
Never.
I will go
to the lady aethelflaed's estate.
She remains in danger, I believe.
Lord king.
Fetch me cnut. He needs to see this.
Haesten looks a broken man.
He looks like shit. He brings my woman.
- Lord haesten, my friend.
- Cnut.
You will point your cock
somewhere else, bloodhair.
The woman is mine, make no mistake.
What has happened?
I have lost everything,
bar what you see.
You have lost more than half your men.
And my man, dagfinn.
- How?
- Alfred lives, that is how.
They came at night in their thousands.
- He lives?
- And uhtred is with him.
Who says Alfred lives?
I say. I saw him on horseback,
as strong as he has ever been.
That is a nonsense, it must be.
He lives!
And half my men do not!
If uhtred is with Alfred,
then it is over before it has begun.
Nothing is over. Nothing is over!
We are strong still!
How did you come by skade?
Skade is not important!
Haesten spared uhtred.
You will shut your mouth!
It's true.
We do not care!
He could have easily killed
both uhtred and the Princess,
but instead he desired me.
He thinks with his cock.
You find that amusing, bloodhair?
I've missed her sharp tongue.
She is mine. I will lose nothing more!
We are meant to be one army!
Haesten, rest. Then the three of us shall
sit and decide how we are to proceed.
A war council.
You mean the four of us?
Aethelwold, another word from you
and I shall take your head.
Very well.
Not another word.
You have no appetite?
No appetite for celebration.
What is it you are holding?
Thor's hammer.
Yes.
From ragnar the fearless.
I have told you?
Once or twice.
They will be together now...
Father and son, in Valhalla.
That is what you believe, isn't it?
I must go to him. My men will remain here.
Uhtred, I know what you have sacrificed
to come to my aid.
I know how much it has cost you.
It was my choice, lady,
it is what I wanted to do.
I would like you to have mercia
as your home, to live here with your men.
I can identify land...
Thank you, lady,
but say nothing more. Please.
Where are the prisoners being taken?
To the hall, to be fed upon my orders.
Come join us, lady aethelflaed.
Hold your tongue, dagfinn,
or I will cut it out!
I do not like my enemies within my walls.
I will leave you to your peace.
How's osferth?
Sleeping. As we should all be.
Just as soon as he's recovered,
we should attempt to recover skade.
Once again.
So long as she is free, lord,
you are cursed.
Skade is with the Danes.
We cannot reach her.
We will not chase her to our deaths.
Death will find us regardless.
Do you have something to say, sihtric?
He does not.
Except that enough of us
have died already.
You are a warrior.
Death is a hazard.
I've decided to go to ragnar.
I must help him find peace.
All you will find at ragnar's graveside
is ghosts.
You will keep watch of aethelflaed,
and you will rest.
No man who serves uhtred can rest,
not until skade is reclaimed.
Sihtric, you are drunk
and you are tired.
Yes, I am tired...
Of marching north and then south,
of being called a traitor,
of abandoning my wife!
For what?
Then leave, boy!
Uhtred, you do not mean that.
If you are unhappy in my service, leave!
I have fought for you!
You fight because you enjoy it!
And you would dismiss me as easy as this!
Stay or go, I do not care!
He does not mean that.
He does care. Now, let us all sit.
Stay or go, sihtric kjartanson,
it is your choice. Make it!
If you wish to make the square,
uhtred of bebbanburg, let us do it.
No, there'll be no squares made,
no fighting, just sleep!
Sleep!
Jesus!
Get the prisoners
back with the pigs, bound!
Sihtric!
I will leave first light.
But I will return.
And if you are here still...
Then I will kill you.
Why?
He has cursed us all!
She has cursed you all,
and uhtred allows it!
Shut your mouth.
Abandon him, boy, it's your only chance!
You're a Dane first and last!
Quiet!
You abandoned your fortress,
and your men abandoned you.
Some.
You fell into Alfred's trap.
I was told that Alfred was dead.
By your messenger.
The trap would have been uhtred's.
Alfred brought his armies to beamfleot
because that is what uhtred
had asked him to do.
Alfred will die soon enough,
but it is uhtred we want dead.
He should have died at dunholm,
but ragnar was weak.
If we are to make wessex ours,
we must rid it of its talisman.
Uhtred of bebbanburg must die.
The days are short.
We've been weakened
and ragnar's death is an omen.
Wessex must wait.
Aethelwold. You will return to Winchester.
I cannot. I will not.
For what reason?
You have long promised us a Saxon army.
It's time to deliver that army.
Once Alfred is dead, yes.
Aethelred of mercia is ripe for betrayal,
as are many men of wessex,
but as a corpse, I can do nothing!
Alfred would kill me!
You will ask for forgiveness.
- And I would be ignored.
- Then you will beg!
You will deliver me a Saxon army,
and if uhtred has joined Alfred
at Winchester, you will kill him.
I will kill him, how?
As you killed ragnar.
Lord...
He wouldn't have the balls.
Lord cnut,
you must learn to hold your tongue.
This fool killed ragnar?
Cnut is joking with you.
While he slept.
He was not sleeping.
It was either he died or I died.
I am no fool.
This fact goes no further than this table.
Are you part of this?
I'm no longer concerned by his death.
You wish to lead?
Ragnar should never have allowed
uhtred to live.
He should never have allowed him
to leave with your woman.
Who is now my woman.
Who will take ragnar's men?
Ragnar's men belong to brida.
They merely await her return.
Aethelwold, you will leave tomorrow.
So I am journeying to wessex
to become a corpse,
and from my grave, I am to raise an army
and kill the greatest warrior in the land.
Mmm.
Ale, lord?
Always.
And thank you for reminding me
I am a lord, offa,
my faithful servant.
You and I are to make a journey.
I shall return to Winchester,
whereas you will travel
from peasant to lord.
I do not understand.
Of course you don't, you're stupid.
As I have been stupid.
However, complete this next task,
and your reward
will be land and title, ealdorman offa.
I will get you out of here.
But you will take me to your camp.
You're no longer sworn to uhtred, boy?
Uhtred is cursed and has lost his mind.
I am at the mercy of gods,
and this is their will.
Are you with me or not?
http://hiqve.com/
I knew you would come.
He calls to me in my dreams.
From niflheim.
Asking me to help him cross
from he! Into Valhalla.
If there is one thing I could do,
it would be that.
You're here because you want forgiveness.
You abandoned him three times over.
That was through fate, not choice.
What are you doing? We will freeze.
Niflheim is much colder
than you will ever be.
If ragnar suffers, then so shall we.
There will be no comfort for you here.
I'm going to sleep.
Wrapped in fur?
Give me your strength,
your heart and your wisdom.
Give me your love, brother.
You shall always have mine.
Edward.
You look very clean today,
apart from this Mark here.
Mother, please.
- She teases you.
- Stop.
Lord, I do not mean to disturb.
There was a matter
I thought we might discuss.
Speak your mind, Edward.
The king appreciates honesty.
I do not regret what was done,
giving my word to uhtred,
honouring my word
and the battle that followed,
the victory.
But I... acknowledge
I went beyond what is my right.
I went against you, even.
I shall accept any punishment
you think necessary.
Without my permission,
you swore my men to a traitor.
You led my armies
into a battle I did not sanction.
Your actions
were not worthy of an aetheling.
They were worthy of a king.
Wessex shall soon be yours.
For now, it is strong.
But england remains fragile.
Its future will not only be secured
with battles and with men,
but with unions.
We should like you
to meet the lady aelflaed.
It is time.
It is a match that will strengthen
wessex and the crown.
Your crown.
I will do my utmost, lord,
for wessex and for my king.
[Qasdsi
hmm.
Do you know them?
They look like Danes.
Yes, but do you know them?
We should leave. We can eat later.
And go where?
To a shithole village
on the road to legaceaster.
I do not know how we can help
ragnar escape niflheim,
but I will not return to my own life
until I've tried.
What is at this village?
A seer.
Do you remember storri?
- Storri is a piece of shit.
- He is.
But he was ubba's seer,
a sword Dane's seer.
If any man will know
how to reach a lost warrior, it is him.
They have gone.
We can be at the village in two days.
Yeah.
One more arrow,
and I will take your eyes!
I know who sent you!
You do?
Tell cnut I will return when I'm ready!
Cnut will want the Dane-slayer dead.
He's with me! He has my protection!
His head will be worth
its weight in silver.
I have a very small head!
Come out!
Uhtred is mine to kill, when I'm ready.
Now, go, while you still have your balls.
Cnut will hear
that you are protecting him.
Tell cnut I will return,
and when I do, he will have my men.
He will know what that means.
Now, go.
You do not change, woman.
I spared you for ragnar.
I am told that uhtred
has ridden north to ragnar's grave.
Alone or with his men?
Alone. His men remain with aethelflaed.
I see.
He is a man in great need
of the guidance of god.
Lord, I could place uhtred
in the waters a thousand times,
and he would not find god, only fish.
My son will need him.
It pains me greatly to say it,
but it is true.
Edward will need uhtred.
But he is an outlaw.
He must remain an outlaw until I am gone.
That is your wish, lord?
That is what I wish,
but I can say it only to you.
It cannot become a command.
My wife is sure to oppose any bond
between Edward and uhtred.
But Edward must make his own decision,
with your counsel, father beocca.
Yes, lord.
You plan to give your men to cnut?
They're my men.
Will you become cnut's woman?
It's none of your business.
Will you?
I must survive. Men won't follow a woman
for long, they're too stupid.
But cnut? He's a weasel.
Well, what do you suggest?
That I give my men to you
to attack bebbanburg?
Because that's something
you will never do, because you're a Saxon.
He's a weasel.
You deserve better than cnut,
is what I'm saying.
It's your turn to shit!
I do not need to shit.
Then let's go and find this turd, storri.
This is the second time
we have gone in search of storri.
The last time, you despatched him
with a stick up his arse.
I remember. Never forgotten.
We were so young then.
We were Danes then.
Race you over the hill?
Why?
Why not?
Child.
Afraid of losing?
I think of gisela every morning I wake
and every night before I sleep.
I understand.
I should despise ragnar for whoring...
But I can't.
You loved him.
More than he knew.
The thought of him in he!
Is not one I can bear.
I swear I will not leave your side
until we have found a way to help him.
Or until you have killed me.
Then we must find a way quickly,
because I'm sure to kill you soon.
I can't forgive you, uhtred...
For failing him.
- One time.
- Three times.
Once.
I made one mistake.
I gave one year's service to Alfred.
You gave your life.
I swore an oath to Alfred
for a second time because I had no choice.
A man always has a choice.
After the battle of ethandun,
when ragnar became Alfred's hostage,
he was sent north by Alfred
to free me from my slavers.
I was there.
Ragnar saved me...
And then we rode to save gisela.
Whereupon I killed a priest.
Good.
And because ragnar did not prevent it,
because I was in ragnar's charge,
Alfred did blame ragnar.
He was going to have him put on trial
and then killed.
The options given to me
were to swear a second oath to Alfred
or my brother's life.
You didn't tell ragnar?
From ragnar...
And from me.
I have always loved you.
Not as a wife.
No longer as a wife.
But you will always be
half my life.
And all of your madness, is what you said.
It's true.
This is it? This is where we find storri?
- I see him.
- Huh?
The gods are with us.
And this is from your wife?
What is it?
It's bad.
The ale?
Your wife, she will bear many children.
But none shall be born living.
I'm sorry, the gods can be cruel.
There must be something you can do.
I suggest you find a new wife.
I despise him.
We need him.
[Qasdsi
come no closer!
I have skill!
Storri, you have chickens,
a goat and a bad smell.
That is all.
Uhtred ragnarson.
And you, I know you too. Oh, I remember.
All we want is your knowledge.
In exchange for your life.
She shamed me.
You shamed me with a branch!
I shat blood for days!
Storri! We will pay.
We will not!
We mean you no harm, and we will pay.
She is to come nowhere near my arse.
You understand?
You swear it!
She will come nowhere near your arse.
I liked young ragnar
and his father, the fearless.
For him to be lost
in the cold of niflheim,
no true warrior deserves such a fate.
Then you will help us?
I would like to, but that would mean
walking with the gods,
asking for a solution,
perhaps time and time again.
And each time would require payment.
We are not here to be robbed.
You are here to save young ragnar.
Right?
You will give us the answer tonight.
Or you will die tonight.
Is she allowed to speak to me like that?
Help us, and you will be paid,
but it must be tonight.
Well, then,
you should allow me to prepare.
You are in luck, though.
I have everything I need and young ragnar
will share in that good luck.
We need to kill a chicken.
But not the small one, she has a name.
What is she called?
I wouldn't be surprised if he humps it.
Storri?
Uhtred?
He's gone. He's gone!
I swear I did not mean to run, just habit.
My curse. I'm assuming it worked.
It did.
It cost me a family and my husband.
I... I can make amends,
I can help you reach ragnar.
I liked him.
Please don't kill me.
Don't let her kill me.
I can see she'd like to.
- He says he can help us.
- I heard.
You might think I'm afraid of death.
I'm not.
I think there are times
I would even welcome it.
Almost finished.
What is it you are using?
I thought to walk with the gods
you needed mushrooms?
Oh, yes, mushrooms are vital.
This is a mixture for something else.
What?
This is to help me...
Shit.
You are playing with us.
Ugh!
Perhaps I am.
And perhaps this was poison
to help me end my life.
I am playing with you.
But it does help me shit.
You will tell us how to help ragnar
or I swear I will cut you cook to throat.
I know exactly how to help him.
Then say it!
And nothing more!
Very well!
The goddess hel...
Will surrender your brother's soul,
but only in return for another's.
You must kill the man who killed ragnar,
the man who denied him.
You will wet the blade
with the blood of ragnar,
and with that blade only,
must you kill the man who sent him to hel.
Only that way, will he be free
to enter the feast halls of Valhalla.
Ragnar is dead, his blood is black,
it's dust almost.
Might his blood be in others?
Thyra.
Who's thyra?
Ragnar's sister, blood sister.
Then, you have it.
Now, pay me well and leave me in peace.
Thank you.
I have one more thing to ask.
I will pay.
Ask.
How do you kill a curse?
I knew it.
I saw the darkness on your shoulder.
It's yours.
Do you have something for me,
uhtred?
Brida, no!
Yes! Trust me!
Don't touch him, don't touch him!
Trust me, don't do anything!
Don't!
Bnda?
I just did what one has to do
to break a curse.
You have to kill the sorcerer
without breaking the skin
and without shedding one drop of blood.
And you've got to do the same to skade.
Or if you can't,
you can make her your woman.
He cursed you when?
Along time ago, we were young.
He threw a curse, I stuck a branch
up his arse. It was that day.
I've been a barren bitch ever since.
You have lifted your own curse.
Yes. For what it's worth.
Why not sooner?
Because I was a warrior first.
Because I'm a fool.
You are no fool.
But you are the bravest warrior.
I've known how to kill a curse
since before you arrived at dunholm.
I chose not to tell you,
because I knew you wouldn't stay.
So I wanted to see you suffer.
I did love you, uhtred,
but that has passed.
I do not believe you.
We are one, you and I.
From the moment I took your hand on
the steps of the great hall of eoferwic,
we were bound as one.
You may dislike me. Hate me if you wish,
despise me at times.
But love is immortal.
It goes on.
I will find skade,
and I must kill this curse.
Then I will go to thyra.
I will discover who killed ragnar.
And we send him on his way to Valhalla?
At some point,
I will see you on the battlefield.
I won't hesitate to kill you.
That does not mean you do not love me.
http://hiqve.com/