I am uhtred, son of uhtred.
I am a Dane for life.
I have stolen the mystic woman, skade,
from the Danish warrior Earl sigurd.
She's mine, if I have to kill you,
then that is what I will do.
King Alfred
seeks to protect his legacy,
but his son, Edward,
refuses an arranged marriage.
I am married to ecgwynn!
Your wife will be dealt with.
And his daughter,
the lady of mercia,
has fled to a nunneiy for safety.
I have not forgotten what the bitch did.
I will never forget!
I rescued her in the past.
And now she needs me again.
The Danes have formed one army
under my brother ragnar.
They plan to march south on wessex,
leaving me with an impossible choice.
Do you stand with us?
I am needed.
You are a whore to the crown of Alfred.
He does not leave with skade.
Ragnar, she belongs to me.
Yes, bloodhair, you can fight
for the witch... to the death.
Agreed, we fight.
Destiny is all!
- Kill him! Kill him!
- Come on, lord, that's it!
Kill him!
- Come on!
- Kill him!
Finish him!
Get up, Dane-slayer!
You dirty bastards, you!
Come on! Get his shield!
Right, if you want to play that game!
You are happy with this, ragnar?
You believe this to be a fair fight?
It's a fight!
It's all he deserves. Kill him!
Take his balls!
Kill him!
Kill him, go on!
Take the legs off him, lord!
Kill him!
Uhtred! Lord! Here!
His shoulder!
Yes, lord!
It's over!
No! It's not over until he's dead!
I say it is over.
I demand my woman!
I will not lose one single man
before the true battle has even begun!
It was to the death!
If you disagree with me, Saxon,
then fight me!
Kill him, ragnar, and be done with it!
It is over! It is done.
Take what belongs to you. Take your witch.
She belongs to me!
I shall see you across the battlefield.
Have no doubt, I will kill you.
Leave while you are still alive.
Alfred needs his arse to be wiped!
Enjoy your prize.
You ride with me now.
Skade! He must remain cursed!
It's your duty!
He has defeated you twice over!
I belong to uhtred now!
Never! I've tasted your blood!
What you see is mine!
Ragnar, he cannot be allowed to leave.
Didn't mean to miss! Next time, I won't!
The gates. Now. Let us be rid of them.
Earl ragnar, lord cnut.
Can one of you, both of you, tell me
why we have allowed uhtred to leave?
We are gifting Alfred his best warrior.
What is it that you suggest that we do?
I suggest we kill him.
We can still kill him, kill all of them,
apart from your sister, of course.
But we cannot allow uhtred the Dane-slayer
to return to wessex and slay more Danes.
What is your worth?
It was you who helped create these events.
Give me one reason not to kill you.
I am the reason we are gathered here.
His worth is that he can drip poison
into the ears of saxons.
Exactly.
Ragnar! Enough!
Ragnar! That's enough!
You drip poison into every ear!
You smear everything around you with shit!
It's uhtred you're angry with.
He has caused this division!
Ignore this piece-of—weasel shit...
And remember we have a task ahead.
Cousin, you are our leader now.
I am hungry for blood and battle!
Nothing has changed! We've lost a handful
of men and nothing more than that!
Nothing has changed.
We march as soon as we're ready!
Get up.
He took me by surprise.
Otherwise, I would have made a contest.
You were right to speak out.
He should never have been
allowed to leave.
That was...
Weak of my cousin.
Uhtred! Uhtred!
This is where we must leave you.
There's a ship waiting at eoferwic.
Alfred will be wondering where we are.
Alfred will know exactly where you are.
Yes. That is most likely.
Do not get yourself killed...
Until aethelflaed is safe.
That would be unfortunate.
It would.
And I would have had a wasted journey.
Aethelflaed is important to the king
and to all saxons.
After she is safe, what then?
Fate will decide.
Uhtred, you are my brother,
and you shall always be my brother.
Haesten...
Only you may enter the palace.
You must give up your weapons.
- Earl haesten.
- Lord king.
It is a considerable journey
you have made.
A necessaryjourney.
Is your wife with you?
I would like to hear of her faith.
Sadly not, lady.
Pity.
Ale, lord?
I know you.
You're the warrior priest.
I am just a priest. Father pyrlig.
You have been to the north,
haesten.
I have, lord, to dunholm.
I journeyed there with bloodhair,
who remains with ragnar,
alongside uhtred and aethelwold.
Aethelwold is there?
He is.
No doubt spreading rumour.
They are building an army, I assume.
They are.
The plan is to march
before deepest winter makes it impossible.
They will march from north to south
as a single army.
The further south they come,
the greater they will grow.
They will attract warriors.
Hmm, that is true.
If it were my place to advise you, lord,
I would suggest
you march out to meet them.
Thank you, haesten.
Your loyalty to our agreement
will not go unrewarded.
Thank you, lord. Lady.
Despite aethelwold's obsessive insolence,
I did never believe he could turn wholly
against his father and his homeland.
And his king.
It can only mean death.
Yes.
Alfred will be thinking of battle
for the weeks to come.
I want the lady of mercia found quickly.
Father pyrlig?
Lord?
You will draught and deliver a letter
to my son-in-law, aethelred.
You will recount the warning
of an army marching from the north
and you will inform him that together
we shall face this army...
At mercia's most favourable point.
- This is to happen when, lord?
- Immediately.
We cannot wait.
We shall confront them
and we shall defeat them.
In the name of god
and the england yet to be.
Yes, lord.
The king speaks and acts
with authority, as always.
The king fears his strength
shall fail him all too soon.
Never.
God is great.
As is Alfred. That is how
you will be remembered.
It is time!
I will make no proclamations,
except everything is possible!
I will say nothing more than it is time
we change these lands forever!
It is time to begin a story
that will be told
amongst the living
and by those in Valhalla forever more.
It will be our song... and our story!
Let it begin.
Let's move out.
My lady is asking
if you've had enough to eat?
I have told her yes, because the poor nuns
have been in the kitchen the whole day.
How about a drop more ale, for the night?
Godric, you have a job to do
and you will need to be awake to do it.
Abbess, may I ask,
how strong must a woman be
to live like this for all of her life?
Strong?
Yes. To deny yourself
a life outside of these walls.
Lady, we wish to live like this,
in the service of god.
I do not regret one day of my time here.
Abbess! Abbess,
there are men in the kitchen. Danes.
Close the doors,
move the table against them. Quickly!
- Why have your guards not dealt with it?
- They will.
Just as soon as they become
aware of the danger.
We should call to them.
No. No, if it is thieves,
they may come and go.
This is god's house!
You will leave us this very moment!
If you do not and you are Christian,
then he will send you
to the depths of hell!
Abbess, they are Danes.
Well, then, if you are heathen,
he will strike you down!
And what if I am a Christian by birth
and a Dane by my heart? What then?
Uhtred.
You know this man?
Yes. Yes, I do.
Your guards are not, lady.
Not what?
They are not guards.
Their swords are trinkets.
- It's true.
- They are good men.
I'm sure they're loyal,
but they are not guards.
They are barely men.
I do not like you, young man.
You have a very high opinion of yourself.
I am heathen, I am godless
and an enemy of Alfred,
but what I will do is keep you alive.
And who is it that wishes me dead?
Several people, I imagine.
What uhtred is saying,
is that the lands are changing.
Men are becoming sick with greed,
and we must all be on our guard.
Well, perhaps.
But I know when I'm hearing half-truths.
I do not like him.
Ugh, I like her even less.
Nor I you, hag.
She reminds me of my mother,
and that woman was never wrong either.
Cnut!
Yes, ragnar?
Tomorrow, I want men sent on ahead.
They are to watch for Alfred's army.
So soon?
He is no fool. He will not wait
for us to knock on his door.
He will want to choose the place of battle
and we cannot allow him that advantage.
We each volunteer a man,
you, me and bloodhair.
Yes, lord.
Will you speak to bloodhair or shall I?
You.
Ragnar belittles you.
He is ploughing a new field in the hope
of sowing the seed of another son.
If you wish to sit with me,
you will respect me.
Oh, I respect you very much.
Though I do not wish to sit with you,
brida. I wish to lie with you.
You should go while
you still have a tongue in your head.
I like that you are proud
and strong and loyal...
And I will go now.
Bloodhair.
A private moment, lord sigurd?
Ragnar requests that we each send
a spy on ahead, to watch for Alfred.
- That is fair.
- It is.
What was not fair was ragnar's decision
to allow your fight
with uhtred to proceed.
That was an insult.
Skade is yours.
- Ragnar is your cousin.
- But this is war.
Would I trust my sister in command
of my men just because she is my sister?
Our spies should also act as messengers.
They should carry word of our intentions.
Men will join us, you and me, good men.
We should grow our armies together.
Do you agree?
I do not disagree.
Then...
That is enough.
I hoped you would come.
I have released you from your oath,
you do know that?
Beocca did say.
And still you are here.
I was broken to hear of gisela's death.
Your father allowed her
to be called a whore.
I'm sorry for that.
It was not your doing.
The woman is still with you I see. Skade.
She is my curse. My problem to resolve.
She is no longer a prisoner?
She will not stray.
You are carrying so much pain.
Do not give your trust to a person
who does not deserve it...
Regardless of her guile and beauty.
You are speaking of skade still?
It is not my business to ask,
but do you lie with her?
I do not.
She has a darkness.
My immediate concern is your safety.
You must return to wessex, to your father.
I can't. I am of mercia now...
Aethelflaed, you must.
Aethelred will soon know
that you are close.
The real danger you will face
is from the Danes.
They are marching as we speak,
a great army.
Haesten is with them.
He has not forgotten you,
and I cannot protect you forever.
I will not fight against the Danes.
Alfred must protect you now...
You are here, and I am glad of it.
Soon I shall travel to my estate, and I
shall face both my husband and the Danes.
Ishahfight
I must.
As my father must, he too shall march.
Aethelflaed...
If you will excuse me, I promised
the abbess I would pray with her.
There is much to pray for.
There should be no doubts in your mind,
lord.
Once you have fulfilled
your promise to the Princess,
you must return to your own path,
to the Danes.
- And they would have me?
- They would need you, uhtred ragnarson.
If that is who you are,
then you must return and you must lead.
And you will need skade, the seer,
to help you lead.
It is not a seat I want.
I have made my choice, uhtred,
now you must do the same.
Make your life your own once more.
Turn away from me
and you and those you love
shall be tormented 'til death and beyond.
Lord aethelhelm has arrived.
A good choice, I feel.
Yes.
He has quite a gathering with him.
Oh, he likes to show his feathers,
but he has money and men,
both of which I will need.
A perfect choice.
He must not witness me sickly.
Lord...
On behalf of king Alfred and
lady aelswith, welcome to Winchester.
The king is with Edward...
I do not recall your name.
I am beocca, father beocca,
an advisor to the king.
My rooms are in the palace?
They are not, lord. They are the most
comfortable rooms available at the inn.
An alehouse?
Yes, lord.
And if my daughter were with me, would she
too be expected to rest in an alehouse?
But she is not, lord.
The palace is under repair.
In my experience,
Roman walls rarely need repair.
You will inform Alfred
I did expect a room at the palace.
I can find my own way to an alehouse,
father. You are dismissed.
Yes, lord.
May you choke on your oysters.
What was that?
The oysters, lord. They are a delight.
We are to march in one week,
less perhaps,
and I will have this matter settled.
What do you say, Edward?
I have looked to god, as you asked,
and it is before god
that I did swear my love.
I say that I am married already.
Then you shall unmarry!
It is as simple as that!
As you clearly lack the courage
to take this step...
Father, to remain married is honourable!
Edward, you will say nothing more!
Bishop erkenwald?
Lord, the girl in question
has chosen to enter a nunnery.
- No, no. She has not, she would not...
- She has given herself to god and...
This is not true.
Therefore, the marriage,
if it did exist at all, can be dismissed.
I wish to see her.
I wish to speak to her...
What you wish, Edward,
is of no importance! None!
The father of your match
has both wealth and men.
You will do your duty!
I do not wish to do my...
Do you believe that I wished
for my brother to be killed in battle
and for the crown
to be placed upon my head?
I did not.
But I soon realised that as well
as it being a burden, it is a privilege...
To lead our people.
The crown of wessex is all-important.
Wessex and england are all-important.
Matters of the heart are not.
She... she would not have
entered a nunnery by choice.
Unless she cares more for her god and
her country than for the son of the king?
You are to be betrothed
and, in good time,
you shall marry aelflaed.
Father pyrlig, the holy relics.
My son will now swear.
Saint cuthbert's teeth, lord,
or something kinder?
The teeth are appropriate, father.
What of my children?
The children will be cared for.
But... not by their mother.
Of course not by their mother.
She now belongs to god.
The children will thrive,
but first, there is a bargain to be made
and a battle to be won.
If the battle is not won,
the children shall become slaves
and their mother a viking's whore.
The crown is all-important.
Do you understand?
I do.
We go slowly, and we rest often?
To remain strong.
The battle cannot begin without us.
That is true.
I would like to ask,
in all seriousness and in confidence,
do I have your confidence?
Of course. Speak freely.
In confidence, then, I ask,
is ragnar the man to lead our army?
Uhtred did suggest him,
but uhtred is gone.
- Uhtred has betrayed us.
- My point exactly.
So is your cousin
the man to lead our army?
Cnut, I was talking friend to friend,
nothing more than hypothesising.
I do not know what that word means,
but I will say this in confidence.
Ragnar is a good man, his father,
the fearless, was a better man.
And ragnar's whole purpose in life
has been to avenge him.
Which he has done by killing kjartan.
I was there.
Which he has done, yes.
Hence, no more purpose.
Once again, ifind it difficult
to disagree with you, aethelwold.
Ragnar is spent.
That said, he will kill you.
What? Why?
He blames you for losing uhtred.
Why? I merely opened his eyes.
And he will close yours, for all time.
I like you, aethelwold,
but ragnar will kill you. Soon.
In the name of Alfred, king of wessex,
I am confiscating these children.
- No. You can't!
- They shall become the property
of the church and dedicate their lives
to the worship of god.
- You are ecgwynn?
- She is.
- Yes.
- You are required in Winchester.
He will ask of his precious daughter.
And you can tell him aethelflaed is well.
Lord, if a Dane army is fast approaching,
then there is only one path to take.
To join Alfred.
Tojoin him and to preserve mercia.
Then we shall fight, aldhelm.
And with luck, the right people shall die.
Ugh! They are ravenous. Permanently.
Take them through.
They are eating into our winter store
and belching it out into the air.
Right.
Here you are.
There, hey, there.
That'll fatten you up nicely, hey?
Good girls.
Good morning, nun!
I am an abbess.
I don't care.
We will wait... for aethelflaed!
To the hall, all of you, quickly, now!
That's it.
What is it?
Abbess?
Danes. Outside.
- I have just witnessed them kill a man.
- How many Danes?
I did not count them, but many.
Why are they not
bursting through the door?
Finan, hold. Sihtric.
They may not know we're here.
No, they have asked
for the lady aethelflaed.
Well, they know someone is here.
There are two other hostages.
We wait inside and will remain silent.
Abbess. You will go to them
and you will talk to them.
No, no, I... I will not.
Yes, you will, because you must.
Did I not say, I do not like you?
You did.
Allow them to believe you are unprotected
and deny aethelflaed is here.
And we will do what, hide?
We will make
an advantage out of this.
Abbess, the hostages, they are dead men
breathing, you cannot save them.
What we must do now is save
the lives of your nuns and my men.
And aethelflaed.
Abbess?
I will do it.
No, this is my house,
it's my responsibility.
I will do it.
It is haesten, with no more than 40 men.
40 that I can see.
Then let us fight them.
No, wait.
What is it you want?
We have some food and some ale.
It is yours.
What we do not have is silver.
If it is ourselves you want, our lives,
I ask you, why?
Aethelflaed!
Aethelflaed, aethelflaed, aethelflaed.
How many times
do I have to say that stupid name?
What I want is aethelflaed!
Give her to me now, or this man dies.
There is no one in this house
called aethelflaed.
Deny her presence once more
and a third man dies,
and I will burn down your nunnery
and everyone inside.
Release him, release him
and take me in his place,
or am I too strong for you?
Why must you behave like this?
Why must you slaughter for no good reason?
Dagfinn.
Aethelflaed.
Why must blood be spilled?
It is heathen. Ungodly.
And you are the devil's incarnation,
nothing more!
And all I can try and do
is ensure that he shall have you.
[Qasdsi
Could you not just have taken
the axe from her hand?
Lord, now?
We do nothing... yet.
Aethelflaed! Enough men and women
have died to save your bony arse.
At beamfleot and now here.
Did my lord Erik
not give his life for you?
How many more must do the same?
Show yourself!
There are many horses at the stable.
Why have her other men
not shown themselves?
Because like the men we just killed,
they are busy filling their breeches.
Aethelflaed!
She is here!
http://hiqve.com/
- It was uhtred!
- I saw who it was!
- Why is he not in the north?
- Because he is here!
We block every entrance
but not the main doors!
And we wait!
We are trapped.
We're alive,
and they are 12 or 13 men less.
But we are trapped under a wooden roof.
Well, what do you suggest, then, lady?
That you give yourself over?
Yes.
Haesten speaks the truth. Why should
I live when so many others have died?
Haesten has never spoken the truth
in his life!
Do not say as much again! Never!
Or those men have died for no reason.
Your men have arrived
at the river ouse, I'm told.
That was the message.
That is good news.
We will rise early tomorrow
and quicken our pace.
Why expend our strength?
The first battle is always in the mind.
Alfred will have his spies
and when they see us
I want bloodhair's men alongside with us.
I want us to be a swarm, one army.
Then we will rise early
and quicken our pace.
What of haesten?
I expect him to keep his word and protect
us from the east, attack from the east.
But only when we have sight
of the enemy and battlefield
can we discuss exactly how we fight.
Agreed.
Are you away to sow another seed, cousin?
I'm away to my bed, cnut.
Alone?
Ragnar!
Again?
Yes.
It's the last time, I promise.
One more son, I swear.
If it's not, I will take your cock.
I swear.
Aethelwold, my friend.
How are you?
Alive still, which is good.
I have been thinking on what you said...
About ragnar
and the likelihood of him killing me.
Soon.
Yes, soon, thank you for reminding me.
I was thinking that perhaps...
I should kill him first.
Is that a plan, at all?
At least you are not laughing at the idea.
How?
How would you kill him?
Well, in his sleep, of course,
I'm not going to fight him.
When?
Soon.
Sooner than he kills me.
Tonight?
I don't know.
The idea's only just come to me.
It should be tonight.
Tomorrow, we quicken our pace, tomorrow,
we begin to think about the battle ahead.
Tomorrow,
ragnar will become a different man.
Once it is done,
you will have my protection.
Fdend.
Very well.
Tonight.
The ale is good.
- It is.
- Very good.
To the creators of fine ale!
May god... bless them.
May the gods bless them. Him.
All doors have been blocked
from the outside, apart from that one.
Will they set a fire?
No. Not yet. He will want you alive.
We should fight, lord.
We should open the doors and fight.
- What, and die?
- It's as good a plan as any.
Osferth, you will open the door
on my word and retreat.
We form a shield wall
and then we negotiate.
Negotiate?
Haesten will want his prize.
To the door!
If you truly belong to me...
You will do as I ask.
In return, I will not abandon you.
I will come for you.
- You're choosing her over me?
- I am keeping us alive.
By making me a prize.
I will not abandon you.
I will lie with you.
You shall remain cursed
until your word is made true.
Your life shall wither, uhtred,
until you find me.
And I will find you.
Shield wall ready!
Lord! There is something happening!
Every man at the ready! Every sword!
Lift the bar and open the door.
Move!
I count a few more
than 30 of the bastards.
Fight, haesten, and you will lose men,
many men, I guarantee it.
I have many men.
But you have just the one life!
And I plan to take it.
Move out!
Dagfinn! Easy, easy!
I will not leave without her, uhtred.
I may lose men,
but you will lose everything,
and the bitch will still be mine.
Then take her,
because that is what you will have to do.
Or we can strike a bargain.
One woman in place of another.
I am in no need of a nun.
Who is this woman?
Skade. The seer.
Finan.
She is yours.
In return, you and your men ride clear
of this place and do not return.
She is not yours to give.
She belongs to bloodhair.
I belong to the man I choose!
The man who has the will to lead,
to conquer!
Bloodhair is not that man!
She has seen Alfred's death and in battle.
Her man will benefit
from that death, greatly.
Is this true?
It's true.
May I approach?
Uhtred, you cannot bargain
with this sack of chicken shit.
You're close enough, lord.
Ifa bargain is made, I will not be
handed over like you would a whore.
I will walk to my new lord.
And should either man go back on his word,
I shall see he is tormented till the end.
I swear.
Do we have an agreement?
Skade in place of aethelflaed?
Agreed. The seer is mine.
Then step back and she will walk to you.
And then you leave.
I will.
And you are cursed once more,
uhtred of bebbanburg.
You shall wither!
Open, let her pass.
This does not mean
the Princess is forgiven, uhtred.
She is safe for now, no more than that.
Leave! Go!
Your life is not your own, lord.
Lord.
Aethelhelm, how good of you to join me.
I thought it fitting that
our first meeting should be at prayers.
My lord king, it's an honour to be asked.
And this, if I am not mistaken,
must be Edward?
Lord. I too am happy
to see you here at Winchester.
I look forward
to meeting your daughter, aelflaed,
but only at a time that you think fit,
of course.
Hmm, charming.
Aethelhelm, I shall bring you
into my confidence immediately.
War is coming,
your lands are under threat.
Danes are marching in numbers
from north to south.
Let us pray for the strength and fortitude
to defeat them once again.
Join me.
I am to my bed.
Good night. Good night.
http://hiqve.com/