I am uhtred, son of uhtred.
Born a Saxon nobleman,
I was robbed of my ancestral lands
and raised as a Dane and as a pagan.
I am uhtred of bebbanburg
and I shall take what is mine!
But I became king Alfred's
greatest sword warrior
defending his kingdom of wessex
and his vision of one united england,
supported by my loyal band of cut-throats,
barbarians and a fallen priest.
I pray that when battle comes,
I will not fail you.
I have found happiness
with my wife gisela,
who has given me two children.
Alfred has married his own daughter
to the weak aethelred,
who sees himself as king of mercia.
But, taken by the Danes,
she fell for one warrior Erik,
and is coveted by haesten.
This haesten has seemingly allied himself
to Alfred.
He can never be trusted.
Now that Alfred's health is failing,
these are dark and dangerous times
for all the peoples of this land.
Destiny is all.
Protect your king!
[Qasdsi
Father beocca.
If what we believe is true
and heaven awaits us?
Which it does, lord, no doubt.
I fear that even if I were allowed to pass
through the gates,
it would still feel like purgatory.
It will not. It cannot, it is heaven.
What has changed since I took the crown?
Danes still raid and slaughter continues
and will continue until the day I die
and beyond.
What has been my purpose?
Your purpose, lord,
is that you are god's king.
Without you there would be no church,
no wessex, no laws,
no burhs, no havens of safety,
no idea of an england.
What you have done is laid the foundations
for a great and godly country.
Nothing has changed, no task is complete.
And after I am gone...
What then?
What you have begun will continue.
It must.
Yes.
Thank you, beocca.
It must.
Guards! Turn away now!
No man is to show me his face!
No man is to see me before bloodhair!
You will go on ahead and remind the camp
that Earl sigurd
must be the first to see me.
Yes, lady.
Once he has my message,
they'll be free to gaze.
My... my lady...
I swear, I did not look at you.
I must take your eyes.
Lady, no, be merciful.
And your tongue.
Bitch.
I will kill...
No. No.
Turn away!
Only the women may look at me
until I have told my lord
what I have seen.
Sigurd, my love.
Drink me and make my vision real.
Let me give you all the strength
that you will need.
I see the death of a king.
Which king?
I see the death...
Of Alfred.
[Qasdsi
It has been seen.
It has been seen!
The death of Alfred and the glory
of Odin's warriors has been seen!
Our path will not be simple.
The gods will demand
that we earn our reward.
But I make you this promise...
From the smallest pig,
to the golden crown upon Alfred's head.
Wessex and everything it holds
shall belong to the warriors of bloodhair!
Uhtred,
what is your opinion
of Edward's sword skill?
My opinion, lord,
is that steapa is wasting his time.
Would you care to explain?
I will lady.
Steapa, stop.
Stop this nonsense.
You should not be using swords.
Skills are taught with a staff.
Thank you, lord.
I prefer to feel the weight of a sword.
It is a sign of the aetheling's bravery.
Let us watch, my dear.
Show me what you've learned.
He learns by the day.
Mother, please.
Show me.
Lord, that grubby Dane
haesten is here.
Uhtred, you must test the boy.
Put the child on his arse.
It is not your place to speak.
Oh, bad luck, Edward.
Uhtred, we have a visitor.
An old friend of yours.
Sacrifices were made
so you would live, boy.
From now on,
you practise only with a staff.
You learn from being hit.
There is warrior inside you.
We will find him.
Hmm. Thank you, uhtred.
You will do
as the lord uhtred says, prince Edward.
He has your safety and welfare in mind.
Bishop erkenwald, thank you.
I trust your wife is well?
She is.
Pretty girl.
Her name escapes me.
She's called gisela, lord, a pagan.
She is once again with child.
A boy.
Your child shall be a boy.
Brother godwin has a gift.
God-given.
Hmm.
If you will excuse me, lord.
Of course.
Edward, you are late for your lessons.
Come.
I hear there are ealdormen
who wish you dead.
You made a whore of a young girl
and left her pupped.
She is no whore.
Bad Edward.
Say it again, I dare you!
His name is sigurd.
His men call him bloodhair.
I do not wish to know why.
Something depraved I'm sure.
I have a man watching
bloodhair's camp, lord, but I'm curious...
He's not asked you to join him, haesten?
He has.
Idechned.
Like you, I have given my word.
Unlike you,
I've accepted the king's missionary.
Your word means nothing.
Does the peace between us all
not hold?
Do my wife and children
not wish to become Christian?
They do?
They do, lady.
I've asked the priest to arrange it.
That is good news.
It is certainly news.
It should be an occasion, lord.
I will consider it, my dear.
Just as soon as we are done
with Earl sigurd, bloodhair.
Will he attack or will he raid?
He will raid, lord.
To assess your strength and readiness.
It is you who must attack.
Destroy his army
and send a message to all northmen.
My lord has eaten something
that is not agreeing?
Too much wine, lord?
Uhtred, you are right.
Sigurd landing his ships on wessex soil
is not acceptable.
We will attack, before the winter bites.
Soonest, lord.
Then we march.
Beocca, send word to aethelred of mercia.
This is a threat to both our lands.
Our allies must join together
with the guard of wessex.
Yes, lord.
I shall draught the letter at once.
Inform him, we shall join him
at the burh of aescengum.
I will now, um...
Take some air.
How is the lady aethelflaed these days?
And the child?
Who does the girl resemble...
One more word against the king's daughter
and I will shove that food
so far down your throat
you'll be shitting it out seconds later.
I have seen him do it.
It's a small miracle.
I am saying nothing
that her husband aethelred is not saying.
And I would say
you are in aethelflaed's debt.
You have men and ships
not because you earned them,
but solely because
she did kill your lord, sigefrid.
I have not forgotten what the bitch did.
- I will never forget.
- That is enough.
Tell her,
I pray our paths will meet once again.
Haesten... no more.
Bloodhair...
Has a woman you would like, uhtred.
Skade.
Her beauty blinds you like the sun,
yet she has all the darkness of the night.
She's a seer.
She's of the devil, father.
I would say
it was a pleasure to see you, uhtred,
but it never is.
Likewise.
May god forgive me,
but I'd like to remove that man's head
with a blunt axe.
The king's health, beocca,
it worsens.
From time to time, yes.
That is why the time you spend
with the aetheling, Edward,
is so important.
Alfred's work must continue.
And you can ensure that it does.
Tell the king I shall meet him
on the road to aescengum, or at the burh.
Why? Where are you going?
To my wife.
Then on to see bloodhair for myself.
You should seek the king's permission...
For once.
A good morning, lord.
Ready yourselves and the horses.
We leave before nightfall.
For where?
For battle.
And not before time.
I'm a warrior.
I'll take this.
What's this gisela?
We have servants to prepare food,
you should be resting.
I have said this to her.
How can I rest
with this wild boy inside of me?
A priest has just told me the same,
that you are carrying a boy.
Of course it's a boy,
he will not keep still.
Thankfully, he will be the last.
That is not something you can prevent.
Oh, I know how to prevent it.
He will be, the last.
You are marching?
Yes, I will join finan
and then we are marching.
Thyra will be here
and I have sent word home,
to coccham, to hild.
She will be with you for the birth
should I not return in time.
But I promise, I will return.
Uh-hmm.
And when you do,
you will be sleeping alone.
You would do that to me?
Oh, yes, I will do that to you...
For a time.
We move!
Good evening to you.
Though I'm pointing a sword
at your heart...
I am a friend.
Habit.
With me.
Then you can tell me about your village.
You!
Come!
Please, god. Holy father in heaven,
spare me from this ordeal.
Stop my heart from beating
and take me now I beg of you,
I beg of all the saints in heaven
to strike me down.
Take my soul and hide, and spare me.
Spare me, lord. Spare me.
It is not death that I fear,
it is the path.
Lord, I beg you.
Stop my heart from beating
and take me now.
Please, please...
Where is the silver?
There is none.
I'm begging you to believe me.
I do not lie.
If you wish to be cooked alive,
then I will cook you alive.
There is no silver. I swear!
Lady...
The silver!
You will answer her.
I have answered her, lord.
There is no wealth here.
Put him into the fire.
No, please. Please, I beg you!
The silver!
Can any of you holy men answer for him?
God in heaven, help me!
Help me!
You have no right, lord.
He was mine to question and to kill.
You have no right.
This is a church,
and a church holds silver.
You.
What's your name?
I am called brother Hubert, lord.
My lord, I swear, we are a poor church.
We have food and ale but we have no more.
Brother Hubert,
if you're speaking the truth,
you will take your own life.
You will do it now, and save your friends.
But, lord, my soul will be damned.
Take your life like a warrior!
And we shall ask
for no more than food and ale.
Lord, I swear. There is no silver.
They're yours, to do with as you please.
Lord, are you certain
you will not use the carriage?
I'm certain. We ride to aescengum.
Steapa.
http://hiqve.com/
Lady,
bloodhair is heading on to the next
village in search of silver.
Did you hear me, lady?
He is ready to leave.
Then let him leave!
We will remain here until
I've finished my work with the priests.
Tell him we will follow.
But he is to leave my guard.
Yes.
Good morning, Hubert.
I believe you now, there is no silver.
So what else can you give me?
Lord, we are ready to march.
Then we should march.
But with half of the guard, no more.
You will follow?
Yes we are allies with wessex,
but there is talk of Danes
raiding on our northern border.
There are forever Danes
on our northern border.
I shall remain here
for the good of mercia.
We cannot neglect our own lands.
Lord, it makes sense
to remain close to wessex.
Alfred will not live forever
and the aetheling Edward is a boy.
He seems to be doing his very best
at living forever.
He is constantly ill but he will not die.
If you see him you should tell him
that I am busy with vikings.
I will inform my father
that you will join us
just as soon as you are able, lord.
Thank you, lady.
You are riding to battle?
Is that not forbidden?
I wish to see the king.
He is a king, he is not "the king."
There are kings and kingdoms all over.
Aldhelm, are we ready?
Lord, you are certain you will not ride?
In god's name, go. Leave me in peace.
Yes, lord.
Good luck at the northern border.
Return safely.
You should be leading your men.
I do not wish to hear the whining voice
of the so-called lady of mercia.
Which is why I prefer you to spend time
at your own estate.
Then I shall leave you in your peace.
How is your daughter?
Our daughter is well,
though I pray she does not inherit
her father's temperament.
Nor the morals of her mother.
Whore!
You have diminished me.
We march into wessex!
To the aid of wessex!
But be in no doubt, what we fight for
is the freedom and the glory of mercia!
And once again we will show
the king Alfred how a warrior should be!
We will show the bastard heathen
how a warrior should be!
She's in there, lord, inside the church.
Am I still needed?
Go find your family.
Who are you? What do you want?
I would like you all to surrender.
Or I will smite you.
What did he say?
"Smite"? What is "smite"?
It's a word, isn't it?
A word from the holy book.
It means slay or kill.
I will kill you.
Smite.
You will smite all of us?
Yeah, most.
Some of you might run away, hopefully.
I've got... I've got a sword.
A very sharp sword.
Though I'd prefer it if you surrendered.
Kill him!
Haesten says she is of the devil.
Then it might be an idea to bar the door
and burn the place down?
Why not?
To bloodhair she will be priceless.
You are skade?
You.
You will do nothing
except go to your lord.
You will tell him that
uhtred of bebbanburg has his witch.
I knew it was you.
There will be a ransom to pay.
No. You will go to my lord and you will
tell him that from this moment forth...
Uhtred of bebbanburg is cursed.
The witch holds his heart in her hands
and she will...
Squeeze it...
And break it.
It is you who are my prisoner now, uhtred.
Seize her.
I said seize her, sihtric! Now!
Bind her hands!
I have aligned myself
with the three spinners of fate
and taken hold of your life.
You belong to me now.
And her mouth.
Your path is the path I choose for you,
uhtred ragnarson.
And your spirit is mine to torment.
Cover her eyes.
We will take her with us to aescengum.
I think she may have got herself
inside his head.
He should kill her and be done with it.
That will not kill the curse.
There is no curse.
If I say there is no Christian god,
does that make it so?
There is no curse, sihtric.
I have seen women throw a curse
and the next day a man is dead.
Right, that is enough talking.
To speak of it makes it stronger.
Uhtred,
we have been discussing strategy
and have decided that we shall
remain here, within the burh, and wait.
For what?
For bloodhair to attack.
What makes you believe he will attack?
Is that not what Danes do, uhtred?
They cannot help themselves.
Why should he not attack. I am here.
You are here and so, too, is your guard.
Why throw men against the walls of a burh
when the riches of Winchester
are unprotected?
Would he do that?
He doesn't have an army
large enough to hold Winchester.
What if haesten were to join him?
You seem to be saying
we should have remained at home, uhtred.
If you believe the advantage
of the burh to be dismissed, lord,
you must clearly have an alternative.
I don't know you.
I am sigebriht, son of sigelf.
It is my villages that the heathen burn.
My father built these walls.
And he built them well sigebriht,
which is why bloodhair will not attack.
He will not want to lose men.
Not even to kill a king?
He will wait, for us to starve,
or he will pass, lord. He will not attack.
But we must. That is still my advice.
If Winchester is vulnerable, lord...
This woman that you have taken,
why is she here?
She has value.
And sigurd will want her back.
I refuse to call him bloodhair.
- He will.
- She is what to him?
A wife?
A lover?
Erm, she is a...
A seer.
Sorceress.
Hmm.
The simple mind of a Dane
believes in signs, Edward.
If a bird would fly
from their camp to ours,
they would see it as a sign and follow.
They would march into battle,
all because a "seer"
caught sight of a bird.
Yes, lord.
It can happen that way.
Then it follows that without his "seer",
there can be no signs.
Sigurd is blind. There can be no battle.
Lord, you are both right and wrong.
We wait, uhtred.
Now...
I wish to look at her.
Skade.
Father beocca,
you do not need to trouble yourself.
No, lord?
Unlock the door.
What are they doing?
Alfred's said he'd like to hump the witch.
No word of lie.
Uhtred, you will leave us.
Is that wise, lord?
She is secured by chains
and I will not venture too close.
You will leave.
You have left him alone?
It's his wish.
Do you honestly believe that bloodhair
will go directly to Winchester?
Our families are there, unprotected.
Which is why we cannot sit and wait
for an attack that will not come.
Uhtred you must make him see the danger
for those we love.
You reek of death, lord.
I do. Sadly, I do.
Why sadly?
Your life has been rich,
you have reputation.
There is more to be done.
I must see that it is done.
Ask your question.
How long...
Before I am taken? Do you know?
Is that something that you can see?
You will not see another summer.
But your name will live on.
You will be remembered
as the first, last
and only king of all saxons.
I do enjoy the summer time.
Sigurd, my lord,
bloodhair, my lover, hear me,
free me, avenge me.
Come for me, die for me,
want me, desire me.
Sigurd, free me!
Bloodhair, come to me!
Die for me, avenge me! Free me!
There is a king in this camp!
Come to me, desire me!
If she insists upon calling, lord,
we should make use of her.
Free me!
Bloodhair!
Come for me! Avenge me, free me!
I demand it!
When can we bind her mouth shut?
Die for me! Desire me!
Let her sing.
There is a king in this camp!
That is not singing.
Bloodhair!
Lord uhtred...
Come to me!
Are you going to allow that woman
to wail all night long?
For a little while longer, yes, sigebriht,
Bloodhair!
There is a king for you to kill!
Shut her up.
Quiet, woman.
Here is a bit of loose talk
for you.
Sigebriht there,
son of whoever,
would like to rip the innards
from young Edward's belly.
Would you like to know why?
- No.
- I'll tell you.
Edward, the non-bastard son of Alfred,
has whelped twins
on the girl whom sigebriht did love.
And does sigebriht still love this girl?
Can someone not just cut her throat?
Why are you telling me this?
It is of no concern to me.
They will make it your concern, uhtred.
They will find a way
and Edward shall become your charge.
You are a king-maker, my friend
and Alfred knows it.
I am undecided.
I could take the place of your woman,
uhtred ragnarson.
Together we could rule
from north to south.
Hear it.
You men there, take her down
and return her to the cell.
Let her rest.
Good night, lord.
Why have you not killed me?
What is it you want?
I am worth more than just silver.
Put the food into your mouth and chew.
If it is me that you want,
then have me.
I will not object.
I have no need of a whore.
You will soon have need of a woman.
You have not killed me, lord,
because that will leave you cursed still.
Until the end and beyond.
Our paths are entwined
and our fate is shared.
He is here.
Lord! It is bloodhair! He has hostages!
Every man to the walls!
Every sword and spear must be ready!
Osferth, prepare to open the gates,
finan with me.
- Uhtred, what is it?
- Who is it?
Bloodhair, lord, with hostages.
He wishes to negotiate?
Possibly.
Uhtred ragnarson!
What depravity is this?
Alfred of wessex!
You have my woman.
Return her now, or your people will die!
Lord, I know each of those wretches.
Does he wish to negotiate or not?
If it is your woman that you want,
then let us negotiate!
We do not wish to see the death
of another innocent!
I have said all I will say!
Lord, I beg you, not the young, please.
Not the young!
Not the young, please.
Spare the young, lord.
They can serve you. Please, lord...
Osferth, the gates. Steapa, be ready.
They are killing women, lord!
- That gates!
- Open the gates!
Earl sigurd!
Kill one more hostage and I shall let
every man here see her nakedness
and then I shall spill her guts.
Just one more!
Do it, lord,
I'll see you in the next life.
Kill them all! Attack!
Bloodhair, kill them now!
She is an angry woman.
- Attack now!
- What is your answer?
I have a mind to kill her regardless.
She tires me.
He cannot do it, lord! He is cursed!
Kill them all!
You will not harm her again!
The price has risen.
You will not only spare the hostages,
you will free them all
and send them across to the burh.
What I'll do is feed you your own cock.
Release her.
You have until sunset
to free the hostages.
Or each man in this fortress
will take his turn.
Until sunset!
I believe negotiations are over, lord.
You will not see Valhalla,
uhtred ragnarson! I swear it!
Bloodhair!
Uhtred ragnarson!
- Kill them all!
- Uhtred ragnarson!
Do not harm one hair from her head.
She is mine!
Lord, we need to change our plan.
We cannot wait for him to attack
because he will not.
Her value is even greater
than I first thought.
He will wait for as long as it takes.
Aethelred and the mercians,
they will be close.
And they will be seen.
What we must do is stop them on the road.
I can send finan to do just that.
And then we must join them.
We must choose the place of battle, lord,
but we must act quickly,
while his blood burns.
Join aethelred where?
I am thinking fearnham. There's a hill.
I know it, lord,
it would give us an advantage.
But how do we join aethelred at this hill
and how do we ensure Earl sigurd
will follow, if that is the plan?
Finan will find the mercians
and we will ensure bloodhair follows.
You and I, lord, we will draw him.
And if aethelred cannot be found?
Then we fight alone.
But we must act quickly. It must be today.
I'm ready, lords.
It won't take me long
to find the mercians.
To fearnham. Go.
Open the gates!
Psst.
The gates.
We go and we do not stop!
They cannot overtake us!
They must not overtake us!
For the freedom of wessex!
They are escaping.
Lord! Lord, they are running!
Lord, the Saxon army
is fleeing the fortress.
Who did you see?
I saw them all, lord.
I saw the lady skade.
I saw uhtred ragnarson. The whole army.
Every man and every sword with me.
It's time!
Horses!
Close the gates!
Lord! They're giving chase.
They're giving chase.
We wait.
Long enough for them not to see
they are being followed.
And we pray.
Lord, the cart is stuck.
Release the horse from its harness
and ride.
Sihtric, your axe.
They've been after silver,
so let's give them some.
Keep going! Ride!
We must not be seen!
We track them,
and then we kill the bastards!
Be prepared for a trap.
Is this the place, lord?
Is this fearnham?
It is.
Perhaps finan did not make the journey.
Do we wait for the Danes to catch us?
It's silver, lord.
They must have been too afraid
to stop and fix the cart.
Wrap it in cloth. Keep it safe.
Let's move on.
I want every Saxon dead by nightfall.
Move on!
Your man is here.
I know it.
It is finan.
And the mercians.
We are an army!
Glory shall be ours!
Shield wall!
Ready!
They have the hill, we have the numbers
and will of the gods.
Odin's warriors!
We stand our ground!
They will come onto us!
And we will take their heads
from their shoulders.
No Saxon leaves this field alive!
Hold firm!
We do not break! We stand our ground!
For mercia!
Fight for your women and your children!
Hold the line!
- Get me up, man!
- Close the gap!
Hold!
Who sounds the horn?
It is Alfred.
It is Alfred and the men of wessex!
Steapa.
Shield walls!
Form a line!
Advance!
We are trapped, lord!
Lord, do we fight?
Bloodhair, you do not yield.
Do not yield.
Give them no ground!
Give them nothing but your sword!
They are running scared!
They are beaten!
Uhtred...
She is gone.
She has given you a son.
But she's gone.
I must go to her.
- Uhtred, no.
- No, I must go to her!
Uhtred she has gone!
She's in the ground.
It was days ago.
She is gone.
http://hiqve.com/