I am uhtred, son of uhtred.
King Alfred grows weaker each day
leaving wessex vulnerable
to enemies within.
Aethelwold is there?
They will march, from north to south,
as a single army.
I too am now seen as a threat.
But I have promised to protect
Alfred's daughter, aethelflaed.
Your husband intends to kill you. I shall
leave now and you must do the same.
Indeed, both aethelred
and haesten wish her dead.
Saving her life has come
at a high cost to me.
Skade in place of aethelflaed.
And you are cursed once more,
uhtred of bebbanburg.
I have been thinking about ragnar
and the likelihood of him killing me.
I should kill him first.
My brother has disowned me
as a traitor.
And it is true.
You are no longer my brother!
I betrayed him by leaving him
in the company of men without honour.
Destiny is all!
He is dead! He is dead!
Alfred's dead! He is dead! Alfred's dead!
The Saxon cur is no more!
He is dead! Alfred is dead!
Jackdaw, is this true?
How did you hear this?
It's all over the country, they say,
he is dead!
Alfred has shat his precious soul
out of his arsehole!
Ragnar! Alfred is dead!
The Saxon shit is gone!
Ragnar!
Ragnar?
Ragnar...
Ragnar... ragnar...
Take it. Close your hand. Ragnar.
Ragnar, close your hand and take this.
Ragnar, take this.
Ragnar, take it! No! No! No, ragnar! No!
No! No! No! No!
So he is dead. This is good news.
No! No!
Ragnar! Ragnar! Ragnar, no!
Move! Move!
Ragnar, no! No!
Who? Who did this?
His whore?
I will ask.
Ragnar ragnarson,
the only man amongst you is dead!
Who did this?
Cowards! All of you!
You had to kill him while he was sleeping!
Brida, it was his woman,
the knife was in her hand.
It is ragnar's sword in her belly.
Why would he kill a woman
he was trying to pup?
Why would she kill him? How?
Maybe it was you who killed him.
Her husband was ploughing another field,
so the crazy bitch killed them both.
No. Bloodhair, no!
This is not the answer!
He was your leader!
He was to give you wealth! Protection!
We go on! Nothing has changed.
Everything has changed!
We go on!
You have no leader.
Then I shall lead!
With bloodhair,
we will Bury ragnar and we will march.
Then get it done and keep her quiet.
Release her.
Though I did not know him well.
He was a good man, a brave warrior.
Are you going to behave?
You speak to him as if he understands?
He will not understand the words,
but he will know I am a friend,
someone he can trust.
So, when the time comes to push him
into battle, he will not hesitate.
Is that the way you treat your men?
You win their trust
and expect them to follow?
It is not a game nor a strategy.
It is who you are.
A man who instils trust.
I would like you to kiss me.
And then?
Begin with a kiss and see where it leads.
- If you would rather not...
- It is something I would enjoy...
And then regret.
Lady, in Erik, you chose
someone you could not be with.
And I am the same.
I would not see you hurt again.
Who would have to know?
- Who would need to know...?
- Skade.
Skade would know.
She would see
everything I care for destroyed.
She must be found, recovered.
I would say it is impossible
for you to recover her.
- I must.
- How?
How? You cannot attack beamfleot.
To fight haesten's army,
you will need an army.
My father is to join the mercians
at aegelesburg.
I will meet him with our guards
and aethelred.
You will be safer there than here.
It is a good decision.
I will tell the king
of haesten's attempt to kill me.
By attacking me, he has made himself
an enemy of wessex.
Come with me.
My father will forgive you.
And you will lead his men
against beamfleot.
I do not want his forgiveness.
Then use his army! Use his men!
And recover skade.
I offer you a way to end this curse.
Lord? We are ready for another chapter.
The country is rife with
word of my death I am told?
So what a fright you shall be
to the Danes.
Marching beyond wessex and into mercia,
to stand by the side of aethelred
and look them in the eye.
To look them in the eye.
Yes.
- Steapa, when you are ready.
- Yes, lord.
[Gasdingl
We march, men of wessex!
We march!
Leave us.
Some of his men believe this to be a sign.
For ragnar to die without his sword
means the battle can't be won.
They are your men now.
You must convince them otherwise.
I won't prevent any man
from returning north.
They have no leader.
We can lead, you and I.
This morning, you claimed that you would
lead with bloodhair and now you choose me?
I do not wish to bed bloodhair.
Already we're divided.
Without ragnar,
we shall become separate tribes.
I will let you grieve.
You will find us at the river ouse,
one army.
It was either you or bloodhair
who killed ragnar.
Brida, you cannot accept
that his last night was spent with a whore
and that she killed him.
Who knows what goes on
between a man and a woman?
Ragnar did not appreciate
nor deserve your love.
We have lost a great warrior,
a great man.
I know this better than most.
Ragnar ragnarson was my cousin.
And I am angry with him,
because he deserved a better death!
Killed half naked,
killed without his breeches and his sword!
Far from the battlefield!
It is a death I fear most.
It is a death our great warrior,
bloodhair, fears most.
But we men standing here
are fortunate men, the gods are with us.
Yes!
We have swords in hand
and the battle ahead of us!
Land to be won, silver to be shared
and saxons to kill!
We are Danes, together!
- Together!
Together!
Osferth...
Fetch uhtred, tell him we have a guest.
A woman.
How can you tell it's a woman?
You have to ask?
Fetch uhtred.
I knew you'd be
with your Princess.
Something has happened?
You left him.
Ragnar?
He had waited years for you to come home,
and within a matter of days,
you were gone.
You should have left
the Saxon bitch to die.
Where is he? I will go to him.
He's dead! Ragnar is dead!
He doesn't feast in Valhalla.
Instead, he lies under a pile of stones
at a lake near loidis!
There was no honour in his death.
None.
He will spend eternity
in the cold of niflheim,
because of you, uhtred of bebbanburg.
You chose her.
You chose Alfred, and you left him.
No, sihtric.
I should kill you,
but I want you to live
with the pain of his death.
He was your brother.
Uhtred, I...
My brother is dead.
Oh, god.
It is her, skade, and her curse.
It goes on and on.
Could it not be just life?
Death comes to us all.
It is her. She must be recovered.
We go to Alfred and to aethelred.
We do?
And we beg for an army.
Once the last of bloodhair's men
have sailed up the ouse,
we will march on mercia and then wessex.
He will have me send you to him,
bloodhair.
It is I who chooses who I sit with.
Lie with.
Kill.
You have only ever taken women.
They do not give themselves to you.
Whether it is given or taken,
I get what I want.
You may take my body,
but you will not have my power.
I have one thousand men.
That is power enough.
The man I choose, he will benefit greatly
from Alfred's death.
But I will have to give myself
to that man...
And only when it is earned.
Maybe I should just hump you now
and be done with it.
Prove yourself, lord.
Prove myself to a woman?
And I will allow you inside me
and my power inside you.
Uhtred will come for me,
and if you are to take his place,
then you must first kill him.
And then I am yours.
Riders.
Spears to the walls!
No man is to pass. No man.
http://hiqve.com/
I ought to kill you where you stand, lord.
You could try, my friend.
I am here to see the king.
You ride with outlaws, my dear.
He is an outlaw of wessex not mercia.
We are here to see my father.
What is it that you have
to say to the king
that you cannot say to your husband?
I wish to speak of treachery and traitors.
The Dane, haesten,
did attack the nunnery at wincelcumb.
It was his purpose to kill me.
Haesten claims to be a friend to Alfred.
He is not.
Let the outlaw pass.
No weapons.
None at all.
Lord aethelred, like you,
we stand against the Danes.
No weapons is the command, irishman,
none at all.
It is good to see you safe, lady.
Lord aldhelm.
I shall advise the king you're here.
My father cannot suspect
my husband is the traitor.
We should kill your husband
and be done with it.
And begin a war
between wessex and mercia now?
Lady, I'm joking. We'll kill him tomorrow.
We halt! Stop!
We know what "halt" means, big man.
Steapa, we are both thirsty and hungry.
You may enter the hall, lady,
the outlaws do not.
Then I choose to remain here
with the outlaws.
As you wish.
Erm, what if I need to piss?
Then take out your cock.
And if you mistake it for a weapon,
what then?
Steapa, food and ale would be appreciated.
I will arrange it.
And steapa, good food!
Meat! And lots of ale.
If uhtred is no longer
with the Danes, that is one matter.
But should he realign himself
with Alfred or Edward, that is another.
What has occurred to
bring uhtred from one side to the other?
He is uhtred.
Who called him from north to south?
My wife?
How, lord?
Why? Why did she call him to her aid?
What does she know?
Is it important, when Danes are marching
and we are unsure on which side we stand?
Yes, it is important! Very!
She knew of the danger posed by me.
She tied and summoned uhtred
with the promise of her bed, no doubt.
She knew.
Then lord, may I suggest
we first establish what business
uhtred has with her father?
I want all of my men at the ready.
For what?
If she is here to accuse me,
to discredit me, we must be ready.
Yes, lord.
- Steapa.
- Lord sigebriht.
An approximation to a witan has gathered.
The outlaws are required.
What is an approximation to a witan?
It's almost a witan but not quite.
We must be without the king.
Apologies for keeping you waiting
in the cold, my dear.
Your father is to blame.
After deliberation,
he has decided not to attend.
I am here in place of the king.
I am here to speak for the king.
Our business is with Alfred.
Edward is Alfred.
On this occasion.
We are all curious of what
you have to say, my dear. Speak.
Danes are near.
Yes. Which is why we are gathered.
This is not some hunting party.
Haesten is with them.
His army is allied with them.
But it was haesten who first advised the
king that the Danes were marching south?
He would do that, lord.
Haesten also advised the king
this Dane army included yourself,
uhtred ragnarson.
It does not, father.
Which we can clearly see.
Haesten has betrayed the king.
He rode to mercia to kill me.
Uhtred saved me.
God is good. Praise him!
Praise him!
Uh, I am at a loss.
How is it that uhtred knew of this danger?
How is it that he knew
exactly where to find you?
An interesting question, lord.
An irrelevant question.
Uhtred made a plan with this Dane,
this haesten,
to save you, to gain your trust,
to gain entry to this estate.
An assassin, even?
No, he saved me!
I should have expected nothing different.
Uhtred has risked everything for me...
That is what he wants you to believe,
I'm sure.
It seems a rather grand strategy
lord aethelred, and for what?
He is here, among us!
And under guard.
Then let us
get to the truth of the matter!
Let us hear exactly why uhtred is here.
What do you have to say to me?
I wish to speak to you alone.
This is a witan. We are one people.
What you have to say affects all of us.
These men are my friends and allies.
I have nothing to hide.
I saved your daughter's life.
It was haesten's intention to kidnap her.
If that could not be done,
he would have killed her.
And you claim that he, too, is your ally.
I have never made that claim.
I have listened to haesten,
but I've never believed him fully.
That you are here with aethelflaed
is the only reason you are alive.
Do not tell me what you have done.
Tell us all what it is you want.
You always want something.
I want one thousand men.
One thousand men
and I will give you beamfleot.
I do not need beamfleot.
I will give you peace.
I will defeat haesten.
I will prevent him from joining
with the earls cnut and bloodhair.
Not forgetting the Earl ragnar.
My brother is dead, lord.
That is to your advantage.
With haesten defeated and ragnar gone,
the Danes will have half the army
and no leader.
To prevent a great war,
you must attack haesten.
That seems viable, lord.
You wish me to divide my army?
- Yes.
- Send one thousand men east?
- Yes!
- That is too great a risk to wessex, lord.
Haesten sits inside a fortress.
One thousand men could die upon its walls
easily, and then what?
We are overrun.
We devise a plan.
Why?
What is at stake for uhtred ragnarson?
Is it mercia you care for? Is it wessex?
Or is there another reason
for this attack?
Vengeance, lord!
Do you require the detail?
You seek vengeance?
I do.
The man is a fool...
Who believes all of us to be fools.
You arrived here under
the protection of the lady of mercia.
I shall not undermine that protection.
You are free to leave
when you are ready and rested.
You remain an outlaw of wessex.
Are you here to join me in prayer,
father pyrlig?
I am not.
My lord, Edward,
would like to speak with uhtred.
About what?
I would like to give him hope, father.
Hope.
Half the number of men he asked for.
Or more.
But, only if it were to bring a peace,
till the spring at least.
Edward needs time.
My father's sickness has cast a shadow.
And I, um, I am not yet ready
to... bring light.
Cometh the hour.
I fear a great battle now
would have only one outcome, defeat.
But if we were able to weaken the Danes,
as uhtred has suggested...
We need to hear more of his plan.
Forgive me.
There is nothing to forgive, lord.
You have the wisdom of a king.
Should I bring him to you? Uhtred?
We could all at least listen.
He does plan well.
Yes. Do that.
You are going to fetch him now?
Yes, lord.
I should meet him privately. Where?
Thinking on it, lord, may I suggest
you meet him in clear sight,
as though nothing is secret nor hidden?
She shames me with
every breath that she continues to take.
There are more pressing matters, lord.
You continue to defend her, aldhelm.
It has not gone unnoticed.
My concern is mercia and aethelred,
always.
What's this?
Who does Edward imagine himself to be?
I came to sit with my sister for a while.
My sister, the outlaw.
You grow by the day, Edward.
He grows wiser.
Slowly, but hopefully.
If you would excuse me.
I was sorry to hear of ragnar's death.
He was a heathen but a good man.
I shall pray for him.
Amen.
He would not thank you
for your prayers, father.
Well they are his, all the same.
I pray for you too, uhtred.
And I will not stop,
in spite of your pigheadedness.
And me, father?
Oh, I'm afraid you belong
to the devil already.
Hmm, you could well be right.
Should we get on with the matter,
father beocca?
The sooner we get back to the hall
the better.
Yes.
Edward is here because
he has something to say, to ask.
For the sake of appearances,
you should all try to behave
as if you're completely disinterested.
How... how many men does haesten have?
Maybe as many as one thousand.
And a fortress.
Beamfleot.
I wish to understand why...
You believe you can defeat him
when it appears impossible.
Laying siege to the fortress would
take three thousand and many would die.
But I will use his hatred of me
to draw him out.
We could feint an attack with
a small number of men and then retreat.
Haesten will not be able to resist
the opportunity of killing me.
On open ground, with an army,
we will have a chance.
Men will still die.
It is war.
Men will die at beamfleot
or they will die here and at Winchester.
But as I said to the king,
defeating haesten
could well prevent a greater war.
And that is no false claim, lord.
Nothing deters a warrior more
than the news of defeat.
It is a plan that can work,
but uhtred will need men, an army.
And I do not wish the devil
to take me too easily.
There's a thick forest
surrounding beamfleot.
A good place to hide an army.
Yes, lord, a good place
to hide 500 men, or more.
Then you shall have them.
Is that a promise you can keep, lord?
It is, or I can never be called king.
Edward, you are certain?
Set a day for the attack
and I will be there.
You shall have the men.
Draw haesten out of the fort.
Our army will be
hidden in the woods, waiting.
You have my word. I swear.
Open the gates.
You cannot do what you have promised
without the approval from the king.
I will speak to him.
Do not leave it too late.
If he denies you, leave time
to ask him again and again.
To beg?
If needed, yes.
It was cold, so I lit a fire.
I hope you don't mind.
We have servants to light fires.
Come.
Sit.
I do not have an appetite.
When will you return to wincelcumb?
Oh, I have no plans to return.
I have assigned my guard to uhtred
and will remain here to go with my husband
and the men of mercia into battle.
May I say...
You did not appear...
Concerned, nor surprised, lord,
at haesten's attempt to kill your wife.
Does my reaction
now meet with your approval?
It does. Thank you.
My dear, I assure you
that I will not rest,
until I find the truth of what happened
and those responsible
shall pay with their lives.
Haesten, for one,
is directly responsible for the attack.
Why do you not seek to punish him?
Because I am required here.
My father too will seek
retribution and justice, I am sure.
Should he live that long.
I pray that he does.
I've found my appetite, after all.
I killed this hare myself with an arrow.
You are pleased with more
than the hunting of a hare?
I am. Alfred is dead.
And I sit opposite a vision of beauty.
I belong to another.
He will come.
Soon, lhope.
And like this hare,
will fall by my arrows.
And then he avenge me, lord.
All of me.
Who else was witness to this promise?
Is that important?
All that matters is that I gave my word.
Lord, I was there
with the lady aethelflaed,
finan, the boy, sihtric, osferth.
Some others may have overheard possibly.
Father, it is a worthy plan.
I gave my word that...
What you gave was not yours to give!
- Father...
- Say nothing!
Father beocca, inform uhtred
that Edward has withdrawn his support.
But I have not.
- Lord uhtred has already left camp.
- Then send a messenger!
Lord king, haesten is our enemy now,
attacking him is to our advantage...
- Despatch a messenger!
- It is to my advantage!
I beg you to listen to me!
If haesten is allowed
to join cnut and bloodhair,
there will be a great battle.
I'm not ready for such a battle
nor what will follow.
I am not a king, not yet.
And I fear the aftermath of a great battle
will be a challenge too far.
Lord, I am no warrior nor strategist,
but if we can defeat
one third of a great army
before it has the opportunity to gather...
Surely that is a good thing?
We would not be marching to beamfleot
in support of uhtred
but to protect the kingdom.
And to delay a greater battle
and give me time.
Time to become worthy of your crown.
You should have approached me.
But you speak the truth.
You are not yet ready, far from it.
You gave your word without the means
nor ability to keep it.
Perhaps you will never be ready.
Leave me.
- Father...
- I said, leave me.
Is it possible to be both proud
and feverish with anger?
It is often the way, lord, with children.
He is his father's son.
Of that, I have no doubt.
He can become a man to follow, lord,
given the opportunity.
Gather your weapons.
Off your arses now
and gather your weapons.
Gather your weapons!
Steapa!
We march, lord, to beamfleot.
Come on. Make ready. We march!
It has grown heavier these past weeks.
I will manage.
God willing, this will be
the last of both Alfred and Edward.
You disagree, aldhelm?
They know my god, lord. The Danes do not.
Long live the king! Long live the king!
Long live the king!
Are you are not going with them, my dear?
My place is in mercia, lord.
Huh?
You are a lucky man.
You will go back to haesten and tell him
exactly what you have seen here. Agreed?
Yes.
Uhtred has finally arrived to claim you,
as you said he would.
With how many men?
Not more than 30.
That is all?
30... 50...
All he can do is
try to creep over the walls.
And when he moves,
I will have his balls.
30 men is nothing.
He is no longer a lord.
He has no men, no silver, no land.
Then be sure to win me, lord.
And be sure to gift me prisoners.
I have not seen a man beg for mercy
for some time.
The great lord uhtred and his army.
Ready the archers
and prepare every last man.
The Dane-slayer shall die
this very morning.
Yes, lord.
Lord uhtred! Such a frightening sight!
You are a coward, haesten,
hiding inside your fortress!
When the priests of eoferwic did rise,
you fled.
When sigefrid attacked Alfred, you fled.
And at the nunnery, once again, you fled.
I took your woman!
And as long as I live and breathe,
she still is my woman!
Fight me! I will wait for you
in the clearing there.
Bring a guard and no more.
Let us make this square
and let the two of us fight!
That is what you want uhtred, to die?
What I want is an end to this!
What is most likely to happen
is you will remain a coward,
you will remain inside your fortress...
Songs will be sung about your cowardice.
I shall pay for them to be written!
I am no coward, Dane-slayer!
If death is what you want,
then you shall have it!
Lord, the job is done.
It's been half a day.
Maybe he's scared of the priest.
Vveleave!
Lord! Lord! Lord!
Run!
Halt!
Two lines!
Shields up!
Surround them!
Give them no escape!
And then we kill
every last one of the bastards!
Turn!
Circle!
May the good lord protect me.
Protect us all.
We wait.
- We hold. We give them no ground!
- We have no ground to give, lord.
Give up uhtred,
and the rest of you will live!
All I want is the Dane-slayer!
What you will get, haesten,
is my sword up your hairy arse!
As you wish.
You will die on your knees!
Lord, where is Alfred's army?
Why are they waiting?
I want the head of uhtred ragnarson!
Stand fast!
Sihtric, no!
Not one man is to live!
Turn the field red
with Saxon blood and flesh!
- Lord?
- We hold our position.
They're being slaughtered.
Lord king, I gave him my word.
We hold our position!
We cannot just stand by
and watch them die!
What would uhtred do?
He would allow his enemies
to destroy one another.
- I gave him my word!
- Then what will you do, boy?
You can either bleat
or you can make a decision!
What will you do?
http://hiqve.com/