I am uhtred, son of uhtred.
On the Eve of his death,
I finally made peace
with the great king Alfred.
You are hereby pardoned.
He is gone.
Wessex is in chaos.
Aldhelm, have a messenger
return to mercia,
I would like the comfort
of further hearth guards.
And his vision
of one england, is incomplete.
It is the purpose of the witan
to choose a king.
Uhtred cannot be allowed
to ally himself to Edward.
This is the moment
the Danes have long waited for.
But brida seeks the truth.
Men are saying freely
it was him who killed ragnar.
Aethelwold?
Was it him?
He was in fear of ragnar.
Then he's mine to kill.
Only with thyra's blood can
we send my brother ragnar to Valhalla.
You will tell your friend uhtred
that his pardon is to be rescinded.
He must leave Winchester
or I shall have him taken.
The lady aelswith
has dishonoured her husband's wishes
and I am imprisoned...
At a time when my sister
is seen only as a Dane.
Is that not what she is?
An enemy.
In a hole is where you belong.
Destiny is all!
Beocca!
Beocca my love.
He is with god.
May his soul rest in peace
for all eternity.
Amen.
Fire!
Sound the bell!
Fetch the water barrels!
We should meet, lord,
continue our previous discussion.
For what purpose?
The Danes will hear of Alfred's death
and they will attack.
Mercia.
- Mercia will be ready.
- To die? Or to thrive?
Find me.
I find him to be lower
than a snake's belly.
That does not mean that he is wrong.
We need to stop the fire spreading!
Get more water!
Faster! Get more water!
Oh bejesus!
Oh, dear lord!
Fetch father beocca! Fetch him now! Go!
- More water!
- Sihtric!
Thyra? Is she inside?
I thought, I thought
she was at the palace?
- No. No, she left. She walked out!
- More water!
[Gasdingl
father beocca?
We would like a last moment with the king.
Alone.
Yes, of course.
Lady aelswith, forgive me...
You appear to be going against
the king's wishes.
Father beocca?
You may be needed.
Get the door! Get the door!
Get back! Get back! It's falling!
No! No, this is not happening!
Thyra!
I am here!
Father, she is with god now,
you know that.
And he will welcome her, I'm sure.
It's how her family died, within a fire.
You think that would been a comfort?
Or would it terrify her further?
Father, all we know is
that she's at peace now.
She's at peace.
You need to walk away
now, father.
A drink of ale maybe?
Once the heat has gone,
I shall recover her
and wrap her for you to Bury.
No. No I will find her. She is my wife.
She is.
We'll help you then.
This fire did not just happen, it did not.
These are dark and important days
for both wessex and mercia.
Just as soon as the Danes
hear of Alfred's death...
They will attack,
you have said, and we agree.
- We will fight.
- Why?
- Why fight only to lose?
- Who says we must lose?
To have even the smallest chance
of victory,
mercia would need wessex
and wessex has been left with a pup
as its master. You will lose.
The Danes will march and we will have
no choice other than to fight.
We negotiate.
Then let them slaughter Edward,
and the small number of idiots
who choose to follow him.
Small number?
Edward does not have
the whole of wessex behind him.
Some will follow, but not all.
Wessex will not have
great numbers of men.
Lord sigebriht is about to return to cent
and ready his own considerable guard
and fyrd.
To do what? To join the Danes?
Edward is not Alfred
and never can be but...
- There will be no need for swords!
- I am merely introducing myself!
- You will let me go!
- Not until there is calm!
There is madness.
Father beocca, you are suffering.
I do not wish to hear your voice!
It was you who killed her,
not some stray Ember on a bed of straw!
I am not to blame for your misfortune.
It was you, if not directly,
then by the words you whisper,
by the lies you tell, the bile you spew
I think we should find another table.
In the eyes of some, a gentle woman
became an enemy and nothing more.
You should turn a deaf ear to this man.
Father beocca,
I will forgive this display, just once!
Another word and you will pay.
What have I been saying?
Wessex is splintered.
I will have no more of it.
Haesten? What is this?
It is the beginning, my friend.
Alfred, king of the shit-eating saxons...
Has breathed his last!
The king is dead!
Haesten, and you are certain this time?
Dagfinn?
It is true, lord.
We have heard it many times,
from priests, and warriors,
and peasants alike.
They cry in the streets of Winchester.
Then it begins.
It begins.
Sharpen your blades!
It begins!
Is there to be a trial,
or just a simple execution?
Uhtred, it was mother's intention
to cut your throat,
but she has been persuaded
to revert to banishment.
You are to leave Winchester
and wessex and never return.
And what of Edward?
What of the king's letter, his pardon?
Does that count for nothing?
Uhtred, you must leave
or she will have you killed.
Find beocca.
I must speak to beocca. Fetch him, please.
I cannot fetch him...
He has trials enough.
What trials?
I am here.
I have heard what the lady has said
and I am here to beg you,
uhtred, to beg you to stay.
- Father beocca, he cannot stay.
- There will be a hearing.
Perhaps.
And we shall be heard.
We must be heard.
What has happened?
Accept a trial and speak out.
If you do not,
then the devil will have won!
Beocca?
Do not abandon what you helped to build!
There is a change in you.
Thyra is with god...
The gods even.
How?
Fire.
Set by good Christian men...
No doubt.
Which men?
She is with gisela now,
she is with her mother!
We cannot allow ourselves
to be consumed by her death.
All that Alfred stood for is crumbling.
You, uhtred, cannot be
dragged into the shadows!
You must become the light.
My lady aethelflaed...
You will inform your brother
and your mother,
that mercia has a king
with his own mind.
I will do nothing of the sort.
Alfred is gone.
Therefore all agreements
made with Alfred no longer stand.
Mercia will remain allied with wessex,
the two countries will stand together
or they will fail.
The two countries are equals!
Each free to choose
who to befriend and who to fight.
Who to fight?
Lord aldhelm...
You must remind my husband
what it means to be mercian.
Lord king...
I must say I do not disagree with her.
I need assuring, lord,
that you will not align mercia
with aethelwold, nor the Danes.
- It would be a betrayal.
- You need assuring?
We are proud mercians, lord.
Do you question me?
I am concerned.
Do you doubt me?
I simply wish to understand your thinking.
My guard of 50 men...
Did you send for them?
You will agree
they are needed at home, lord.
Did you send for my guard of 50 men?
I did not.
Should you live, aldhelm?
Never disobey me again.
Never.
Your wound is from an alehouse brawl.
I have been considering
my defection to the Danes.
I will hold until the very last moment.
Meaning what?
Edward will march
and I will promise to join him,
but I will arrive late.
As the Danes attack from the front,
I will attack from the rear.
My army against a fyrd of peasants,
it'll be a slaughter
and my men will survive.
I can almost hear the screams of panic.
Lady, forgive me,
I did not know where else to go.
He believes he can negotiate...
Or is at least considering
the possibility.
The bleeding has stemmed. I hope.
A gut wound is a slow death.
A gut wound can heal.
It will heal.
Lady...
You have my heart.
I fear that I love you.
If I can't say it when I'm dying,
when will I say it?
You're not dying.
Lady, you must act, for mercia.
You must.
Call the men to arms and save us.
It's time.
I am to take you
to the frontier of mercia...
To witness you leaving wessex.
Lord? What is this? A hunting party?
I am an outlaw once again.
To be banished or executed.
Shall we follow you, lord?
Leave Winchester for the Danes?
Lord...
Walk.
What is he doing?
He's standing still, lady.
Uhtred!
You will walk and you will get up
onto your horse!
I am a free man.
I have a letter of pardon.
It bears the king's seal.
- It is written in the king's hand.
- Someone take his tongue.
Does the word of Alfred count for nothing
in Winchester, now that he is gone?
And you are a man who once held a knife
to the king's throat!
Show us one witness who can say
this letter was written willingly,
one witness.
There was no witness.
We are gifting you your life!
You should be grateful
and you shall leave this land in peace!
There will be no peace, lady.
War is coming.
There is a Dane army
marching this very moment.
And I will not abandon
the people of wessex.
Who do you think you are?
Steapa!
Mother, the entire city is watching.
Uhtred speaks the truth.
And you are nothing but smitten.
Lady aelswith!
I cannot let this injustice
to go unchallenged!
If uhtred of bebbanburg claims
to have been made a free man
by king Alfred himself...
We cannot dismiss it so lightly.
Only a king can deny a king.
Wessex has no king.
Wessex has no king!
We have Edward Rex!
It is for the witan to decide who is king.
- Edward is the aetheling.
- He has no authority.
He is Alfred's son and nothing more!
I'm sure the monasteries
are full of Alfred's sons.
Do all bastards have a claim to the crown?
Bishop erkenwald,
you will end this display.
King or not, if Edward believes
the letter of pardon to be untrue...
Then I will leave wessex!
Steapa, you will return the prisoner
to the palace,
this is not the place for such decisions.
This is precisely the place!
Justice must be seen to be done!
Steapa!
Unhand the prisoner.
Though he remains a prisoner...
I will allow lord uhtred to speak.
He has earned that right.
Though you have not, lord,
not yet, you have no authority.
Do you object to the people
bearing witness to justice,
lord aethelwold?
I do not.
Uhtred, the king swore
that you were to die.
Why the change in his heart?
Because he believed
that I deserved his forgiveness.
Is that a boast?
Look to his chronicle.
I am there on every page.
That is a lie!
You are not named, even once!
But I am there!
Unwritten, lady, but I am there!
The warriors of wessex know it.
The Danes know it.
And it is what the king
has told me himself.
I have heard enough.
I am with him from the somerset marshes
to ethandun and all of the battles
that have followed!
We were bonded, him and I.
He was the man that I could never be...
Nor did I wish to be.
He was a man that I loved and despised...
But it was never less
than an honour to serve him.
He was my king!
And he did not wish to go to his god
without granting me what I have earned,
many times over!
My freedom!
But the question remains,
why did he choose not to announce it?
You will remember
my great friend leofric...
A warrior and a Saxon to the bone!
He told me once
that I could never better Alfred...
"Because the bastard thinks", he said.
Perhaps your father chose not to announce
my freedom for this very reason...
So that the people could witness
their new king Edward...
Dispensing justice...
And fairly I hope.
Will you accept the decision
of Edward Rex?
I will. I give you my word.
Lord...
Again, I say and with respect,
the boy does not have the power
to make such a statement!
He is an aetheling and nothing more.
He is no more an heir
to the crown than myself.
Lord...
Decision is yours to make.
My father, king Alfred,
demanded loyalty, unity.
He believed in his god
and doubted those who did not.
A heathen would not be trusted completely
until he had embraced
Alfred's god as his own.
And yet...
It was a heathen he did trust most.
It was the word of uhtred
that he respected most.
Uhtred of bebbanburg...
I find the letter written
by my father to be true...
Alfred's pardon does stand.
You are a free man,
able to choose your own path.
May I ask...
Lord uhtred, may I ask?
Now that you are a free man once more,
where will your path lead?
I would like to know.
Steapa, my sword.
One day, father...
I hope that my path will eventually
lead north, to bebbanburg...
But now, I believe I am needed here.
I will follow Edward Rex!
Cnut!
Swear to the gods that it was aethelwold
who killed ragnar.
It was. I swear.
He must not fall in battle.
If you wish to see ragnar
in the hall of the slain,
then aethelwold must not
just fall to any sword.
I do not understand.
Keep him safe until I'm ready.
Do it for me and for ragnar.
I will. I will keep him safe.
We fight for ragnar!
And for every Dane that has ever fallen
to a Saxon sword!
Yeah!
If the Danes are moving
through east anglia
and towards eastern mercia,
then that land is danelaw.
Their army can only grow.
As before,
we must march out to meet them.
I have spies inside danelaw.
They have confirmed
that they are moving closer.
I have issued an order
for my men at the frontier to retreat.
- Retreat?
- It is good sense, lord.
Every warrior must be made to count.
But how far do I retreat?
Where and when does
mercia make a stand?
Where and when will we be joined
by wessex?
That is to be decided.
I would like to know...
Because wessex appears to be
in a land of chaos and doubt.
Does each of the handful of ealdormen here
stand with Edward?
We do.
Of course, we do.
He is to be king.
Lord sigebriht?
We do.
And what of those who are not here?
Those who have already
hurried back to their halls,
despite knowing there must be talk of war?
They are with us, lord aethelred!
Wessex will not have great numbers,
I am hearing.
We shall be marching
and we shall be marching to fight, lord.
Lord king.
Do not dare believe
there is another option.
Haesten and cnut are men without honour.
They will take your land, your silver,
and the tin crown from your head.
All of you hear me.
Yes, it is likely that the Danes
will have greater numbers,
but this is a battle that we can win.
Though it will take all of us,
every man and every sword
and we will fight with all the guile
and wit that Alfred has instilled.
God is with us.
I shall return to mercia.
Send word of your intentions
and soon, but, I warn you,
I will not fight a battle
that cannot be won.
I will not be seen to send my subjects
into a slaughter.
Do you wish to become a puppet,
lord aethelred?
Send word.
Lord.
He is right.
I am not my father.
When Winchester fell to guthrum,
your father hid himself away
in the marshes, for months.
He hid in fear for his life
and of failure,
but he overcame that fear.
We will find the words
and you will write letters
to each and every ealdorman
and thegn of wessex
and they will answer your call.
They will come.
To where?
Lord.
If we have fewer men,
the very last place we want to fight is
open ground.
Bedanford.
Bedanford is a good distance away.
That is the path they would take.
It is a long march, lord,
but the land could be to our advantage.
It could, lord.
Bedanford it must be.
Then I will do it.
With your help...
I will find the words.
The devil cannot win.
The devil will not win.
I will need a sword or an axe, a shield.
This is a battle I will not watch.
I need to fight, uhtred,
'til I can fight no more.
Lord sigebriht...
You are leaving in the night?
There is an army to raise.
You have been sitting with aethelwold
for some time.
If you are questioning my loyalty, do not.
I am wessex, as was my father
and my grandfather.
But you are not for Edward?
That does not make me a traitor
to my country.
Then you will be there, in battle?
I will.
Wessex will need the men of cent.
A letter will soon find you.
We will be there,
for the good of cent and for wessex.
Yes, for wessex, lord sigebriht.
You are one day Saxon,
the very next day Dane, uhtred.
I have not yet offered you
my condolences for ragnar.
Your brother deserved a warrior's death,
I am sorry you will not see him
in Valhalla.
This is where you belong, aethelwold.
Winchester?
Standing on a stable floor
like a horse's turd.
Will you be riding for Edward?
Like sigebriht, I will be there,
and I will be praying
for a great victory.
For Saxon or for Dane?
Do you care? You belong to neither.
I did once fear you, uhtred,
but now I see you are nothing
but a sword, a lump of metal.
Yes, you have reputation,
but that will fade.
And you will die forgotten and unwritten.
You will go neither to heaven
nor to Valhalla.
This letter from Edward,
it had better be good.
A letter has been sent.
Speaks out to every man in the kingdom
demanding that he answers the call
and joins us on the road to battle.
It says that this will be a battle
that will be spoken of
for lifetimes to come.
It is a battle that no man can ignore,
no man can stand by and watch.
Every man must find a weapon
and every man must fight!
Wessex will always be the light.
And no matter
how heavy our swords become,
we must fight, fight, fight,
and keep on fighting
until the victory is ours!
We march!
I have noticed
aethelwold is not with us.
I wondered why the stench had gone.
No doubt he's making his way
to the Danes.
He may know of bedanford,
he will tell them.
Which is why we're heading towards
the woods, beyond bedanford.
We are?
We assemble at bedanford
as requested in the letter,
but then we march on to attack
the Danes in the woodlands,
a small advantage
for our smaller numbers.
Hmm.
You have the blood kept safe?
I do, lord, always.
And it is blessed.
Thyra's blood?
Yes.
And it will save ragnar's soul?
It will take him from niflheim
to Valhalla, yes...
From hell into heaven.
I must kill the man who killed ragnar,
with a blade marked with ragnar's blood.
Thyra's blood.
It is the same.
Who is this man you will kill?
I do not know.
http://hiqve.com/
So uhtred lives...
Now rides with Edward?
Yes.
You were supposed to kill him.
And I did not.
Could you not find him sleeping?
It barely matters
because wessex is broken.
Half of the ealdormen
will not answer Edward's call
and in one that will, we have an ally.
Sigebriht of cent,
he commands one of the greatest armies
of wessex and he is with us.
He is?
Then he will join us, when?
He will join us in battle.
My plan is that he will arrive
to attack the saxons
from the rear, once battle has begun.
Good.
Jackdaw!
What?
Cnut will be sending out spies
in search of the Saxon camp.
You will follow.
I will?
You will find uhtred
and give him a message.
There's still no word
from lord sigebriht.
I'd hoped some men
would be here already.
They will come, lord.
We must continue on to the woodland
and begin the fight.
We cannot allow them
into open ground.
Then this may well be
the place we die, uhtred.
Or it may well be the place
you become king, lord.
A great king,
like your father at ethandun.
There is nothing
more useless than a dead spy.
Finan?
Jackdaw?
He says he has a message, lord.
I do, lord.
It's from brida.
Say it.
Am I to be spared?
Yes, you will be spared,
but you will not be returning
to the Danes.
Say your message.
She says, "aethelwold", lord.
She says, "do not fail."
How long? Before they come?
They are near.
You are facing death, for certain.
You are wrong, jackdaw. I will not die.
Osferth!
The blood.
Today, I ask you not to fight for Alfred.
I ask you not to fight for Edward,
nor the crown.
But to fight for yourselves
and your forefathers!
They are buried in the soil of wessex
and mercia
and they have become the soil!
They are the land.
And even as I speak,
it is for them, we are fighting!
They're attacking the rear!
Defend the line! Move!
Everyone! Attack! Attack!
- Move!
- Now!
Kill every shit eating Saxon bastard!
There's just too many
of the bastards!
Give no ground!
Where are the mercians!
Uhtred, the line is breaking!
Push back!
Where is sigebriht?
Lord! Horses! Horses!
It is aethelflaed! It is mercia!
They are holding firm!
Aethelwold, when will your man attack?
Soon!
When they are tired! Very soon!
There! There! There he is!
Did I not say?
What position is he taking?
For our forefathers!
And for wessex!
Is he joining our line?
That is your man!
That is your man.
And he's fighting for Edward!
He has betrayed us!
We still have the numbers!
That is your man!
Push! With me!
Fight!
Stand your ground and fight!
We have been betrayed.
They are possessed by devils!
It is lost.
Uhtred, please.
My arm is broken.
I have no way of wielding a sword.
- You have another arm.
- Please.
I will go north, east or west.
I will go to frankia, to Ireland even.
You killed ragnar.
No. No, I didn't. I couldn't.
- You killed him.
- Never.
Admit your guilt.
Uhtred, I am guilty of nothing more
than wanting what is rightly mine.
Admit it.
We are the same, our kingdoms stolen.
You killed my brother!
Admit it to me!
Yes!
Or he would have killed me.
It was a war of sorts between us.
I am not worth it.
I swear you will never see me again.
I will go anywhere,
travel as far away as you wish.
Please.
Please. Please.
Uhtred.
Uhtred, please...
You will need silver to travel.
A ship's fare.
Yes.
I would.
Not much.
You will never see this face again.
You will go to hell.
Uhtred, look.
A bridge.
He's crossing to Valhalla.
He's free.
It will be written
in the Saxon chronicle
that Edward did gain a great victory
over the Danes.
Ensuring he would become
king of wessex.
But other battles lie ahead,
both with the Danes
and within wessex itself.
A king must decide who he can trust...
And who he must discard.
He must understand the minds
of both his enemies and his friends.
He must recognise
that the truth of a man
lies not in the land of his birth,
but in his heart.
A king must be a king on his own terms.
He cannot be his father,
he can only be himself.
The chronicle will grow,
pages will be added,
but uhtred of bebbanburg
will not be mentioned.
Although I too was victorious.
My name is uhtred, son of uhtred.
My name is uhtred ragnarson.
Destiny is all.
http://hiqve.com/