I am Uhtred, son of Uhtred.
A great battle has been won,
but the Saxons
do not find themselves at peace.
You've chosen Mercia
over the Kingdom of Alfred.
In Winchester, Lady Aelswith
has also worked fo her own plan.
You will take a message to the Welsh king.
And the rivalry simmers
with the new queen Aelflaed.
Lady Aelswith was seen visiting
Edward's bastard at the monastery.
What business has she showing kindness
to a whore and her offspring?
Yet my part is done.
I turned away from Saxon conflict
and looked to uniting
with my daughter Stiorra.
I want to make a home
for my children to return to.
Stiorra thrives.
She's now grown and is at Saltwic
with Aelfwynn, Aethelflaed's daughter,
and another child, a mysterious boy.
Who are your family?
I've been told not to answer that.
And though I hope
the gods will allow peace,
I fear ambitions will lead us back fo war.
When we return to Aegelesburg,
I will publicly castrate you!
But the heat of battle
has brought Eardwulf unexpected reward.
Destiny is all!
Open the gate!
Halt!
Make way!
Gently.
Lift him. Careful.
Have no fear. He will recover.
Stop praying for him to die.
- We will be blamed for this.
- Not if we blame him first.
Stiorra!
- Open the doors!
- Perhaps she is sleeping.
Stiorra, wake up. It is your father.
Stay back and name yourselves.
My father calls himself Uhtred
of Bebbanburg. Who are you?
Stiorra, it is us. It really is.
Father has defeated the Danes.
I've come to take you home.
You're lucky I didn't stab you.
The battle was never close.
We would not have left you in danger.
There have been rumors
of retreating fighters.
We made a plan if we were attacked.
- Where's my daughter?
- Aelfwynn!
Aelfwynn, your mother is here!
Mother!
I've missed you!
Oh, I've missed you too!
Aethelstan! You can come out.
Cnut has been sent to hell!
Who's the boy?
I am no one.
I will explain later.
Father, when do we ride home to Coccham?
Tonight?
No, but soon, once the peace is secure.
Please! I'm too old to be stuck here
with children!
Stiorra!
Lord Aldhelm
approaches from the road.
Lady, Aethelred is injured.
Some are saying fatally.
There's a rumor he will not last the week.
- We must go to him.
- Tomorrow.
- These roads are too dangerous at night...
- We must speak to him and the Ealdormen.
No plan has been made for the succession.
Lady, the mood amongst the Ealdormen
is ugly.
Those who survived the massacre
blame Aethelred for deserting them
and denounce your brother
for not coming to their aid.
Does this anger extend to Aethelflaed?
I don't know.
- We ride at first light.
- Lady.
Stiorra, take the children
and secure yourselves.
Open the door to no one but us.
Why? You said the Danes were defeated?
- It is not just the Danes we have to fear.
- What?
How much longer
will I live like a prisoner?
She is young to take on such a burden.
You were betrothed by her age
and suffered worse.
They will remain secure
until the new threats have passed.
We should not leave the children
unprotected any longer.
My men will stay here.
If Aethelred dies, times will be unstable.
An empty throne provokes more trouble
than a weak king.
Our traditions are strong. The Ealdormen
will choose a wise successor.
And what if that successor
seeks to have you removed?
Widows are rarely welcome
in times of change.
- Look at your mother.
- Mercia is my home.
Yet you have no formal protection here,
no son or father to speak for you.
At best, they will send you to a nunnery
and marry your daughter
to the highest bidder.
No! Aelfwynn will not suffer
because of this.
So leave.
And come to Coccham,
where I can protect you both.
Unless you want to live a life
of prayer and chastity.
The Ealdormen will not turn on us.
Battle does not always bring reward,
Aethelflaed.
This much I have learned.
Why do the Ealdormen circle?
How long have I been sleeping?
Since the day of the battle, Lord.
- You fell and injured your head.
- Did we win?
I remember very little.
We did. We returned from East Anglia
and sent the Danes running to the sea.
Who in the name of God
advised that we go to East Anglia?
You did.
Then news came of the invasion
and we returned to protect our people.
After hundreds
had already been slaughtered.
I remember arriving at the battle...
but I...
- Am I to recover?
- I'm assured that you will.
Why do you lie to him
when he is certain to die?
I ease him in his time of need.
More like in his time of judgment.
What is this but punishment
for greed and ambition.
- Burgred.
- He left us to face the Danes alone.
Took all the defenses we had and for what?
A few miles of marshland
barely able to yield a crop?
Burgred.
I will speak
for I have nothing else to lose!
My eldest, pulled from my hands, be...
beheaded.
My youngest and my wife beaten.
Men of honor paraded and humiliated,
and no one came to help us!
And yet we survived.
I will not honor him.
And nor should you, Burgred,
not after all that you've suffered.
Suffice to say that I did all I could
to persuade him to return sooner...
but I failed.
Trust me, the Mercian Guard
feel your loss deeply.
Aldhelm, have you spoken
with the Ealdormen?
There's to be a Witan with the survivors.
Perhaps I will address them.
They can thank me
for bringing Cnut to the field.
- Perhaps you should remain here.
- You do not want me with you?
Times are feverish.
Now is a moment for calm negotiation.
The men who play politics always say that.
And then they come running
for my help.
I demand you do not leave the room.
We are in love, are we not?
Did he mention my mistake?
Does he blame me for our late return?
- He has not spoken of you.
- Good. Perhaps he's forgotten.
If he has, it will not be for long.
- We should leave before his mind repairs.
- No, we will stay until he dies.
There is an opportunity
to regain our influence.
- Brother, no...
- No, listen.
The Mercian Guard are loyal to me,
and the Ealdormen are against him.
Groups are forming as the ravens circle.
- I could be a peacemaker between them.
- Brother, this is madness.
We've played with fire
and found ourselves burnt.
Lady Aethelflaed.
- Are you the woman who is healing him?
- No.
Merely sitting by his side.
My name is Eadith.
I've heard your name.
You must be her brother whose late entry
into battle helped us prevail.
- Our actions were decisive, Lady.
- If a little delayed.
- I'd like to speak to my husband alone.
- Lady.
I command the Mercian Guard.
- I only take orders from Lord Aethelred.
- Lady.
Lady Aethelflaed.
Are you questioning whether
I know the mind of my own husband?
No, of course not. We will withdraw.
Aethelflaed.
I must be dying if you're here.
I am certain
God will restore you to health.
I fear that may not be true.
Priests have prayed over me
as though preparing the final rites.
They will not meet my eye.
And nor will you.
Why have you come?
To revel in my suffering?
I am concerned
about the fate of our daughter,
should you be taken from us.
Without a father to protect her, I wish
to ensure she is not further abused.
- You have treated her most unkindly.
- That's because she is not my daughter.
I may struggle to remember,
but that I know.
So, you must also know the people
regard her as your daughter.
- She is rather fair for a Mercian...
- And that consequently,
they will seek her hand
to support their claim to your title.
So, what is it that you want?
At the very least, you agree
not to betroth her to some heartless fool.
As you were?
Our union brought us misery,
and the people knew it.
It created a crack in Mercia
that did not serve it well.
The Ealdormen of marriageable age
were all slaughtered...
the best of them taken.
There's a danger
dishonorable hands will try to grasp her.
- So?
- So, allow me to choose someone suitable
and I promise you,
this kingdom will thrive.
I agree. You should approve the match.
If only you were as faithful to me
as you are to Mercia.
If you had not treated me with so much
cruelty since our wedding night,
perhaps things could have been
very different between us.
If you fear death, now is the moment
to ask for forgiveness.
Who ordained you confessor?
Then let it be between you and your God.
May he weigh you in the balance
for all you have done.
Aethelflaed!
I know that I have not always
treated you kindly.
For that, I am sorry.
I was younger and more foolish.
And, as for you,
I hope that you can find some comfort.
To live without being loved is a torture.
Which is why you acted
with so much cruelty?
http://hiqve.com/
If I may say, Lord King,
I think this is unwise.
Injured or not, Aethelred will
be held to account for abandoning Mercia.
I say let them drown
in a turmoil of their own making.
Turned out well for us last time,
leaving them to it.
Until the enormous battle.
Indeed, Father Pyrlig
knows how to win battles.
We won the war.
Now we must help bring about the peace.
Mercia does not need any more instability.
- And what about the people of Winchester?
- Indeed.
Have my mother publicly rebuked
for raising King Hywel's army.
She must learn
her interference brings a cost.
- Cenric!
- Lord.
Have our men directed here
to help rebuild the town.
- Lord.
- The Mercians are proud people.
I doubt they will want our help.
We will not ignore their plight again.
Our Lord will not recover!
We should not delay the decision!
We are too few
to pass a decision!
We should wait until other Ealdormen
have arrived from all parts of Mercia!
That is how it has been done
and shall continue!
- But the matter is pressing, Ludeca.
- Yes!
And the next successor is clear.
My younger son's claim is strong
through his uncle...
and he is untainted
by a connection to disloyal Wessex.
Your son is too young, Burgred.
Oh, come on!
If the worst should befall our Kingdom,
we will need a man of wisdom!
Oh, wisdom!
And who would you be thinking of, Ludeca?
He may yet be well enough
to announce his own successor.
We should speak to them.
They talk in circles.
- They will not offer me a chance to speak.
- They can refuse you?
They say I should be
at Aethelred's bedside.
Tell me it is less disordered
than it looks.
I cannot.
There is division. There is anger.
They think Wessex has abandoned them.
And there is talk
that they do not honor the union.
As in Mercia break from Wessex?
Some are saying that, yes.
Then we must appease them. I understand
their frustrations with my husband,
but to sever Saxon unity
would hurt us all.
We must remain united.
Lord Aethelred, I heard you were injured.
Yes, I...
Forgive me if I do not get up.
They told me that...
Has your father sent you?
What...
He will be in his shroud
before the week is out.
You must act decisively to install
someone here before chaos breaks out.
His successor is decided by the Ealdormen.
And who decides what the Ealdormen decide?
I cannot simply march into Mercia
and tell them
how to conduct their affairs.
I've not been as attentive to them
as I should have.
Fortunately, you are already here.
So, no marching is required.
Danish survivors
have been spotted heading east.
Should we send a band to capture them?
No, all forces must come here
to Aegelesburg.
- Are those the Ealdormen?
- Yes.
What do we know of them
and their intentions?
Those two reckon
they have a chance to take the title.
The gray-haired one, Ludeca,
wants the kingdom
and hasn't the balls to fight for it.
The other, Burgred, wants it for his son,
but no one likes him enough to say yes.
Could this son be betrothed
to your niece Lady Aelfwynn?
Bring a successor under your wing
with a family connection?
It worked for your father.
A child on the throne
will not bring security.
Let us meet
with the older Ealdorman Ludeca.
He is likely to be the most reasonable.
First, I must speak with my sister.
Lord?
It appears there might be new turbulence.
Tell the Wessex Guards
to settle within the walls.
Of course.
And that command
to punish the King's mother,
that is an order
you yourself could undertake?
Was punishment what the King commanded?
It's what he wants
but cannot order directly.
He feels the Lady Aelswith
needs... containing.
Brother, you have heard
of my husband's injury?
Yes, I've seen him. Should he die,
what are the plans for the succession?
It is not clear.
The Ealdormen are much diminished.
There is talk of a break from Wessex.
They wish to abandon the alliance
between Wessex and Mercia.
- They feel you have abandoned them.
- That cannot happen.
If Tettenhall has taught us anything,
it is that the two kingdoms
stand stronger when they are together.
- I know...
- I cannot preside over
the breaking of our alliance
and I will not allow
the fracturing of our father's dream!
We will betroth the Lady Aelfwynn
to the successor
and seal the bond between our lands.
In return for the strength
she'll bring to their claim in Mercia,
we will ask they are loyal to Wessex.
I agree with the idea,
but it is not that simple.
The best of the young Ealdormen
have been slaughtered.
There's no one suitable.
Then we will find someone suitable.
Lord King, the men who remain
are not well disposed to you.
- There's no obvious choice.
- Where is the Lady Aelfwynn now?
Safe at Saltwic with my men.
Bring her here
and we will settle the matter.
No! We will settle the matter
and then we will bring her here.
Aegelesburg is volatile.
Surely it is best
if she is with her family.
She's too young to be used as bait.
Find me the right suitor
and we will make haste to arrange a match.
I promise you, brother, this alliance
means as much to me as it does to you.
Bring the Ealdormen to me.
Have no fear, I will resolve this.
Keep an eye on the Ealdormen yourself.
I will find out
how long Edward intends to stay.
My brother is finally trying to enact
my father's will. We should welcome this.
I know, but his authority is under threat
and men under threat
do not always act with wisdom.
Show respect for the fallen of Tettenhall!
Your sacrifice will not be forgotten.
You must pay your respects, Aelfweard.
Come with me.
He is too young to be displayed
before the people.
If he's to send men to war,
as the future king of Wessex,
he must know the consequences.
I will not try and woo King Edward!
I'm not asking you to hump him,
merely ingratiate yourself, as will I.
Why would we try a plan
that has failed before?
Has it failed?
We're in the palace, are we not?
By luck, nothing more.
- You're giving up too easily.
- And you are living a fantasy.
Take this opportunity and escape.
Go back to having nothing?
And avoid the turmoil that will unfold
when Aethelred dies.
I am mistress to a dead king.
You are the favorite of a dead king.
Since when have such people thrived?
Edward is not foolish like Aethelred.
Please, brother,
see what is real and what is not.
For a whore, you lack ambition.
- What did you say?
- Every plan we've made, you've agreed to.
You cannot choose to play and then run,
when it gets a little dangerous.
Aethelflaed.
Edward has ordered all his troops
to Aegelesburg.
He is just being cautious.
Or he's expecting a fight.
There will be no fight,
because we will find a resolution.
Trust him. He knows now
not to put one kingdom before the other.
I am going to Francia
before your insanity drowns us both!
You will go nowhere without my permission!
Is all well, Lady?
Yes.
He is my brother
and it is just a foolish disagreement.
My husband is asking for you.
Attend to him, please.
What kind of a man
treats his sister this way?
Aethelred has soured this place.
Then leave.
You do not have to do this.
If we went with you, they would follow
and drag us back in shame.
Then we go further than they can follow.
North, to the edge of the Danelaw.
Ceaster.
The road to Ceaster is too dangerous.
But if we made it, it has Roman walls.
It can be defended.
I want to, Uhtred...
to live in peace by your side...
to raise my daughter in safety.
Nothing would bring me greater happiness.
But if we left, we could never return.
We cannot let them destroy
all we have fought for.
This is a generous gesture, Lord King.
I know I speak for the people of Mercia
when I say we are grateful
for your men's labor.
Come on, men! Let our friends from Wessex
see our strength!
Ladies of Wessex, don't pout.
Is this intended as a slight?
Oh, no, Lord King.
He merely strives to redeem
his family name
and I, for one, look on it kindly.
His father lost his lands
in very undignified circumstances.
He merely has the drive
of one tainted by disgrace.
Eardwulf?
I believe you pulled me to safety
during the battle.
Yes, Lord King, I did,
something I'd do for any warrior.
Tell me, how are the Mercian Guard
minded on the succession
should your Lord depart this life?
They have no view on it.
They're loyal to the leader of Mercia,
whoever that is.
They have little time for politics, but...
They're good men who respond
to strong leadership.
Well, I thank you for your honesty
and your action on the battlefield.
Lord King!
On behalf of my people, I demand that
you remove your troops from Aegelesburg.
I will not abandon Mercia,
when she is in need.
It's clearly a provocative show
of strength!
I know that you are a man in grief,
but may I suggest you remove yourself
from the King's presence.
Gladly.
I've had my fill of Wessex.
There are ways to make men
Lord of Mercia without the Witan.
You seek to control us...
and I will use them.
I fear these are not vacant threats.
Burgred will do something foolish
to place his son on the throne.
Has he not lost one child already?
Aethelred is fading, Lord.
Time is pressing.
- What do you make of Ludeca?
- He cares deeply for peace, which is good.
But he also cares deeply for Mercia,
which may lead us into conflict in time.
He seems a man of piety and reason.
But how old will he be when
Aelfwynn is of age to produce an heir?
He is not much older than I am
and I am still active in the field.
Aethelflaed will not like it.
With respect, your sister
needs to start doing as she's told.
That man Eardwulf,
he seems respected by his warriors.
He is younger and we know him to be brave.
But he's not an Ealdorman.
Find out what you can about him.
Do not ask me!
What is Edward planning?
I do not know,
and I've had enough of politics!
You got in trouble for raising the Welsh?
You did what was needed.
Did I? Hundreds dead, Mercia in turmoil!
- It turned the tide against the Danes.
- And led to new chaos and new divisions!
Look how the people turn on each other.
This is what happens when kings weaken.
The lines of command are broken
and the people on the streets suffer.
Nonetheless, I need you to find out what
Edward is planning to do with his troops.
No. I'm a man who speaks the truth,
or at my worst, a man who uses his fists.
I was not built for spying and betrayal!
I'll leave you.
Beocca warned me.
He said I might have to choose
between my conscience and my King.
But what if it was a message
to be steadfast that I ignored,
seeking my own glory?
Beocca saw things...
more clearly than the rest of us.
He knew what was coming.
And he knew that you would choose wisely.
Shut up.
Where are you taking these women?
On a pilgrimage
to the shrine of Saint Wite.
We will give thanks for our great victory.
You shall not leave the town.
An order has come from Aegelesburg.
You are to be confined as a punishment
for raising an army
without the King's consent.
And when was this confinement decided?
I've been asked to enact
the will of the King.
Have Lady Aelswith
guarded in the Reading Room.
Do as Cenric orders!
Ignore this girl!
She speaks without authority.
- Look how she trembles!
- Do you defy the will of the King?
You are not the King.
No, but I am anointed Queen.
And in Edward's absence,
my will takes precedence.
I will not fight against it.
I simply ask that a soldier
bring a prayer book to my room,
so that I may reflect.
It will be resolved
with a little will on all sides.
Some wine...
He is honest and good-natured,
but I am troubled by his age.
Should I offer Ludeca my niece...
as a dowry in return
for a renewal of the alliance?
That is, of course, your decision,
but I would follow your instincts.
Look to the hero of the battle.
No more trouble in the taverns, I hope.
We will send men
to water down the ale, Lord King.
Lord Aethelhelm asked me
to join you at the table.
I did indeed, welcome.
Continue.
The Mercian Guard is loyal to him.
It would bring the fighting force
under your command.
As you know, he's keen to restore his name
and he served Aethelred
with complete loyalty.
They even called him The Arse-licker.
I do not want an arse-licker.
I want a man
who will serve all of our interests.
Yes, someone who will work with us
to achieve the peace you need.
But the choice is yours.
Is there more trouble in the town?
Does Burgred gather men?
No.
No, the King just asked I sit beside you.
It's a sign that he wishes to propose
to the Ealdormen and the Mercian Guard
that I should be the successor.
Do I have your loyalty?
The Guard are loyal
to the leader of Mercia.
Good.
Then finally order will be restored.
Thank you for staying by my side.
Your wife has commanded it.
They all wish me dead, do they not?
Why? Did I do something
to offend my people?
All of you, leave me alone... with...
with Eadith.
I remembered your name.
Were we in love?
Though I know
I regret to see you suffer...
I could not in truth say that I loved you.
If I mistreated you, then I am sorry.
Women are used to being mistreated.
We are taught to endure it.
Will you survive without me?
I do not know.
I have survived a great deal.
Tell me the truth. Am I to die?
Prayers are being said for you, yes.
The rumor is that your mind fails
and you will die, Lord.
Then I need a miracle.
And it's not clear that I am owed one.
You could try praying on the relics
of our beloved Saint.
For all your mistakes in Mercia,
gathering his bones was not one of them.
They're in the treasury.
Ask for them to be brought to me.
I will fetch them.
Perhaps they will bring you to yourself.
Or just a scrap of luck.
I fear that I have much to account for.
This reminds me
of when I drank with your father last.
He had just secured victory
at the battle of Ethandun.
The feasting was magnificent.
My father always felt our two lands
thrived when we broke bread together.
Exactly, the unity between us is critical,
both countries, side by side,
equal like brothers.
But with deference to King Edward.
With mutual respect, yes.
We should discuss this unity.
And the betrothal of my niece.
It seems wise to secure one
with the other...
subject, of course,
to the approval of the Ealdormen.
The Ealdormen will do my bidding.
I have them under my control.
Well, as you know,
Lady Aelfwynn is dear to me.
I should like her to be
betrothed to a man I trust.
I agree that seems preferable. Her youth
means that she could be fertile for years.
Yes.
Well, obviously, we want a man
with standing in all parts of Mercia,
someone we might see as a...
I think the phrase you're
searching for is peacemaker.
Someone who can unite
the divisions in Mercia.
Indeed.
A peacemaker for times of peace.
Could you be such a man, Eardwulf?
Eardwulf is not an Ealdorman.
His family was disgraced.
Well, disgrace can be reversed
by royal decree.
If you agree, all we would need
would be the approval of a Witan.
And the Ealdormen will do your bidding,
will they not?
Unless they feel that I am being cheated.
But you would not be.
Because if Eardwulf takes the title,
the land he is owed becomes vacant.
And those could be handed to you
in exchange for your generous support.
To the peacemaker.
Peacemaker.
Lord, I come with news
that will revive you.
Has a successor been chosen?
The King wishes to betroth me
to your daughter.
No.
I will not agree to it.
But her hand with mine
will unite the two kingdoms
and I will be the peacemaker
who saves Mercia.
I promised my wife
I would not act without her.
Without a plan, King Edward will take
your throne and Mercia will be subsumed.
Please, Lord, just trust that I have
Mercia's best interests at heart.
I'm begging you.
Have I not always served you well?
No.
No, you do not.
I cannot place it,
but my stomach tells me that you lie.
Lord...
I have never lied to you.
You have a stench about you.
You are not worthy of my daughter.
You will never rule Mercia.
Get out.
Leave me.
Guards, help!
Help...
Hel...
You did not hear it from me.
I merely left the feast to take a piss.
And if I am asked, I will deny it.
Of course, Pyrlig,
I will not mention your name,
but enough talking in corners,
I'll simply confront him with it...
Edward, tell me there is a mistake,
that you have not broken our agreement
and betrothed my daughter
without my knowledge.
We are simply making plans
should the worst happen.
You agreed Aelfwynn should not be used
as a bargaining piece.
That was before King Edward
struck a bargain.
Ludeca, you cannot be joined to Aelfwynn.
She's a child.
I'm not the suitor. I'm merely someone
trying to prevent chaos.
So, who have you betrothed my daughter to?
Edward,
you swore you'd not betroth her
to a man I despised.
He is a great warrior.
He is a leader of men.
Aethelred still rules here,
and he will not allow this.
I cannot wake him.
I had looked to this moment
for many years.
And now it is here,
why do I feel as if I want to cry?
I think he regretted the pain
he caused you, Lady.
Lord have mercy on his soul and on us all.
Prepare the body
and inform your brother that his betrothal
will take place imminently.
You are to be sister
to the new Lord of Mercia.
- Edward, I will fight this!
- You will not.
You agreed that Aelfwynn's betrothal
was best for Mercia...
I will not have my child
condemned to a life of misery.
- Please, Ludeca, do not accept this plan.
- The plan offers stability.
I believe it to be the best solution.
Eardwulf is not the man
to bring peace. Please.
Lady, begging is unbecoming.
After everything I have done for Mercia...
to have risked my life for this reward,
my child thrown to a man
who will mistreat her?
Perhaps it will teach her
more deference than her mother has.
Ride to Saltwic. Fetch the Lady Aelfwynn.
King Edward would like you to ensure
no force is used.
He is gone.
Aethelred is dead.
Then you are free.
He can torment you no longer.
I wish that were true.
But they seem to be set on destroying me
and all that matters.
I thought Aethelred's death would be
a chance for me to live in peace...
after all this time.
But they cast me aside...
treat my child as a bag of silver.
I will bargain a way out of this...
somehow I will.
We do not need negotiation.
We must alert our allies,
rally them against Eardwulf, if necessary.
It would set the Mercian Fyrd against
the Wessex army. It would be a civil war.
A group of riders have just been sent
by Lord Aethelhelm to Saltwic.
They are to take Aelfwynn.
Edward is not himself.
I will speak with him again.
Go to Ceaster.
Take her somewhere you can protect her.
Lord, I've heard the terrible news.
I will inform the people of the tragedy.
Our traditions will unite us in grief.
May it bring a time of healing for Mercia.
I fear my sister will not mourn him.
With respect, Lord King,
your sister should follow the custom.
She loves Mercia,
but she never loved its leader.
Have Aethelflaed confined
until all this is settled.
If only to save her offending
the Ealdormen by her lack of grief.
- I do not wish to be confined.
- It's a chance to mourn.
May I suggest you make this simple
and comply?
Lady Aelswith...
Good, a man I trust.
Follow my next instructions...
and I am sure you will be well rewarded.
Dip-dip.
Was Bebbanburg as impressive
as we were told as children?
It was more so...
and harder to attack.
Do you think we'll ever return to it,
or is it lost forever?
I don't think I will see it again
in my lifetime.
Perhaps our children will reclaim it.
I do not want children.
I'm tired of their company.
Aelfwynn, come in... now!
Aethelstan...
Men are riding this way.
- Which men?
- I don't know, but they're coming.
Wait!
We have a plan.
Oh? Can I help you? Are you lost?
We're taking Lady Aelfwynn to Aegelesburg.
She's already been taken to Winchester.
Who by?
Erm, I think he called himself Uhtred.
Let us in!
You two, search the grounds.
The rest of you with me.
Nothing here.
Off!
I told you...
she's not here.
Let's go!
Stiorra!
Stiorra?
Stiorra! It is your father!
- Did they hurt you?
- No, it worked.
- I sent them away.
- Good.
Sihtric!
I told you.
- We prepared ourselves for an invasion.
- Lord!
Is it over?
Hey, little trickster you got here.
Where's Aelfwynn?
Death came for Mother
faster than she could ever know.
I've always felt it would come for me,
at speed, from nowhere.
When I saw the horses, Father,
I was prepared, but I wasn't afraid.
Besides, I had faith you'd come for me.
And I was right.
Bread, water and weapons,
the rest we'll find on the road.
Stiorra, get the children on the cart!
We head north towards Ceaster.
Do you think we have enough?
With children and a band of five?
It's only until Aethelflaed
secures agreement from her brother.
All will be made right.
Come. I have alerted the man
who protects you. He's outside the window.
If you think I will fall into a trap,
you are mistaken.
- Please, Lady, I am trying to help you.
- Why would a mistress help a wife?
Because Mercia has wronged us both
and our brothers have turned on us.
Lady, we are not so different.
I have never humped a man for influence.
Just for your country
and political alliance.
I never humped Aethelred willingly
and, believe me, I am paying for it. Go.
I have nothing and no one. You have
silver and men that will help you.
Use them.
Lady.
- Will Eardwulf not kill you for this?
- He will try but he will not succeed.
Go, Lady.
My brother cannot be controlled
and will bring nothing but disaster.
Find Uhtred on the road to Ceaster.
Tell him to meet me at the ruins
of Saint Milburg's Priory.
Do this and I will ensure
you never go penniless.
Aldhelm, do I really abandon Mercia
after everything?
Lady, Mercia has abandoned you.
Go.
http://hiqve.com/