I am Uhtred, son of Uhtred.
After many long and patient years,
I have journeyed north
fo take back my birthright.
- So, Bebbanburg's weakened.
- For now.
I have reunited with my son
and we have begun to forge a bond.
Uhtred, you see these two monks?
They're leaving for Bebbanburg.
- Follow them.
- I will try and do as you need.
And my life-long friend Beocca
has joined us on this mission.
You came to help me be a better father.
Well, there is that.
In Mercia,
Lord Aethelred's military commander
Earawulf has sought an alliance.
I heard there was a Dane
willing to betray his kinsfolk for money.
Perhaps we are fated to work together...
Lord Arse-licker.
Aethelred has now left his stronghold
Aegelesburg undefended and vulnerable.
In Wessex, pressure mounts
on King Edward fo intervene.
- Edward, you must not delay.
- Enough!
I will decide how to respond
to this affront and when!
And while the Saxons are in turmoil...
Go, go, go!
My men and I have Bebbanburg
within our grasp.
But we aren't prepared
for what lies ahead.
You have lost everything...
Osbert.
Put down the bow.
Destiny is all.
My father's weakness
drew you here as it drew me.
He could not hold his lands,
so I have put him out of his misery.
Your men, to the wall.
Go. Be ready.
Move!
Have faith.
Your father has escaped worse than this.
Your father stole these lands from me,
when I was a boy!
And he allowed the Scots to ravage them!
If you want men to call you
the true lord of Bebbanburg...
earn it!
Come down and fight me like a man!
I hold the fortress!
I have no need to fight you.
Wihtgar! Lord!
You do not know me.
I was your father's priest.
I knew his strength and his flaws.
This enmity was of his making!
You have settled that!
Now let us make peace.
You are cousins!
Let this be a new beginning.
Unite against your common foe.
Together, you can defeat the Scots,
secure your land,
for the sake of your children.
For all Saxons.
You have spent too long
in Winchester, priest.
And you have forgotten the north.
We do not seek peace.
You are a stranger here, Uhtred Ragnarson.
But I am wiser than my father.
I will not leave a rival alive
to challenge my birthright...
or my bloodline.
I will kill you, Uhtred.
But first...
- you will watch the death of your boy.
- No!
And all the fools
who followed you to your doom.
Don't! Finan, drop your swords! Now!
This is the end, Uhtred.
Your name will be forgotten.
Uhtred...
Beoccal.
No!
Make for the ship!
They came from the sea gate.
Destroy their ship!
Wihtgar's gone to the walls!
They'll try to sink the ship!
Lord!
No, Lord! No!
You cannot take him!
All the men will die if you do not go now.
Uhtred, please!
Watch out!
Lord, we must go!
Lord, he's gone! Come on!
Aim for their ship!
Untie the ship!
Osferth, untie the ship!
Release!
We need to leave soon!
Get in the boat!
We need to get away!
Osferth, start bailing! Where is Uhtred?
- They're over there!
- We need to go now!
Get going!
- Go!
- Get in the boat!
Lord! We don't have time!
Uhtred, hurry!
They'll try to sink the bastard boat!
- Come on, Father!
- Ready the oars!
- Easy!
- Pull!
Do we follow them?
No. He has failed.
He will not last the night.
Pull!
If we move forward with this,
we stand a chance against Cnut's army.
Father Pyrlig, you have news from Mercia?
Does Cnut march on Wessex?
Cnut has left Aegelesburg
and is camped near Tameworthig.
And Aethelred?
Do we know where he has gone?
Aethelred has ridden into Daneland
and ravages East Anglia.
He has left his lands undefended
and allowed Cnut to shatter the peace.
His ambition is madness.
And Christian men and women in Mercia
are dying for it.
With Aethelred gone,
they expect your aid, Lord King.
Cnut has not set a camp at Tameworthig
to pillage.
He's cleverer than we imagined.
For years, he has watched us
building burhs in Wessex.
This assault is a provocation
to draw us out into the open,
and Cnut has chosen the place
where he means to fight.
There is high ground near Tameworthig.
If he waits there and we come to him,
he will defeat us.
We must fight him, Lord King.
- Mercia burns like a lighted fart.
- That is Aethelred's responsibility.
Lord King.
We have delayed too long already.
When do you ride?
My people suffer, Edward, men who fought
alongside Wessex many times.
I know it!
But you ask me to risk ten sons of Wessex
to save ten sons of Mercia.
These are my people.
I will not send them to be slaughtered
while Cnut sets the terms of the battle!
- And your duty to your allies, my Lord?
- I am King of Wessex.
I am sworn to protect it.
Your father was crowned King of Wessex,
but he always sought
to unite the Christian peoples.
In spirit, he was King of all Saxons.
My father is not here.
Aethelred must return.
Father Pyrlig, you will dispatch
messengers to find him.
Steapa will ready our guards.
When our armies are united,
we will face Cnut together.
By the time Aethelred returns,
there will be no Mercia to defend.
This is your decision?
It is.
You will not oppose it.
Edward!
The Ealdormen remain in Aegelesburg?
- Any that were not killed in the attack.
- Aethelflaed...
Edward betrays his father's memory.
He acts in the interests of Wessex.
Perhaps my father would've done the same.
Never!
I am Mercian.
I was married to Alfred
to knit the two kingdoms together,
as you were to Aethelred.
If Mercia falls, then Wessex
stands alone against the Danes.
My duty is now to Mercia, not Wessex.
If there is anything I can do,
I must do it.
I must go to Aegelesburg
to summon the Mercian fyrds.
Edward will see this
as defiance... betrayal.
Edward is not my king.
And you will throw yourself
into the path of the Danes?
Aethelflaed, you are a target!
You will be killed...
or held for ransom
and not for the first time!
There is no one else to go.
You must not tell Edward I am gone
until I have left Winchester.
Promise me.
Then you must choose a place
for the fyrds to assemble.
There is a valley in Tettenhall,
where lesser numbers might stand a chance.
This is where
you must force the Danes to fight.
The fyrds will not be enough.
I will need Edward's aid.
When you're gone, I will speak to him.
Your brother will not abandon you.
Edward will be there.
- What do you have for me, Bjorgulf?
- The head of a Saxon turd.
So, another village burns in Mercia!
The smell of Saxon blood
stiffens our warriors for battle!
But I hope not your cock.
I have no choice here,
but to act the part of his whore.
He tries to dress me
to make me his property.
I swear, I detest the man.
Come with me. I have news
that will put the King in better spirits.
I gave you a gift.
Why are you not wearing it?
Am I not beautiful enough without it?
On the surface.
What do you want?
For you, Lord King.
Ripped from the hands
of an ugly Dane named Ulf.
We've taken Lindcylne. Word will spread.
And Edward will hear of it.
He will hear that your kingdom
grows greater than Wessex.
That you have taken
what Alfred never could.
While Edward looks like
a weak and timid boy.
You have done well, Eardwulf.
You will be rewarded.
I only ask that I retain command
of your armies, Lord King.
And to restore my family's name.
To lift your decree that every generation
be born into disgrace.
Take all of East Anglia
and I shall consider it.
You are generous, Lord King.
My brother and I will withdraw
to pray for your swift victory.
You may go.
For now.
Lord?
Uhtred, the men are tired and hungry.
There's nothing here. We must move on.
Where shall we go?
Somewhere with a fire,
an alehouse or a whorehouse
that would raise the spirits, eh?
I must go back. I must retrieve his body.
No, Uhtred, you cannot.
Retrieving his body means nothing now.
His journey in this world has ended.
He is left with thieves and traitors!
He should lie beside Thyra
where his friends can grieve.
Instead, I led him to die among strangers.
I've lost every family I had.
Beocca was always there...
the only constant.
Without Beocca, I have no home.
His death is on my hands. I failed him.
No.
Bless you, Sihtric.
Blessings.
Where is Uhtred?
He walks alone.
I fear his spirit is broken.
The day Uhtred is broken is the day
you grow hair down there, Osferth.
It'll never come.
Now, he lost a friend and grieves him...
as we all do.
He told me we must return south.
Well, come on. We'll need horses
and provisions for the journey.
Buy what you can.
There's a village beyond the ridge.
Try not to spend it all on women.
Frigga, tell me I'm not deceived...
that the curse is lifted.
He grows inside me.
- Any word of the Saxon armies?
- Not yet.
We will burn every village in Mercia
until Edward comes to fight.
There's a limit to the suffering
the boy king can allow
his fellow Christians to bear...
and we will exceed it.
- Your sons should be here to see this.
- Haesten will keep them safe.
All my children will inherit everything.
And I will slaughter Edward
and Aethelred's armies here.
And when the kings are dead,
we will sit together on Alfred's throne.
That is my promise to you.
Do it for Ragnar.
We do this in his memory.
For Ragnar.
Lady Aelswith.
Lord Aethelhelm.
You have heard? Cnut burns villages
from Tofeceaster to Fagranford.
He defiles our holy places
and slaughters our priests.
Because I wait for the right moment,
it does not mean I do not care.
- Edward, I must talk...
- Lady.
Yes.
My daughter
called at the nunnery today.
You said the Lady Aethelflaed
had withdrawn there for reflection?
She had.
Then she misled you.
She's not there.
Concerned for your sister...
I asked Steapa to make further inquiries.
The Lady was seen leaving Winchester.
Where is Aethelflaed?
Mother!
Where has she gone?
She has gone to Mercia.
This cannot be true.
I am sorry, Edward, but what was I to do?
I am of Mercia.
And by marriage, so is Aethelflaed.
We could not leave the people to die.
She defied me...
and you defy me.
I only wish to counsel you to follow
the Christian path, as I did your father.
You think I do not fear my God?
I know you have true faith.
But the burden of kingship is heavy.
I have experience, Edward. I can share it.
I have given instructions
that we will fight Cnut on our terms,
when we are prepared
and have the best chance of victory!
Now Aethelflaed has walked
directly into Cnut's trap!
She puts the men of Wessex
and all the Christian kingdoms at risk!
I demand you call her back.
You will show loyalty to your king.
I cannot swear loyalty
to a plan that is misguided!
Aethelflaed will summon
the Mercian fyrds to Tettenhall.
You must join her.
Lord, forgive my sins
for they are all very grave.
Whoever fears you, Lord God, knows that is
your will and you'll show that man just...
Stop this nonsense!
I pray for Father Beocca.
Please allow the soul of Father Beocca
to rise to heaven...
Get up!
You think he needs your words, hm?
Do you think I need them?
I know you blame me for his death.
I am told your God gives mercy.
Where is he?
I've never seen him.
It is not my God that you hate...
but the fact that I am not you.
Are you all right?
He does not want me!
You know, I will return to the church.
And that's what you want, is it?
To run away?
I remind him of his defeat...
and of Father Beocca's sacrifice.
Oh! The blindness of youth.
Uhtred is a warrior and a father.
It was his job to save you
and he could not. That's what eats at him.
As a warrior perhaps, but not as a father.
- He has never been a father.
- Because he was absent?
Do you know how many battles he's fought?
How many times he's sworn oaths
and risked his life
for your Christian kings at the cost
of his own hopes and comfort?
I met your father as a slave,
when we had... nothing.
Now, you look at what you lack,
not what he has given to others.
He fights for Bebbanburg,
not for himself, but for you...
to give you the legacy he never had.
I swear...
he is a great man...
and his blood runs in your veins.
You should be proud to follow him.
The men can no longer go on
wandering in the wilderness like this.
They will need silver.
There'll be opportunity to earn it.
We're warriors.
There's always battles to fight.
To fight, men need a lord who can
lead them into battle without fear.
I'm tired.
My reputation is waning.
These men depend on you.
I know what you do, Finan.
I know what you say to them.
I'm finished with battles.
I thought that my destiny
was to return to my home.
I have not.
I have lost my lands.
I've lost my name.
I can no longer call myself
Uhtred of Bebbanburg.
I am nothing.
If men want to leave me,
you should let them go.
I can no longer be their lord.
Is there word of Aethelflaed?
No.
She forces my hand.
This is not the vision of England
that I swore to protect.
Yet, these events
could work to your advantage...
and serve your father's vision.
Let the Lord of Mercia
return to defend his wife and lands.
They say Aethelred has 400 men
in East Anglia, no match for Cnut's.
So, the battle will remove the problem
of King Aethelred.
Once Aethelred is gone...
you will defeat Cnut...
and unite the kingdoms.
Edward will fulfill Alfred's dream.
By sacrificing Mercia?
And my sister?
Your father knew that uniting the kingdoms
could not come without a cost.
And your sister...
has chosen her own fate.
http://hiqve.com/
Beocca would not want you
to starve or see you destroyed by grief.
He held me on the ramparts,
when Earl Ragnar rode to Bebbanburg
with the head of my brother.
When my father named me Uhtred
in his stead
and told me to die for Bebbanburg...
Beocca was at my side.
He put me into the water to baptize me.
He held me underneath it for so long
I nearly drowned
while he prayed to his God.
He saved my life as a boy...
and as a man...
many times.
He was like a father.
Hey, it's all right.
He'll have no grave...
no place blessed by his god.
He is with God now.
And with your sister. He is at... peace.
Hm? I'm sure he'd be touched
how you mourn for him
while we're stuck in the middle
of nowhere. But if he were here now,
he would tell you this is not the end.
We will gather more men.
We will return with an army
and batter down the gates.
Yeah.
What brings you here?
I ride from Wessex
with a message from King Edward.
You may tell it to me.
I have instructions to deliver it
to Lord Aethelred and him only.
I command the King's Guard.
No doubt you've heard stories about
the King, about his delicate temperament.
I'm telling you he does not wish to be
disturbed, so, if you want to test it...
Cnut's armies have attacked Mercia.
The Lord's estate has fallen.
The heart of Mercia is gone.
They've taken everything?
Danes.
- It is Haesten.
- Where is he going?
He's with his kinfolk.
He'll not want to fight.
Uhtred Ragnarson!
I thought I could
smell something rotten on the air!
We should kill him now, Lord,
while we have the chance.
I've had enough of fighting Danes,
even weasels like Haesten.
Uhtred and his pretty boys...
looking so sad and far from home.
Why?
It's none of your concern. Let us pass
and I will not cut off your head.
I suppose, once more,
you ride out to save the Lady Aethelflaed.
Continue if you like, Uhtred.
It seems fate has brought us
together again.
Your men look like ragged dogs
in need of meat and we have plenty.
We camp here tonight.
Join us.
Haesten's men say Cnut and Brida
have attacked Mercia.
I knew they did not sail for Irland.
Edward and Aethelred will need us now.
I owe them nothing.
And Aethelflaed?
It is true, I fear for her.
Uhtred.
Join me.
There was a rumor you had gone north
to regain your lands.
Are you here with your tail
between your legs?
Your men say the Danes have gone to war,
yet you are here, playing nursemaid.
What happened, Haesten?
Have they cut off your balls?
What can I say?
I'm a family man.
I do not see your fat wife.
She died.
Oh, did she?
As you know, I once had the desire
to claim Mercia and Wessex for my own.
But that did not go well for me.
And now, like you, Uhtred,
I only want a woman to hump
and a piece of land to call my own.
I had both, in Skade and Beamfleot...
until you took them away from me.
How is Aethelflaed?
In my experience, the bitch
has never known when to lie down.
No doubt she'll be riding into battle
with Cnut...
with her silly husband
and her pretty brother.
And you have always been there
to save her, Uhtred.
But not now.
She does not need me.
That's not what I heard.
How is she?
To bed?
I imagine she squeals, like a big fat pig.
Stop it!
Come on, Uhtred!
We were having a nice dinner.
Of course, I would
slit her throat after she'd been ridden!
Wait, Uhtred.
She's too well used to fight over.
Now I will kill you!
Wait, wait, wait!
There is something I can give you.
The name of the man that killed Ragnar...
- Aethelwold!
- No.
He held the dagger,
but another whispered poison into his ear.
Let me live... and I'll tell you
who gave the command.
Speak.
Cnut.
He wanted to lead the Danes...
and he wanted Ragnar's woman
who used to be yours.
He told Aethelwold
that Ragnar would kill him.
He guided the blade...
into Ragnar's heart.
These are Cnut's sons...
You can go.
You will leave Cnut's bastards behind.
I'm tired of the red-headed runts.
You can take them.
- Of course Cnut will hear of this.
- I said go!
Finan!
- Lord.
- Tie them up!
- Let go!
- Come on.
Jesus!
No, no, no! Where are you going?
Where are you going?
Cnut's sons?
I thought you did not want to be
a part of this war.
Brother?
What have you done?
I had to or all is lost.
The rider came from Wessex.
Edward sends word to Aethelred.
Cnut did not sail to Irland.
The Danes have sacked Aegelesburg
and taken Mercia.
Then you were tricked.
Yes, the Dane Haesten
gave me false information.
And Aethelred left Mercia
undefended upon my advice.
You see now
why he cannot receive this message.
But if Aethelred loses Mercia,
then we lose our position!
You think I do not see that?
Do you think
I can bear to return to nothing?
But there is benefit
in delaying our return.
If the Lady Aethelflaed throws herself
into the path of the Danes,
it will leave a path open for you.
I've no need of a husband
who used to be king!
You must tell Aethelred the truth
and persuade him to defend his kingdom.
If I tell him the truth,
he will kill me.
I will do all I can to soften the blow.
Leave us.
Be careful, lady.
Like you...
I'm tired of caution.
What will you do with the boys?
We will take them
to Aethelflaed in Mercia.
I remember watching you
ride out from Winchester...
before you fought
at the battle of Fearnham.
I remember.
Your mother was there.
It was the last time I saw her.
I still see her...
in my dreams.
Gisela.
But then I wake and she's gone again.
I feel her loss also...
every day.
That day I asked her why you left us.
And she said you fought,
because you believed in a cause...
not for God, or the gods...
or for Saxons, or for Danes.
But to keep safe the people that you love.
She said that is why you will always have
the strength to stand up when others fall
and to go on when those around you
say it is hopeless.
It is why these men love you...
and will follow you wherever you go.
As will I.
Creoda.
Lady Aethelflaed.
How many remain here?
Where is the king?
We will find you food.
Search for survivors and bring them here.
We should not delay here.
The Danes could return.
I know.
I have summoned the Mercian fyrds.
They are marching to Tettenhall.
Cnut will pay for this bloodshed.
My husband valued loyalty.
I have been loyal.
- At least as far as I can remember.
- But he was also practical.
If he saw a person
make the wrong decision...
he took action to correct it.
Edward's rule in Wessex is vulnerable...
and Mercia has been left undefended
by its king.
Wessex needs our protection...
and the support
of all our Christian allies.
You will take a message
to the Welsh king, Hywel.
Lady, you are Edward's kin.
If I disobey him,
- he will string me up in the marketplace!
- I know what I ask.
But you have sworn an oath to God, Father.
What use is your mortal life
if you disobey your conscience
for fear of man's vengeance?
You and I must protect the faith,
Father Pyrlig.
Aethelflaed is expecting an army.
We must deliver one.
So, the Lady Aethelflaed
has returned to Mercia.
Do you think she's alone?
If she is, the rest of the Saxons
will not be far behind.
Take her and they are in our power.
You will find Aethelflaed
and you will bring her to me.
Horsemen!
- Wake the Lady Aethelflaed now.
- Lord.
Uhtred!
What are you doing here?
You two, get those boys off the horses.
Why are you not at Bebbanburg?
What happened?
Where are the guards?
You see all we have.
Uhtred, who are those boys?
You should not be here without a guard.
Where should I be?
Decorating Edward's palace?
My place is in Mercia!
What have you done, Uhtred?
They are Cnut's heirs.
Then Cnut will hear of this
and he will come for you.
So, you must get the boys to your armies.
Where are they?
Aethelred is in East Anglia
with his men.
I have ordered the Mercian fyrd
to Tettenhall,
and I believe Edward will meet us there,
then we will summon Cnut to fight.
So, you've put yourself in danger.
I do not know if Aethelred is coming
and I had to force Edward's hand.
You should not be here undefended. Finan.
- Lord.
- We leave at first light.
Aldhelm, prepare the survivors.
We march to Tettenhall at dawn.
Every man must be put to watch.
Positions.
Every man to the ramparts!
Uhtred, what happened at Bebbanburg?
http://hiqve.com/