I am Uhtred, son of Uhtred.
My birthright Bebbanburg
was cruelly taken by my Uncle Aelfric.
My greatest fighters...
or the most fearful?
His men desert him
and the Scots send raiders,
who weaken those that remain.
How many did we lose this time?
The time is right for me
fo take back what is mine.
Give me 100 men. It will take a week.
Two hundred, I can take it in a day.
But the new king, Edward, has fallen
under the influence of Lord Aethelhelm.
I'm no longer the boy
who can be bent to your will!
Aethelred of Mercia looks fo
Bebbanburg for a different purpose.
I'm collecting all the bones
of our beloved saint as a good omen
to signal to the Mercian people that
I shall restore their lands to greatness.
He has sent holy men there
to bargain for an ancient relic.
I have also sought out the help
of a Christian.
Hello, Father.
My son, who was taken by Alfred
and raised with a devout faith.
The Mercian commander Eardwulf
has traveled fo East Anglia
to meet with Haesten.
Did you see them leave?
Yes. They're dismantling
their camp and packing their boats.
And now Aethelred looks
to conquer Daneland
as well as Eardwulfs sister.
The feelings that Aethelflaed
and I have always held
can no longer be contained.
But for now, my duty draws me
fo the north once again.
To Bebbanburg!
Destiny is all!
Ran can be a vixen.
This should settle her.
Ran is pagan lies.
I pity you for believing it.
- Finan, give him something to do.
- Yes, Lord!
Oh, God. Whoa.
Hey! You can empty this.
Tell me the truth.
- Am I the bait?
- For what?
In the plan you are hiding from me.
- Am I the bait?
- Nothing is hidden from you.
We are tracking monks
who have entry to Bebbanburg.
You will befriend them, enter Bebbanburg
and open the sea gate to us.
I think you have another reason
for dragging me into your revenge.
Yes, so you may win honor and reputation.
The only reputation that matters
is my standing with God.
You cannot force a boy to be a warrior.
My blood runs within his veins.
Why can he not see that?
Because your blood
is that of a stubborn bastard!
- Our Father...
- Who do you pray for, boy?
The men you will slaughter.
You seem to take things
when you want them.
When you do, show mercy.
To my Uncle Aelfric,
who spent a lifetime wishing me dead?
- There is a power in forgiveness.
- Good.
Then you may use it to forgive me.
He continues to sign himself
King of Mercia,
and now we hear he leads troops
out of Aegelesburg.
Aethelred has always been ambitious.
- Do you know where he's gone?
- My husband doesn't inform me of anything.
I know he is seeking the bones
of St. Oswald.
Edward, that is grave.
If he is seeking St. Oswald,
he is seeking to break from Wessex.
Many Mercians believe
that uniting the body of the saint
will restore their land to greatness.
Yes, but the people want peace, not war.
Still, it is a signal of intention.
Or a ploy to pander
to the simple folk of Mercia.
The people of Mercia are not simple.
Well, whatever it is he is doing...
do not allow yourself to be drawn in.
The weak should not be allowed
to set terms.
If you do not play, he cannot win.
Leave childishness to the little children.
Ah. Here he is,
the future King of all the realm.
See how nimble he is!
That's a great swordsman in the making!
Yes, indeed.
- Lady.
- Lord.
Yes, and he is a child
of great authority, too.
You should have seen the way he kicked
Steapa to make his displeasure known.
A boy of many talents.
Come with me.
I want to show you
a book of your grandfather's.
Do not pester the boy with Latin.
He is to be a king, not a clerk.
The men of Wessex are fighters.
Rule the sword and rule the land.
He digs away at all that is precious.
Yes, it is troubling...
as are my husband's intentions.
I will ask Aldhelm to make inquiries.
Father Pyrlig?
Bring Father Beocca to me.
I was a little unjust with him...
and wish to ask his advice
on a certain person.
Father Beocca has left Winchester, Lady.
He felt there was nothing left here
for him. I doubt he will ever return.
And so our allies abandon us.
Lady, you asked for him to be removed.
Yes.
Yes, I suppose I did.
Just as I asked my son to be married
to that vain, silly girl.
Why the Lord guided me this way,
I cannot fathom.
Maybe the Lord didn't.
Any path I chose was to secure
the country my husband loved.
And how well did that work, Lady?
http://hiqve.com/
A pathetic hoard,
most of them drunk or senile.
The Scots will laugh.
I cannot hold them off with this!
We need more warriors.
I have been trying, Lord.
The slaver can get us trained men,
but he wants 10,000.
Ten thousand would empty the treasury.
What good is a fortress without silver?
Lord, we must sell
the heart of Saint Oswald.
Time is moving against us.
We can only sustain these attacks
from the Scots for so long.
He's desperate for it, you say, Aethelred?
This is what I have heard.
The monks he dispatched
will arrive here soon.
Then we shall bleed silver from him
and buy the men.
So, where do we start?
Where do you look for monks
in a place like this?
- St. Colman's?
- The whorehouse!
That's it. I'm staying on the boat.
It's not safe for you to be alone
this deep within Danelaw.
- Come.
- Then I will pray for salvation.
I will stay with him, keep us both safe.
- They do not love a priest in Grimesby.
- Thank you, Father.
To the whorehouse then!
You misjudge your father,
you know.
He's not the bloodthirsty heathen
you take him for.
Thou shalt not kill, Father Beocca.
- Or are you rusty on the scripture?
- I know the teaching.
But I also know Aelfric.
And having some years on you,
I also know...
that sometimes
one must do wrong to do right.
Aelfric tried to kill a child
for no gain but wooden walls.
And for that, he wrenched a boy
from his Christian life...
delivered him to the heathens
and damned his soul to all eternity.
Uhtred is avenging
a great wrong done to him.
Help him in his mission
and you will be helping...
Helping him return to a life
of Christian piety?
No.
- Not that, but...
- There is a chance.
All sinners can repent.
Well, we shall see.
Come on.
Grimesby seems like a lovely place.
I hear the oysters are delicious.
Sihtric, don't make eye contact.
- What's your business here?
- We're traders.
We're taking pelts to Frankia.
Really?
Well, you keep trouble out of my alehouse,
agreed?
Hey, we're just hungry for some food,
nothing more.
And do you have women? He needs a woman.
We're not that sort of alehouse.
Finan.
She's yours until nightfall.
If you're quick, you can both get a turn.
He'll certainly be quick.
Hey, why do I always
have to pretend to be the virgin?
Because no one would
believe I am the virgin.
Harder, like your sister does it.
Hit it.
Lead me out to the darkness, Lord.
And let this sin...
- I'm a virgin in that, Lord.
- I'm sure you are, Osferth.
We've found our monks.
Oi, watching costs extra.
Harder!
Traveling overnight, all that way
in the saddle with a red raw ass,
a good thing they like pain!
It takes six days to get to Bebbanburg
on the coast road.
They'll get there
before Ascension.
I'm a good Christian boy, Lord.
You should not arrive before them.
The rocks around Bebbanburg
do not treat ships kindly.
So, we wait here and enjoy the atmosphere?
Uhtred, see these two monks?
They're the ones we've been searching for.
They're leaving for Bebbanburg.
Follow them.
It's our strongest chance
of getting into the fortress.
- I can't simply follow...
- If there were, I would not ask.
My men have been there recently.
They would be recognized.
- So, I am the sacrificial lamb...
- You are our greatest hope.
Do not do this for me.
Do it for your descendants.
Whatever I take will one day be yours.
I'm not the warrior
you seem to mistake me for.
Why do you have this faith in me?
Because I know that
the spirit of our family is within you.
That will give you a strength
that you do not know yet.
I will try and do as you need,
but I will not kill a man.
That is all I want.
Three pieces of silver says he runs home.
- Take this horse.
- Uhtred.
Ride the road north, close to the shore.
Leave now,
so you can be ahead of the monks.
Find them. Join them.
- Lord!
- I would not send you to be slaughtered.
When I see you signal,
I will approach the sea gate.
He'll be looked after.
He's blessed, as are you.
All right, come on.
Uhtred.
Try it on.
I will, when you leave.
No. I had it made for you.
I want to see it now.
Lord, I will not undress before you.
- I am a woman from a noble family.
- Whose father disgraced...
Whose father
was unfairly shamed for no reason
other than falling
from the Ealdormen's favor.
Lady, enough of this game.
You have no good reason to deny me.
I act simply for the good of your soul.
You have a wife.
You are right.
I see that now.
I should make myself a widower
and marry you.
Is that not what you want?
Along with all of these silks and furs.
Just... a good life...
for a girl who has nothing.
Am I being very unfair?
Have I misjudged your Christian soul?
It can all be arranged.
- Did you do the deed?
- No.
Drag it out much longer,
he'll lose interest.
How wrong you are.
He's not losing interest.
He's threatening to have
Lady Aethelflaed killed,
so that he may marry me.
That is good news!
No, it is not! I would have the blood
of Alfred's daughter on my hands.
It seems like a fair exchange.
Married to a man
who kills those who displease him?
- Again, it seems like...
- He is volatile and we must be careful.
Promise me, if he asks you to attack
Lady Aethelflaed, you will refuse.
I will never defy the wishes
of King Aethelred.
And nor should you.
We will rest here
and attack at first light.
Catch the Mercians sleeping in their beds.
How far is Aegelesburg?
- Close enough to surprise them.
- Then this is where I say goodbye.
We camp here tonight,
march at dawn!
You are certain
we cannot tempt you to battle?
I have no interest in fighting,
only women and silver.
Because you have to pay women
to hump them?
Better than reeling them in with lies.
Fair. But everything I did
allowed the Danes to triumph.
You will miss a great gathering
of armies, Haesten.
Edward is honor-bound to defend
the land of his sister and mother.
Aethelred's death
will force swift retaliation.
We will ride into Mercia in a fury
and will force them to a battle place
where we have the advantage.
Wessex, Mercians, all Christians.
This will bring them together.
Then you will have united the Saxons.
Alfred would be very proud.
Cnut! Let's go.
Boys, come here.
I want you to go with our friend Haesten.
He will take you north
until our campaign is over.
Should they not witness the battle?
I know it's dangerous but...
There will be battles to come.
Today, they are too young.
Haesten, attend to them
and teach them nothing you know.
Come, boys, let's get you ready.
The shit loves his offspring.
How did he draw you to him?
We made a bond in blood.
If you ever get bored
of the ugly bastard...
you know, I have fathered ten children.
- That is of no use to me.
- No?
No...
because you carry his pup!
I can tell by the tits.
If you tell him this
before I fight the Saxons...
I will cut off your balls
and feed them to you.
I'm overjoyed for you, Brida.
The world needs more little Cnuts.
Brida!
Come.
Rest tonight. Prepare yourselves.
There will be many sleepless nights ahead!
But, at daybreak,
we shall strike and blood will run!
Mercia will burn!
Bring me Aethelred!
Where is he?
Where's your Lord?
Next!
Are there any more?
Could they be mercenaries...
come to help defend us?
A donation from the slaver?
Offering reinforcements
from the goodness of his heart?
Well, perhaps they will turn away.
Or they are Scots, returning for a fight.
There is one choice,
though it sickens me to say it.
Pay them to go away.
So they can return again
and we pay them more?
Why not just beg them
to make us their vassals?
I did not say it was a good choice.
Send men out to speak with them.
If they return with heads
on their shoulders,
we know that the Scots might negotiate.
I shall go myself.
I am sick of sending men to slaughter.
Which is why you will never lead, Aidan.
Open the gate.
Alert Lord Aelfric.
He'll want to see this.
We heard you were drowned.
We were assured.
They said there was no hope.
I nearly did drown, Father.
I believed it was my punishment
for sending you away.
No punishment.
Just a moment to learn
how much I wanted to live...
and return to you and Bebbanburg.
I thought my legacy was lost forever.
I assure you,
your descendants will thrive.
When I got word you were under attack,
I seized the moment.
I've brought warriors...
men I've collected
from every corner of the known world.
Strong men, loyal men.
Bebbanburg is saved.
As magnificent as ever it was.
Indeed... if it is real and not a dream.
It is real enough.
- We need get no closer at this point.
- Lord!
Drop the sail!
Row inland
and keep under the shadow of the cliff.
How long do we wait
for your son to send a sign?
Until it comes.
It is all the will of the gods now.
Is this some plan
to become a saint?
It is preparation
for the royal consecration.
Becoming Queen
is a now a holy rite?
The insult of it.
I take it
this was also Lord Aethelhelm's idea.
Yes. He is quiet,
but his ambitions for his family grow.
He obsesses over the aetheling
and pushes me aside.
Had I known what sort of man he was,
I would've selected
a different bride for your brother.
What does the King say?
Edward cherishes peace...
both within Wessex and within the palace.
So, I must accept
when I am no longer wanted.
She feels my father's loss.
As do we all.
I would like 17 candles lit on my behalf.
One at each shrine
and no mumbling in the prayers.
The Lord wants to hear your full hearts.
Seventeen?
Is something on your conscience, Lady?
Many things. I fear I've allowed
too much to change in the palace.
Tell me, the young Centish lady,
Ecgwynn...
The girl who married your son in secret?
Yes.
What do you know of her present situation?
She took holy orders,
when her marriage was forcibly annulled.
And, from what I've heard,
she's very unhappy.
Well, the cloistered life
may not suit a simple girl.
She was forbidden from seeing
the two children she bore your son.
Her daughter she sees occasionally,
but her son...
she's not looked on
since he was taken from her arms.
That seems a cruel punishment.
For the crime of loving Edward
and Edward loving her, yes.
You and Beocca are right
to question my mistreatment of her.
I would like to make amends,
in a small way.
- Where is her son now?
- He lives in a monastery.
So, he has a love of God...
but not that of a mother.
An agony I would not want for my own son.
- I would like to see them both.
- I can have it arranged.
I am presuming you do not want
anyone else to know.
It would put the boy in danger.
We both know that.
Send scouts to look for a battle place.
Make sure the grain stores are emptied
and no food remains.
Gut this palace
before the other Saxons retaliate!
- Did you see the Ealdormen?
- I did.
You're inventive in your cruelty.
Have you found Aethelred?
Not yet. I'm just enjoying his bed.
Would you like to join me?
What are you reading, child?
You are Aethelstan, are you not?
Yes.
Who are your family, Aethelstan?
I've been told not to answer that.
Indeed. That is probably wise.
Are you an abbess, Lady?
No. I am... a friend.
Though many great abbesses feel
I could have been one of their number.
Come with me, Aethelstan.
A lady wants to meet you.
Go to the garden.
- Oh, Lord help us! It is a beggar.
- Don't look at him. Ignore him.
I cannot.
He's heading straight for us.
Travelers!
He looks insane!
Be wary!
Ignore him.
Travelers, this road
is full of murderous thieves!
- Be careful, my brothers in Christ!
- Why do you call us brothers, madman?
- Because I am one of your number.
- You look a beggar.
No! I am a deacon,
cruelly kidnapped from his church.
A boy whose mind is spent
and life is ebbing!
- Let me ride with you.
- We should move on.
In the name of the Virgin,
there are bandits on this road!
Abandon me and I shall perish
and lie here unburied!
Come on.
Please, did Christ not pity the leper?
Please, brothers.
I know about your sins in Grimesby.
Don't let me speak of it to your abbot.
What do you want?
Nothing but traveling companions.
I swear to it, I mean you no harm.
- Are you any good in a fight?
- No.
Good, they can kill you while we escape.
Are you the kind soul
who arranged this meeting?
I am.
Do I know you, madam?
Content yourself with knowing that I am
a mother who feels for your plight.
Then I thank you. To see him even briefly
heals a wounded heart...
for both of us.
You have shown us a great mercy.
Tell me...
am I still out of favor
to the Lady Aelswith?
Lady Aelswith disfavored no one.
She simply chose
what was best for her son...
as you will want the best for yours.
What is best for my son
is what he once had,
a mother and a father living in happiness.
Perhaps. What is done is done.
But yes, it would be foolish for him
to be raised without a woman's nurture.
Men raised by men turn savage.
So we must ensure
there is always a lady to guide him...
when he is permanently moved
to somewhere more secure.
Why must he be moved?
There is concern
that he could be in danger in Wessex.
But rest assured,
he will be well-protected.
But I am afraid you will not be
able to visit again.
Why am I being punished?
Did I deserve this cruelty?
Did I hurt someone as I am now hurt?
Did he?
All'I wanted was a husband and family!
To be with the one I loved
in a quiet place to call home.
Then you would have been unsuited to life
in the palace at Winchester, Ecgwynn.
Which is why this has all come to pass.
- Stop staring at me.
- I'm not staring.
I'm admiring your appetite.
Does death make you hungry?
- Have they found Aethelred?
- Yes.
Good. And where has
that little turd hidden himself?
He's in East Anglia.
He has attacked farms there
and many Danish settlers were killed.
There is no way that fool outwitted us.
It sickens me to say he has.
No...
This was not his doing, but ours.
He thought we were in Irland,
that there would be no reprisals!
We have let this happen, Cnut!
Then we must prevail now.
Farmers and their families
die in war. It's just the way of things.
Danish settlers, Saxon children...
they pay the price.
Besides, if Aethelred
has left his people undefended,
they will be easier to slaughter,
and slaughter will bring Edward sooner.
I knew it! I said this!
I said Cnut was trying to trick us!
- What of Lord Aethelred? Is he dead?
- I will try to find out.
Call off the coronation.
Send men to Aegelesburg to retake it.
No, do not call off
the ceremony...
You cannot
leave the Mercians to their doom.
By the sounds of things,
we're too late.
Send men... you must!
What they did to humiliate the Ealdormen,
Lord King! It must be avenged!
- Lord King...
- They are men of honor, men of my blood!
We should not act in haste.
- Maybe Aethelred's right...
- Edward, you must not delay.
Enough!
I will decide how to respond
to this affront and when!
Not you, nor you,
nor you will set the terms.
And certainly not Cnut.
Hard to tell!
Maybe 40 helmets!
He has put all his men on the ramparts
to make it look like he has more.
- He was always a cunning one.
- Still two against one.
- We're twice as good.
- Yeah, keep saying it, it becomes true.
We don't need to slaughter 'em all,
just hold 'em off.
Lord, the real fight
will be you against Aelfric.
Tell me, Beocca...
is it the right time?
I'm not leading men to defeat?
You are not leading men to defeat.
The fight will be furious. Men will fall.
But I would not encourage you,
if I thought you would lose.
Feel the air here, Uhtred.
Feel its cold breath.
This is the air
that you and I were born to breathe.
We're meant to be here.
Let us see if my blood runs thick...
if the signal comes.
- Do you know what that is?
- It's a fort.
Beating heart of this land
they called Bernicia.
Bebbanburg.
The lord who resides here is volatile,
SO be on your guard.
- What if he does not welcome us?
- Then we will not be welcomed home.
And we will be forced to sail to Frisia
to sell your backside in return for food.
It is only monks, Lord.
Aethelred's errand boys.
Let's see how desperate they are
for my holy treasures.
Greetings to Lord Aelfric of Bebbanburg.
I am Brother lestyn.
We are sent by Aethelred of Mercia
to make a trade.
Um, you can turn back.
I've decided I cannot bear to part
with so dear a treasure.
Lord Aethelred will offer a good price.
I put no price on holy relics,
nor should you.
The legacy of my forebears
cannot be measured in silver.
Then might we at least rest
the night here, Lord?
The road has been long.
Perhaps we could discuss the trade.
We are not a lodging house!
Your master has sent you
on a pointless errand.
If Aethelred wishes to reunite
the relics of the beloved saint,
he'll have to fight me for them,
sword to sword.
Lord!
I am but a young man,
but since my childhood, I have heard
that Bebbanburg
was the greatest fortress in the north.
And that its true lord was a man of honor
and great reputation.
Well, who does not take
to a little flattery?
Please, Lord.
I've traveled many weeks
just to admire it.
Reject our plea
to sell us your riches, but...
do not deny my boyhood dream.
Well, I am generous
and a loyal servant to the Church.
So, um...
you are welcome.
Put them in the slave quarters.
Stop looking impressed.
You will push up the price.
- Has he given the signal?
- Lord.
Nothing.
Did you see that?
There, look!
It's the signal!
Move your arses!
Follow us along the rocks.
The rest of you stay here
until I call for the ship.
Which one do you want?
That one.
All yours.
Halt!
Do not move!
Are you there?
Keep this way.
Backs against the wall.
Are you there?
What do we do, Lord?
Do we lift the gate?
- It's worth a try.
- Come on, lift it!
On my count, one, two, three!
Come on! Put your back into it!
Finan, stop. It's too heavy.
Move!
This is a mistake. I was lost!
- You were trying to steal away!
- I was not!
Why? Huh? Why?
Get me those oars.
In there, Osferth.
Put your back into it!
Come on! It's moving! Come on!
Can you get under it, Lord?
A little more.
Go on, Lord!
Summon all to the yard.
Get up!
Let them see how we get thieves
to tell the truth.
Go on, Lord!
Come on!
Heave! Heave!
He's got it!
He's got it! He's got it!
Yes! Yes!
- Is it a trap?
- Is it a trap we can fight our way out of?
Again, who...
do you really...
serve?
My flock and God himself!
- You, what is your mission?
- Simply to...
Must I kill another
before I get the truth?
Let the holy man go free.
He means you no harm!
This one schemes against us, Father.
He is a spy.
We move on.
Who sent you?
You can tell me.
Have the Scots allied with Aethelred?
No recognition in his eyes,
but his face... is familiar somehow.
You are an imposter...
but for whom?
Who are you?
I am Uhtred of Bebbanburg!
It is unwise to mock me.
Kill him.
- Guards...
- Silence!
- Only I shall speak!
- Get back!
Well done!
Do you know who I am?
Hm? Do you know who I am?
I am the true Lord of Bebbanburg!
And I am taking it back!
I have no fight with you.
Only this man is doomed.
Are you happy to see me, Uncle? Huh?
I have waited a lifetime to avenge myself.
I will enjoy taking my time with you! Mm?
No one else will suffer,
if you swear loyalty.
None of you are my enemies.
You are men of Bebbanburg!
And, as Lord of Bebbanburg,
I will provide for and protect you!
And this cruel shit, who has hated you
and mistreated you, will die.
I've come home!
Swear to me and you will have my oath.
Aidan... you remember me?
Who has your allegiance?
I am loyal to the true heir of Bebbanburg.
Good.
Bear witness all,
the true heir of Bebbanburg!
Who are you, boy?
Wihtgar, son of Aelfric.
Very much alive and back at Bebbanburg
as flesh and blood.
And I could kill you with this arrow
in a heartbeat.
You can try.
The arrow would miss.
Then you know nothing
of the weapons of the desert.
Put down the bow.
Put down the bow!
You've lost everything, Osbert!
I won't tell you again, put down the bow!
A son does not always love a father.
Learn from that, fool.
Now, who's with me?
Who is with Wihtgar of Bebbanburg?
Get ready!
Get ready to fight!
http://hiqve.com/